<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="56"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Connection
                           Issue:
Q3 2018
  Selection of industry features for the professional adviser
 Munny for old rope - how robo-advice can help you monetise your client base. Andrew Fay, Munnypot
 Also inside:
The future of advice. Garrett Harbron, Vanguard Europe
Introducing Cazenove Capital’s Discretionary Fund Management Service.
Simon Cooper, Cazenove Capital
›› How planning a wedding compares to the FCA Report. Steve Nelson, the lang cat ›› The perils of passive investing. Henry Wilson, LGT Vestra
›› Embracing the MiFID II storm. Davinia Rogers, Verbatim Asset Management
›› Rfolios - our best ideas. Geoff Mills, RSMR
›› Is the gig up for western inflation? Anthony Gillham, Quilter Investors
›› The evolving pensions/retirement market post-freedoms. Matt Ward, AKG
›› Win, lose or withdraw? Andrzej Pioch, Legal & General Investment Management
  Features Synaptic Risk Rating table inside. Plus:
• Synaptic Analyser: Cashflow modelling is now the rule • This article may contain nuts /
                Sustainable investment
• New! Introducing the new Synaptic 1-10 ATRQ • Talking ‘bout my generation / Protection
 • Asset Allocation – unlocking the value in advice
                   A view from the other side...
Alastair Mundy, Investec Asset Management
                ]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                         Our best ideas for your clients
  The RSMR Discretionary Portfolio Service - Rfolios - has been created to deliver improved investor outcomes, simplify the advice process and enhance the overall client experience.
 We recognise that  nancial advisers continue to be challenged in an evolving regulatory environment. Selecting and managing investments requires specialised knowledge and time to maintain suitable client portfolios.
The RSMR Discretionary Portfolios can be mapped to match existing risk pro ling tools with choice and  exibility being key for the investor and adviser alike.
Offering a choice of income and growth and SRI options with active and passive strategies all the portfolios are backed by RSMR’s unrivalled experience and track record in supporting UK advisory  rms.
For more information, call us on 01535 656 555 or email us at enquiries@rsmgroup.co.uk
Important Notice
This is intended for investment professionals and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons. Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments and any income from them can fall as well as rise, is not guaranteed and your clients may get back less that they invest. RSMR Portfolio Services Limited is a limited company registered in England and Wales under Company number 07137872. Registered of ce at Number 20, Rye eld Business Park, Belton Road, Silsden BD20 0EE. RSMR Portfolio Services Limited is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority under number 788854. © RSMR 2018. RSMR is a registered Trademark.
Number 20, Rye eld Business Park, Belton Road, Silsden BD20 0EE
01535 656 555 | enquiries@rsmgroup.co.uk | rsmr.co.uk
      ]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                              The future of advice 4 Garrett Harbron,Vanguard Europe
Munny for old rope - how robo-advice can 6 help you monetise your client base
Andrew Fay, Munnypot
How planning a wedding compares to the 8 FCA Interim Platform Report
Steve Nelson, the lang cat
Introducing Cazenove Capital’s 10 Discretionary Fund Management Service
Simon Cooper, Cazenove Capital
The perils of passive investing 12 Henry Wilson, LGT Vestra
Embracing the MiFID II storm 14 Davinia Rogers, Verbatim Asset Management
Rfolios - our best ideas 16 Geoff Mills, RSMR
A view from the other side 18 Alastair Mundy, Investec Asset Management
Is the gig up for western in ation? 20 Anthony Gillham, Quilter Investors
Escalating trade tensions: time to worry? 22 Jane Davies, HSBC Global Strategy Portfolios
Real assets - an introduction to an 24 alternative solution
Mayank Markanday, Sarah Ackland, Architas
Making a success of succession planning 26 John Husselbee, Liontrust
The evolving pensions/retirement market 28 post-freedoms.
Matt Ward, AKG
Win, lose or withdraw? 30 Andrzej Pioch, Legal & General Investment Management
Cash ow modelling is now the rule, 32 not the exception
Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software Limited
This article may contain nuts - Sustainable 34 and Responsible Investment
Paul Quarendon, Synaptic Software Limited
Talking ‘bout my Generation...Z 36 Paul Quarendon, Synaptic Software Limited
Asset allocation - unlocking the value in 40 advice
Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software Limited
Synaptic Risk Table 44
When open architecture became a thing, and the industry-changing advantages of working with wraps started to become apparent, the concept of the Central Investment Proposition came into its own. There was concern from the regulator at the time that clients may be ‘shoe- horned’ into investment vehicles that weren’t necessarily optimal on a client by client basis.
But by focussing on suitability, the gaze
shifted away from the need to prove that each investment solution was a tailored suit, and the FSA (as they were then) con rmed that
an independent adviser could have all their clients on a single platform. Central Investment Propositions, or CIPs, are built through client segmentation and allow  rms to streamline processes and standardise advice. Most providers/asset managers are seeking to align with  rms as part of their CIP.
Going back to those years where the FSA was developing its thinking on suitability and the use of platforms, celebrated technical expert and ambassador for all things Welsh, Mr Chris Thomas, encouraged us to approach research and due diligence in relation to ‘Investment Pathways’. Indeed, most of our customers have developed their research and due diligence around the concept of these pathways – whether full DFM/DFM MPS/Model Portfolios/ Bespoke Portfolios or Multi-asset funds.
Our development road map is being  nalised as we consider our role in the coming years, supporting the independent advice  rms of the future. We are clear that the focus of our development will be around better supporting advisers accessing their CIPs for research and due diligence purposes. Synaptic Research provides a unique resource in the industry - we constantly collect and verify much of the data that populates our tools. As a result, the asset allocations that produce our ratings are reliable, the pricing shapes that are accessed within our Analyser and Comparator tools are precise, and our whole-of-market product data is similarly accurate.
We have also been introduced to what
we think is an extraordinary proposition, Munnypot (see p6). We are gaining inspiration and help from them to establish a modern, digital foundation to our own proposition.We like the fact that the principals are ex-heads
of IFA businesses. We’d be happy to introduce any of our customers, who may be considering automated advice as an extension of their own proposition, to Munnypot.
Eric Armstrong
Editor
   Contact Details
Synaptic Software Limited
Fusion 1, Parkway, Solent Business Park Whiteley, Hampshire PO15 7AA
Sales: 0800 783 4477
To sign up for Connection magazine visit
www.synaptic.co.uk
All editorial or advertising enquiries should be directed to:
Eric Armstrong
eric.armstrong@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882994
Sarah Miller
marketing@synaptic.co.uk 0800 783 4477
If you no longer wish to receive a copy of this publication, please email marketing@synaptic.co.uk
The Connection magazine is published by Synaptic Software Limited. The views expressed throughout do not necessarily re ect the views of Synaptic or any other party af liated to Synaptic, and no liability can be assumed for the accuracy or completeness of the content, nor should any of the content be used as the sole basis of any advice offered or received.
Content is offered on an information only basis, and intended only for an audience of professional advisers regulated by the FCA. Content is published with all rights reserved and any reproduction of content, wholly or in part, can be made with the written permission of the publishers. This applies to all forms of the magazine - digital and print, and any part thereof.
 Investment pathways
 3
CONTENTS
]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  4
  The future of advice
 Garrett Harbron | Head of UK Wealth Planning | Vanguard Europe
These days we are not short of headlines warning of the impacts of technological disruption in the advice industry. There is no escaping the fact that technology has created less costly ways to deliver advice with a broader reach.
Many of the foundational tools of  nancial planning, such as rebalancing and portfolio construction, can now be done by algorithms in a more ef cient, scalable manner. Some have gone so far as to predict so-called “robo-advice” propositions will spell the end of human  nancial advisers.
We could choose to buy into the doom-and- gloom, seeing technology as a threat and automation taking away jobs. However, there is another choice. We can instead choose to see technology as an opportunity, embracing the automation it brings. Why risk becoming Blockbuster if you can choose to be Net ix? Far from being automated away, at Vanguard we believe the job of an adviser is very much here to stay. However, the day-to-day tasks an adviser performs are likely to change.
This has implications for the future of the traditional advice model.
Vanguard has conducted extensive research into the advice market in the US, leading to a number of publications in 2017 and 2018,
including The Evolution of Adviser’s Alpha: From Portfolios to People which is currently available in the UK. We have now leveraged this experience to conduct a major study, the Vanguard UK Adviser-Client Survey. We have directly interviewed 300 practising advisers and wealth managers, and 1,000 advised clients, focusing on what advice in the future will look like in the UK.
Our starting point is to step back and look at the future of jobs in general. Our research into the impact of technology on jobs suggests the tasks most likely to be automated away are those that are basic and repetitive in nature1. On the other hand, “advanced” tasks - those that rely on things like creativity, strategising, and maintaining relationships – are uniquely human and tend to be much more resilient to automation.
While we cannot predict what technology will look like in the future, if other industries are any guide we can feel con dent that the way advisers can add value will change. Routine
tasks will likely be automated away, leaving only those tasks that can be considered uniquely human.
One example of a uniquely human task advisers perform is behavioural coaching. While often overlooked, there is signi cant value in providing a client with peace of mind.
Acting as a behavioural coach, advisers can prevent clients taking on excessive risk, chasing returns and generally making decisions that harm their chances of investment success.
However, it will be hard to prevent a client from selling out in the heat of a  nancial crisis if it is the  rst time you are having that conversation. Behavioural coaching is only effective if clients are prepared in advance for the challenges that may come their way and, as the responses of our US Advised Investor Insights survey show, have trust in the relationship.
1See The Evolution of Adviser’s Alpha: From Portfolios to People for a more in depth examination of this topic. www.vanguard.co.uk/adviser/adv/ articles/research-commentary/topical-insights/evolution-vanguard-advisors-alpha.jsp]
 ]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 5
  Many of the foundational tools of  nancial planning, such as rebalancing and portfolio construction, can now done by algorithms in a more ef cient, scalable manner.
  Source: Vanguard
Not all advice can be automated
So, what determines trust? Interestingly, more than half of survey respondents placed the most weight on drivers of trust that are emotional in nature. Clients selected “being the client’s advocate” and “acting in the client’s best interest” as the most important drivers. While the functional and ethical aspects (in short, what advisers do and how they do it) are still essential, it was surprising to  nd that emotions play a greater role than both of those combined.
Unfortunately there is no shortcut to building trust. Trust is built over time. Indeed, our research found higher levels of trust were associated with longer relationships, while
a perceived lack of attention and time was the main motivation for switching advisers. Our US survey suggests clients want what automation cannot provide – a relationship.
Rede ning their value proposition to one of holistic wealth management, advisers will be best placed to compete with the challenges
automation may bring. For US investors, in
a world where time is of increasingly short supply,  nding ways to spend more time with clients will be paramount for success.
We are interested to see if this translates across the pond. What do UK investors value in an adviser-client relationship? Trust means different things to different people – will it look different for UK investors compared to their US counterparts? Do they place the same value on the emotional aspects? This summer we have set out to try and answer these questions and more, conducting a survey focused on UK advisers and advised- investors.
Preliminary  ndings from the advisers and investors surveyed so far here in the UK appear to suggest similarities. As one client put it, “I want a close relationship, but I don’t want my IFA to be a friend... they need to
be a trusted professional, like a GP”. While the ideal relationship may not be radically different to what is currently on offer, initial
responses indicate clients are looking for more empathy and proactivity in their partnerships. However, this will be easier said than done. As one adviser we interviewed said, “There is no manual for how to ask life questions...”.
Nor is there any manual for succeeding in a world of increasing automation. We hope, however, that the  ndings of our survey can at least help point advisers in the right direction. We’ll be sharing our  ndings at our Adviser Symposiums this autumn
(see www.vanguard.co.uk/advisers). We hope you can join us.
Investment risk Information
The value of investments, and the income from them, may fall or rise and investors may get back less than they invested. Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future results.
Important Information
This document is directed at professional investors in the UK only, and should not
be distributed to or relied upon by retail investors. It is for educational purposes only and is not a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell investments. The information in this document does not constitute legal, tax or investment advice. You must not, therefore, rely on the content of this document when making any investment decisions. Issued by Vanguard Asset Management Limited which is authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority.
 ]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  6
 Munny for old rope – how robo-advice can help you monetise your client base
 Andrew Fay | CEO and co-founder of Munnypot
Anyone who has had the privilege of receiving traditional, face-to-face  nancial advice will agree it is an indispensable service.
 IFAs are excellent at delivering professional, personal and appropriate advice to their clients. Advisers have a history of building strong, long-term customer relationships, building up trust over time and becoming essential to the lives of high net worth
clients.
But the  nancial advice market is changing
• Cost of advice is growing – The cost of offering traditional advice is growing due to regulatory requirements (GDPR, MiFiD II, the IDD) and this trend is set to continue.
• It’s not just millennials – Savers with larger investments are actually the most willing to adopt automated advice for at least part of their investment portfolio (see Figure 2).
• £35bn AUM will be robo-advised in the UK alone by 2022* – A new wave of disruptive advisers is  owing into this sector.
1
1
Traditional IFAs need to compete in this space in order to survive.
These market dynamics create a challenging environment for the adviser community. However, they also present a signi cant opportunity.
• Asset owners of the future expect a digital experience – Future generations of high net worth individuals expect digital alternatives to traditional models and are willing to pay for automated advice (see Figure 1). Unless advisers  nd a way to service these customers, in our view they will lose out to digital disruptors. This lack of certainty in the future is impacting the value of IFA businesses today.
3
2
2
  0%
Figure 1.
Willingness to invest more than £10,000 using
5a%utomated  nancial advice by wealth level 0%
28%
5%
0%
5%
0%
13%
£1,000 or more
15%
£5,000 or more
19%
£30,000 or more
 Source: YouGov 23-24 January 2017, Deloitte analysis in 2017 Deloitte report: "The next frontier: The future of automated financial advice in the UK". Samples: GB adults with more than £1,000 in savings and investments (excluding pensions and property wea
£100,000 or more
 ]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 7
 51%
46%
43%
43%
32%
20%
37%
23%
36% 35%
35%
63%
63%
 55%
59%
44%
24%
21%
 Simple financial planning Investing £11,000 Investing £80 monthly pension Finding life insurance
18-24 25-34 35-44 45-54 55+
contribution
     Source:YouGov23-24January2017,Deloitteanalysisin2017Deloittereport:"Thenextfrontier:The futureofautomated financial advice in the UK". Samples range from 50-793. Excludes at-retirement due to small samples
 In our view, tomorrow’s advice market will look very different to today’s. If you are looking to expand your offering, decrease costs, increase revenues and keep up with the times, please get in touch.
  Figure 2.
Willingness to pay for automated advice by age
70% 60% 50% 40% 30% 20% 10%
0%
 The way we see it, advisers have three options
1. Build a low-cost advice offering in-house
But creating an in-house automated product from scratch requires signi cant capital, technology and time, inevitably detracting valuable resources away from core business.
2. Direct clients to a self-service platform
Advisers spend years learning how to provide appropriate  nancial advice. We would never expect someone to diagnose their own health, so why do we expect people to manage their own wealth? Moreover, once a customer is entrenched in self-service management of their assets, it is extremely dif cult to bring them back to the traditional advice model.
3. PartnerwithaFintechtooffera low cost, engaging,  nancial advice product
With Munnypot IFAs can provide automated, yet personalised  nancial advice at low marginal cost with own branding
A partnership with Munnypot has many bene ts for IFAs
• Provide genuine  nancial advice – Unlike many robo-advice products in the market that offer predominantly guidance-based, execution-only platforms, our product
perfectly complements the service already provided by IFAs by producing a customised suitability report for every client. It even provides customers with
an automated recommendation of what product to invest through: an ISA, a GIA or a JISA.
• Focus on high value clients – By using Munnypot for simpler transactions, advisers can reduce the cost of existing clients and focus face-to-face advice on higher value conversations. Attract and monetise future generations, whilst always maintaining
a direct client relationship, using the
fully automated, simple, conversational, goal-based interface to engage with those unfamiliar with investing.
• Ongoing monitoring and advice as standard – Munnypot provides ongoing monitoring of clients’ goals and will  ag when investment performance is off-track. The system provides automated follow-up advice on what action should be taken to resolve the issue.
• We want to help IFAs thrive in this rapidly changing marketplace – Today, Munnypot is offered as a white-label solution for simple investments. Tomorrow, Munnypot, and products like ours will be able to advise customers on insurance products and how best to plan for retirement.
For more information on Munnypot or to arrange a demo, please email andrew.fay@munnypot.com or contact our of ces on 01293 224 281.
Andy has nearly 30 years’ experience in  nancial services. He started his career
as a  nancial adviser, before co-founding Cavanagh Group. He successfully sold Cavanagh to Close Brothers in 2011, where he continued to act as Head of Wealth Management.
Important Information
Munnypot is a trading name of Munnypot Limited which is an Appointed Representative of Resolution Compliance Limited which is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. FRN 574048.
*Source: https://www.statista.com/outlook/337/156/robo- advisors/united-kingdom?currency=gbp
 ]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  8
           How planning a wedding compares to the FCA Interim Platform Report
 Steve Nelson | Head of research | the lang cat
Well, it doesn’t actually. Sorry. It’s just that yours truly is writing this article on his last day at work, three days before getting married. As a result of the FCA paper landing in the same week, my head is a cold soup of the two. Hydrangea colours mixed with model portfolio risk bandings. Catering quantities coupled with platform switching issues. It’s a dizzying mix.
It’s funny though, despite me writing this in the present tense, by the time you read this the wedding will be over, and everyone and his dog will have had their say on the platform study. Writing something for publication is a curious form of time travel in that respect.
In many ways, for reasons I’ll get onto in a moment, I wish the FCA had the same level of awareness when compiling its latest tome. In mid-July last year, chances are if you work in platforms that you were having a good read of the FCA’s Investment Platforms Market Study Terms of Reference paper.
Fast forward 12 months (Great Scott!)
and here we go again. This time, it’s the Interim Report, together with eight annex documents totalling a sturdy 400 pages of output if you can’t resist totalling these kind of things up. Yet, despite the weight of work
that’s gone into it, I’m left frustrated by several aspects.
What was the question again?
Last year’s terms of reference posed two headline questions covering the topics to
be explored. Firstly, “How do platforms
and similar  rms compete on the price and quality of the services and products they offer and the products over which they have in uence?” And secondly, “Do platform and similar  rms’ investment solutions offer investors value for money?”. Sadly, neither of these questions comes close to being answered in the interim report.
Can everyone please board via platform one?
One of the real positives of this exercise is the depth of customer research that
accompanied the project. The research, led by NMG, surveyed approximately 3,000 end-customers (you know, those awkward people who fund our industry) on their views of platform usage, and serves as a pertinent reminder of some of the real issues facing customers.
This consumer research highlights just how (understandably) different the advised and non-advised segments are. Which begs the question as to why the FCA has lumped two completely different markets together in one paper?
For example, asking advised clients their main reasons for using an online investment platform alongside non-advised clients is jarring when surely Les Dennis’ top answer is “Because my adviser told me to”. We feel that a more structured, differentiated approach
  ]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 9
            This consumer research highlights just how (understandably) different the advised and non-advised segments are. Which begs the question as to why the FCA has lumped two completely different markets together in one paper?
to the two markets for the next wave of the project would be of real bene t.
Secondly, there is no real effort to offer an issues-based segmentation of the individual platforms within the market. You’re either ‘a platform’ or you’re not. When, as I’ve covered in previous articles, these beasts are far from the same. The issues facing an adviser who ‘owns’ their tech proposition off-platform and uses, say, a Transact or a Nucleus or an Ascentric are fundamentally different to the business models of, say, Intrinsic users on Old Mutual Wealth. Which leads me onto...
Where is the vertically integrated market? Behind the sofa?
When your initial terms of reference have such a clear focus on value for money and the in uence of price and quality on client propositions, then to pay little more than lip service to vertically integrated propositions (where there have been signi cant questions raised over the value for money of some of the solutions) feels very, very odd to us.
Stop moaning about things that aren’t there
Indeed. What we DO have is a study that has concluded that we have  ve groups of consumers for whom the FCA reckons competition between platforms is not working well:
1. Those who would bene t from switching but can  nd it dif cult.
The ease with which both advised and non- advised clients can move between platforms touches on lots of important subjects, such as exit fees, share classes and transfer times. Again, we feel the dichotomy of the advised versus D2C markets is a little lost here but progress on transfer times can only be a good thing for the reputation of the industry.
2. Thosewhoarepricesensitivebutcan  nd shopping around dif cult.
This one is aimed at the direct space, and whilst we would applaud moves to make it easier to shop around, in a world where many direct consumers either don’t think they pay platform charges or don’t know, perhaps more work is needed on clarity of charges disclosure  rst.
3. Thosewhousemodelportfolios.The risks and expected returns of model portfolios with similar risk labels are unclear and can lead to confusion about how much risk they are facing.
That consumers, mainly using D2C platforms, using these model portfolios and suggested multi-asset funds may have the wrong idea about the risk/return levels they face also feels like an area in need of improved disclosure and clarity of information, especially when investment performance is a far bigger driver of customer outcomes than saving a few percentage points on a platform charge.
4. Those who have large cash balances on direct platforms. They may not know they are missing out on investment returns and/or that they are paying charges.
We have mentioned this a number of times
– the combination of low interest rates and platform charges means that if you are using a platform to “invest” in cash, you are probably getting net negative returns as a result.
5. Thosewhonolongerhaveanadviser and are still on an advised platform but may face higher charges and lower levels of service (referred to as ‘orphan clients’).
Platforms have always had a TCF obligation here, but it looks like the bar may be raised. The suggested requirement for platforms to check that clients are receiving an advised service is also one to watch.
So, there we have it. De nitely a mixed bag and we await the  nal recommendations with bated breath. Until then, it’s back to the last- minute wedding prep. I might weave some platform analogies into the speech. I reckon that’s a winner, don’t you? Hello?
Are you still there?
Visit www.langcat nancial.co.uk for more from Steve and the rest of the lang cats.
  ]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  10
  Introducing Cazenove Capital’s Discretionary Fund Management Service
 Simon Cooper | Business Development Director | Cazenove Capital
With a 200-year history of growing and protecting clients’ wealth, and access to the signi cant resources of the Schroders Group, Cazenove Capital is ideally placed to oversee your clients’ investments.
Cazenove Capital traces its origins back to the early years of the 19th century. It has served its clients through the tumults of war and profound social, industrial and technological change. Five years ago Cazenove Capital came together with another great family business, Schroders - ushering in a new chapter of growth, where even more skill and resource could be harnessed for the bene t of its clients. Today Cazenove Capital is one of Britain’s biggest wealth managers, trusted by thousands of individuals and charities to safeguard and grow their assets.
Your client comes  rst
Cazenove Capital has been working with  nancial advisers for more than 15 years.
We offer broad support including regular meetings with a dedicated portfolio manager, comprehensive reporting services and digital valuation tools, giving both you and your client instant access to online valuations. But whether you are a small practice or national  rm, we are respectful of your relationship with your client: how you choose to work with
us will be led by you. We will support your brand.
Portfolios are tailored according to your clients’ risk pro le and goals. They can
also be tailored to re ect individual clients’ environmental and social values. Once an asset allocation strategy has been agreed,
we will ensure it adapts appropriately as your clients’ circumstances change and in line with your advice.
Investment process
Cazenove Capital aims to deliver real growth with an eye to costs and tax ef ciency.
Our established central investment approach rests on a careful reading of the business cycle and an understanding of the impact this has on different asset classes. Risk is then controlled through a highly diversi ed allocation.
The chart (right) reveals our view on where major world markets are currently positioned in the cycle.
As a result of this view we are today tilted toward cash and alternative investments (including absolute return funds and structured products) and are neutral overall on equities. Within our equities allocation, we favour Japanese and emerging markets.
  ]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 11
  Cazenove Capital traces its origins back to the early years of the 19th century. It has served its clients through the tumults of war and profound social, industrial and technological change.
We have a neutral position on European and US equities – and we are currently slightly negative on UK equities, given the fall-off in growth and uncertainties arising from Brexit. A summary of our investment team’s views across asset classes and currencies is updated and published regularly.
appropriate potential holdings, wherever these are managed.
Where appropriate, we make signi cant
use of alternative investments, such as absolute return funds and structured products, to which your clients might not otherwise have access. Cazenove Capital believes that companies have the ability to enhance their long-term performance through an understanding of the environmental,
social and governance issues affecting their business. An awareness of these issues enables companies to potentially mitigate risks as
well as realise opportunities. Companies that combine good governance and corporate responsibility will tend to deliver long-term shareholder value over time.
Our other services
Cazenove Capital offers banking services including deposit and current accounts
for existing clients. In addition, we offer short-term loans secured against clients’ portfolios or properties. These are individually underwritten and can offer advisers and
their clients a valuable planning opportunity - especially where a clients’ age or income pro le makes them ineligible for mainstream mortgage products.
Our inheritance tax (IHT) portfolio service offers a further planning opportunity for clients seeking to mitigate death duties. The portfolio comprises investments in companies which qualify for Business Property Relief.
Under current rules, these investments become exempt from inheritance tax after they have been held for two years. By contrast, gifts or transfers are not wholly exempt from IHT until seven years have passed. With our IHT Portfolio Service, clients continue to control and have access to their investments which, if held within an ISA, are not subject to other forms of tax.
Unusually within the wealth management industry we welcome clients who are
US citizens or who have links to the US. Increasingly complex tax reporting and other regulatory requirements have made this group dif cult to serve. Our specialist Americas Team, however, is fully able and committed to meeting their needs. The team is among the small number of UK-based operations to be registered by the US regulator, the Securities and Exchange Commission.
For more information about Cazenove Capital’s Discretionary Fund Management Service, contact Simon Cooper at simon.cooper@cazenovecapital.com or on 020 7658 1343.
Disclaimer: This article is issued by Cazenove Capital, which is part of the Schroders Group and is a trading name of Schroder
& Co. Limited. Registered of ce at 1 London Wall Place, London EC2Y 5AU. Authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority and the Prudential Regulation Authority.
 We offer broad support including regular meetings
with a dedicated portfolio manager, comprehensive reporting services and digital valuation tools giving both you and your client instant access to online valuations.
 In creating portfolios we can draw on the resources of the wider Schroders Group,
with its global network of analysts and regional and sector specialists. But our fund manager selection team is not constrained to Schroders’ own stable of funds: it looks across the market to identify the most attractive and
 ]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  12
  The perils of passive investing
 Henry Wilson | Assistant Investment Manager, MPS | LGT Vestra
Huge swathes of investor capital have been allocated to passive strategies over the past decade as investors have feasted on the abundance of liquidity provided by central banks and the continual desire for products with lower fees.
 In fact, according to reports by JP Morgan1
and Bank of America Merrill Lynch2, Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs) now account for circa 25% of all trading volumes in the United States, and around 90% of trading volume is now driven by ‘non-human’ or ‘non-discretionary’ investors. Examples include High Frequency traders,
ETFs, trackers, algorithmic trading strategies, rules-based quant, and so on. In other words, only 10% of trading volumes actually originate from discretionary trades by investors. But why does this obsession with ETFs matter?
Well, performance for one hasn’t been as strong as you may imagine, particularly
when you compare Traditional Index Funds (TIFs) with ETFs. The founder of Vanguard, Jack Bogle, recently shared his analysis of dollar-weighted investor returns with the investment magazine Barron’s3. The research shows that from 2005 to 2017, the average investor return from TIFs was 8.4%, whereas for ETFs, it was 5.5%. If ETF performance is so much worse than TIFs then one might ask – “what is the point?”
Volatility exacerbated
The marginal buyer or seller drives the price of a good and, in this case, a share price or index level. As a consequence, one of the fundamental issues for investors is that passive investing is indiscriminate; there is
no price discovery mechanism relating to
the underlying equity. Participants not driven by the analysis of fundamental factors are therefore responsible for share price levels. The advent of products such as Smart Beta ETFs that allow investors to invest in a speci c sector or style means that when markets are going up, money  ows freely into crowded assets that are trading at expensive multiples. Then when markets subsequently correct, investors (often retail) withdraw their money and sell at the bottom, creating a cascade effect. The effect of this ever-growing wall of passive money could mean that future bubbles could be bigger, and troughs could be deeper, at least temporarily.
Since 2008, yield compression in conventional low risk income assets such as Gilts, Treasuries and Cash has forced investors into higher
risk or income producing strategies such
as selling Chicago Board Option Exchange (CBOE) Volatility Index (VIX) options or buying inverse VIX ETFs. Selling VIX options to generate income or yield has been compared to picking up stones in front of a steam train. We only need to look at the VIX blow up from February this year where many investors lost the total value of their short volatility position in a matter of hours. This kind of occurrence is a cautionary tale of the risks of investing in complex levered products.
The “liquidity lobster trap”
Another issue that we are wary of is the liquidity mismatch that could impact investors in the event of a market stress event. Firstly, ETFs are vehicles that are priced and trade continuously, yet invest in assets that often cannot provide daily liquidity. Investing in assets with poor liquidity can
be like a “lobster trap”; very easy to get into
 ]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 13
  We expect to see an increase in volatility in markets and as such, we believe that it is prudent to invest in active managers and at the very least, hold assets that you understand and have ample liquidity.
but impossible to get out when you need to escape. History has shown us that liquidity, in the  xed income space in particular, can dry up (as witnessed during the Global Financial Crisis), and most commonly for sectors with the lowest levels of liquidity such as emerging market debt and High Yield.
Another issue that investors may encounter is that investors holding synthetic ETFs (ETFs that rely on derivatives such as swaps to execute its investment strategy instead of physically owning the stock) may  nd that the return pro le of their ETF is somewhat different to the underlying index, due to either replication or composition or other market factors. Daily rebalancing and compounding on a leveraged ETF could result in a negative return, despite the fact that the underlying index is up over the investment horizon. This happened in 2008 for many investors who were short the market.
Finally, investors in synthetic ETFs expose themselves to the risk that one of the derivative counterparties defaults. Synthetic ETFs are popular because they frequently have a lower tracking error and are sometimes cheaper than physically replicated ETFs. However, it is not uncommon for individuals to underestimate, or even misunderstand,
this counterparty and collateralisation risk, ultimately resulting in the potential loss of all the initial investment.
It’s not hard to understand why ETFs and passive products have been so popular since 2009, particularly as markets have continued
to push higher through a combination of share buybacks, multiple expansion and for the large part, low volatility. However, betting on a repeat of the last nine years is a bet that we are unwilling to make, particularly
as central banks begin to batten down the hatches and embark on part two of the most extraordinary money experiment in history (transitioning from Quantitative Easing to Quantitative Tightening). The taper tantrum of 2013 demonstrated the dif cult task that Central Banks have in taking liquidity out of the system.
Looking forward, we expect to see an increase in volatility in markets and as such, we believe that it is prudent to invest in active managers and at the very least, hold assets that you understand and have ample liquidity.
Consequently, in the LGT Vestra MPS portfolios, we only hold funds that we have researched, and we try to avoid investments that may encounter liquidity issues. It is for this reason that we sold our exposure to open-ended property vehicles in 2016 prior to the Brexit referendum and it is also why we are cognisant of the risks posed by holding funds that have an elevated percentage of unlisted assets. Holding that jazzy 3X Levered Smart Beta ETF might be popular with clients but when the market drops 20% it may not look quite so impressive after all.
For more information, please visit lgtvestra.com
Important information
LGT Vestra LLP is authorised and regulated
by the Financial Conduct Authority. Our regulation details are set out in the FCA register: Firm Reference No: 471048. Registered in England and Wales: OC329392. Registered of ce: 14 Cornhill, London, EC3V 3NR. This article is for information purposes only and is intended for professional  nancial advisers only. The wording contained in this document is not to be construed as an offer, advice, invitation or solicitation to enter into any  nancial obligation, activity or promotion of any kind. Any information herein is given in good faith, but is subject to change without notice and may not be accurate and complete for your purposes. This document is not intended for distribution to, or use by, any individual or entities in any jurisdiction where such distribution would be contrary to the laws of that jurisdiction or subject LGT Vestra LLP to any registration requirements. Investors should be aware that past performance is not an indication of future performance, the value of investments and the income derived from them may  uctuate and you may not receive back the amount you originally invested.
1 https://www.cnbc.com/2017/06/13/death-of-the-human-investor- just-10-percent-of-trading-is-regular-stock-picking-jpmorgan- estimates.html
2 Equity & Strategy Focus Point: The ETF-ization of the S&P 500, Bank of America Merrill Lynch, 2017
3 https://www.barrons.com/articles/jack-bogles-battle-1526674385
  ]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  14
  Embracing the MiFID II storm
 Davinia Rogers | Sales Director | Verbatim Asset Management
When the Markets in Financial Instruments Directive II (MiFID II) hit the UK  nancial services industry earlier this year, it brought a whole raft
of multiple regulatory implications to the  nancial planning landscape. MiFID II builds on the original Directive, with the aim of further strengthening investor protection, and carries a heightened focus on the key elements of suitability and transparency.
Whilst these are principles we stand behind, transitioning the theory into practice has proved to be challenging for many advisers. With this in mind, how can you ensure
that the MiFID II regulatory storm acts as the wind beneath your wings, rather than blowing your house down? In this article, I will explore the potential investment solutions which can help you to overcome the challenges of MiFID II, and provide an enhanced service to your clients.
The starting line
Whether you outsource your investment strategies to a discretionary fund manager, or simply choose to implement your investment strategy through an advisory capacity, the MiFID II Directive requires that you demonstrate client suitability and risk alignment throughout your centralised investment process (CIP). Implementing a de ned process for selecting investment
strategies allows you to demonstrate clear parameters that you can, in turn, apply to your segmented clients. At the end of the day, your selected investment strategy must match your client’s appetite to risk and ability to bear loss.
So how do you select the appropriate investment solution to meet your needs
and, most importantly, the needs of your clients, and how do you implement and monitor your investment solutions in the most ef cient way? In addition, how do you monitor the performance of your investment strategies against your expectations, ensuring your strategy always aligns with your risk pro ling tool?
For an independent business model you will need to start with a review of the relevant market. Enhanced suitability questions can be used to  lter out investment options that are not suitable for your clients. You
will need to conduct a robust assessment
of your client’s attitude to risk, tolerance for loss, and ability to bear losses. Tools such as Centra (the end-to-end  nancial planning system designed by the SimplyBiz Group and powered by Defaqto) allow you to select investment strategies that are appropriate for your client, by aligning investment solutions with your client’s needs.
The MiFID II Directive requires that you document and formalise your centralised investment process. You will need to outline the processes that allow you to conduct research and planning, determine your client’s risk pro le, set recommendations and  nally compile a suitability report (which must be issued prior to the recommended product transaction being concluded). The Centra system allows you to deliver on all these process requirements and seamlessly links all elements of your CIP, whilst still
 ]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 15
  Implementing a de ned process for selecting investment strategies allows you to demonstrate clear parameters that you can, in
turn, apply to your segmented clients. At the end of the day, your selected investment strategy must match your client’s appetite to risk and ability to bear loss.
allowing you to retain your independence by using a whole of market independent tool.
With these issues in mind, which investment strategies should you consider?
1. Risk versus return: At the outset, you will need to agree your client’s attitude to risk. You will also need to manage your client’s performance expectations in relation
to their risk tolerance. In order to meet your client’s expectations, make use of an investment solution that will absolutely align to your risk pro ling tool.
2. Adherence to strategic asset allocation and volatility parameters: Seek out investment solutions that adhere to the strategic asset allocation and volatility parameters of your risk pro ling tool.
Find an investment solution you can
be certain will not deviate from these parameters, and is designed to deliver to your expected risk and return consistently.
3. Fixed strategy conditions: Look for investment solutions that give you the power to set the conditions for your clients. Whether you choose an active or a multi-index strategy, select an investment solution which gives you the mandate to populate that strategic asset allocation that will, in turn, align to your risk pro ling tool.
4. Clear parameters that match your target market: Utilise investment strategies that have a proven track record of performance in line with your risk
and return expectations, fall within your strategic asset allocation and volatility parameters, and meet your expectations.
5. Reporting: Choose investment strategies that provide you with clear and transparent reporting and that allow you to demonstrate your client’s fees in relation to performance in a transparent manner.
At Verbatim Asset Management, we understand the many challenges advisers face in the management and construction of investment portfolios. With the ever changing regulatory landscape, the advisory process in today’s world has become varied and complex. We understand that it is
vital for you to  nd the best investment solution that matches your clients’ needs and  ts perfectly into your centralised investment process. We offer a range of active and passive portfolio funds, managed model portfolios and a unique discretionary management service. Our investment solutions are overseen by our Independent Investment Committee, which brings with it a wealth of knowledge and expertise
to provide governance, oversight and monitoring for all of our products.
We are proud to offer investment solutions that are designed to  t seamlessly into your investment proposition and meet your and your clients’ expectations consistently.
For more information, please email info@verbatim-am.co.uk or contact the helpdesk on 0808 12 40 007
Past performance is not a guide to future performance. Do remember that the value of an investment and the income generated from them can fall as well as rise and is not guaranteed, therefore, you may not get back the amount originally invested and potentially risk total loss of capital. The portfolios’ investments are subject to normal  uctuations and other risks inherent when investing in securities.
Verbatim Asset Management has taken due care and attention in preparing this document, which is solely for the use of professional advisers. Verbatim cannot be held responsible for any inaccuracies arising out of information detailed within and will not accept liability for any loss arising out of or in connection with its use.
  ]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  16
  Rfolios - our best ideas
 Geoff Mills | Director | RSMR
We recognise that  nancial advisers continue to be challenged
in an evolving regulatory environment. Selecting and managing investments requires specialised knowledge and time to maintain suitable client portfolios.
We have now combined our experience of working with advisers with our knowledge of funds and created ‘our best ideas’.
The RSMR Discretionary Portfolio Service
- Rfolios - has been created to deliver improved investor outcomes, simplify the advice process and enhance the overall client experience. With the ability to match existing or planned advice models, choice and  exibility are key for the investor and adviser alike.
Our portfolios rise incrementally in risk and by making use of the asset allocations we provide for you, together with back-tested risk and performance data, you can map each portfolio to whichever risk pro ling process you are using.
Offering a choice of growth, income & SRI themed portfolios with active and passive strategies, all the portfolios are backed with RSMR’s unrivalled track record.
Working alongside advisers
We work with you and for the last 14 years our personal and tailored approach has set us apart from the crowd. Working in partnership with you, we reduce any concerns and deliver improvements that bene t the end investor (your client) and your business, providing:
• More time for you to focus on growing your business and managing existing client relationships – adding to the bottom line
• Reduced administrative costs by outsourcing responsibility for investment management decisions delivering an enhanced client service
• Improved client proposition through access to a range of risk graded discretionary model portfolios – removing the risk of portfolio drift
• Reduced regulatory risks with the RSMR research team in support of your business.
Our rigorous research process
All of our portfolios are constructed using the same rigorous research processes that support our fund ratings and all the funds in the portfolios will be selected from our rated fund list. The process for putting together the portfolios can be summarised as follows:
  ]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 17
  Our portfolios rise incrementally in risk and by making use of the asset allocations we provide for you, together with back-tested risk and performance data, you can map each portfolio to whichever risk pro ling process you are using.
Our approach
We know that you may already have a risk pro ling and advice process in place and our portfolios have been set up to  t into your existing processes, allowing you to focus on the areas where you add most value, and using us to complement your skills in the others.
Research indicates that the elements where clients believe advisers add most value are fact  nding, identifying client needs and goals, assessing the clients’ appetite for
risk and the ongoing service and support (coloured blue on the diagram above).
The other parts of the advice process (coloured green) take time and expertise with many advisers taking the decision to use specialist resources to help, freeing time for them to focus their skills on the discussion with the client and generating fee income.
Asset allocation
The asset allocation has been put together with a number of aims in mind. Firstly, we’ve developed a variety of portfolio options to meet the varied needs of your clients.
Secondly, we recognise that most advisers encourage their clients to take a long term view and to avoid a reaction to each and every change in market direction. We’ve therefore focused on taking a strategic approach with each portfolio, with our eye  rmly on the 3-5 year time horizon. We will have shorter term tactical views, but these
will be expressed through the funds that we choose. In our experience, this approach provides the most suitable investment process for the majority of clients and avoids unnecessarily high portfolio turnover.
Thirdly, we have assumed that outside the lower end of the risk scale, investors would be 100% invested in cash, and outside the higher end they would be 100% invested in higher risk and less diversi ed investment strategies.
Performance reporting and support
Fund switches and portfolio rebalancing will take place automatically and you will also have the opportunity to utilise your platform of choice. We will also formally review and report on the portfolios on a quarterly basis.
We will look not just at the underlying funds, but also at the portfolios as a whole, and how they have performed (both in terms of return and risk) in comparison to the benchmark.
Detailed portfolio factsheets are available to support the portfolios, plus our reporting and quarterly newsletters for investors.
Contact us for more details on 01535 656 555 or enquiries@rsmgroup.co.uk
Important Notice
This is intended for investment professionals and should not
be relied upon by private investors or any other persons. Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments and any income from them can fall as well as rise, is not guaranteed and your clients may get back less that they invest.
RSMR Portfolio Services Limited is a limited company registered in England and Wales under Company number 07137872. Registered of ce at Number 20, Rye eld Business Park, Belton Road, Silsden BD20 0EE.
RSMR Portfolio Services Limited is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority under number 788854.
©RSMR 2018. RSMR is a registered Trademark.
   ]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  18
  A view from the other side
 Alastair Mundy | Head of Value | Investec Asset Management
‘Simple, but not easy’
Investing, and particularly contrarian investing, is often described as being ‘simple, but not easy’. The simple part is straightforward. One waits for a share price to fall, carries out some due diligence to check for any hidden nasties, checks the stock is cheap on some sensible assumptions and then buys the share. And if everything goes to plan, the shares, as they recover, will attract the attention of other investors and provide the investor with a handsome pro t.
The ‘not easy’ part is where the sweating begins. A stock only tends to fall if investors have some concerns about a company’s future.There
may be issues over a company’s indebtedness, accounting, industry exposure or some purely idiosyncratic issue and virtually all of the time
it is perfectly rational to hold these concerns. And, in many cases, history tells us it is correct to have such concerns as worst-case scenarios can often play out (of which a recent example is Carillion).
But a more dispassionate assessment of history tells us that on the whole these worst-case scenarios are a fairly rare species. They just tend to stick more in investors’ minds than those stocks which do recover.
What can often be worse than the embarrassment of holding one stock that
does very badly is holding a portfolio of stocks which, in general, are doing reasonably badly. This typically happens in markets which are in uenced by a signi cant and prolonged theme – such as the technology, media and telecoms bubble in the late 90s and the mining bubble
in the mid-noughties. At such times equity markets can become bifurcated with a group of stocks heavily in favour and the rest unloved.
We have been in one of these times over recent years. The belief that in ation will remain low for an extended period of time has seen interest rates fall to extraordinarily low levels, and this has created a number of market-wide effects that have worked against us. By reducing the discount rates that are applied to equity earnings, lower interest rates have disproportionately favoured more highly rated quality/growth stocks which have a greater proportion of their value further out in the future.
I’ve been on the wrong side of things and am seated  rmly on the naughty step. I’ve been sitting there for so long now, that I’m starting to leave an impression.
So, what to do?
There are three options. Option one is to simply capitulate – admit that the world has changed, that the old rules do not work and to embrace the dark side. Option two is to sit tight, accept one’s portfolio is signi cantly different from
the market and trust that eventually themes (however strong the story) will reverse. Option three is to break the  rst law of digging holes made famous by Dennis Healey, the Labour politician, who opined that, “if you  nd yourself in a hole, stop digging”. If the bifurcated market throws up increasingly attractive opportunities it is surely right to keep buying?
 What can often
be worse than the embarrassment of holding one stock that does very badly is holding a portfolio of stocks which, in general, are doing reasonably badly.
 ]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 19
  By reducing the discount rates that are applied to equity earnings, lower interest rates have disproportionately favoured more highly rated quality/growth stocks which have a greater proportion of their value further out in the future.
At this point, the career risk that Jeremy Grantham, founder of GMO, has often talked about becomes relevant. It stops being how long the fund manager can take the pain of underperformance and morphs into a discussion on how long the client is willing to take the pain of underperformance.
For a contrarian investor (and we are talking about a portfolio of stocks here rather than
an individual stock) the typical response
is somewhere between options 2 and 3. Continue to analyse the opportunity set and
as it becomes ever more attractive to do so, skew the portfolio more towards the cheapest stocks. However, it is probably best not to come over as too pig-headed, bloody-minded or unprepared to investigate alternative views.‘The market is obviously wrong’ rarely wins plaudits with clients on the receiving end of one’s underperformance.
Looking in the tea leaves
The psychologist will tell you at these times that to remain rational, one should actively search for those whose views oppose your own. Continually seeking solace from like-minded individuals can quickly encourage ‘con rmation bias’ – the belief that something must be right because someone else agrees with you. Clearly it is healthy to search for contrasting views, but at such times the opposition have the upper hand – they are supported by a good narrative to which a trending share price brings further validation. The contrarian, on the other hand, appears to have just conjecture – ‘what if the story reverses even though there is no sign of
it in the tea leaves’, or history – ‘something typically turns up; the market’s just not always smart enough to see it’.
It’s not that the psychologists are wrong – it’s more that when markets or stocks are at extreme levels, there is probably not a great deal of rationality on either side. Someone who sold a stock a lot higher is busy patting themselves on the back and telling their war story rather than considering whether the price has gone too far or the facts have changed. Whereas someone who purchased a stock on the way down only to lose a reasonable amount of money is busy licking their wounds, reluctant to add to a position and worried that the market knows something they don’t. In these cases it is often good to return to analysis conducted in quieter, more rational times. The popular view may be well made, but at a lower price and valuation, what odds are being received for taking the contra view?
Underperformance is never nice, but for investors with high conviction portfolios and/or distinct investment styles it is unfortunately an almost inevitable price to pay for subsequently experiencing the good times.
www.investecassetmanagement.com
Important information
This communication is for institutional investors and  nancial advisors only. It is not to be distributed to the public or within a country where such distribution would be contrary
to applicable law or regulations. If you are
a retail investor and receive it as part of a general circulation, please contact us at www. investecassetmanagement.com/contactus.
The information may discuss general market activity or industry trends and is not intended
to be relied upon as a forecast, research or investment advice. The economic and market views presented herein re ect Investec Asset Management’s (‘Investec’) judgment as at the date shown and are subject to change without notice. The value of investments, and any income generated from them, can go down as well as up and will be affected by changes in interest rates, exchange rates, general market conditions and other political, social and economic developments, as well as by speci c matters relating to the assets invested in.
There is no guarantee that views and opinions expressed will be correct, and Investec’s intentions to buy or sell particular securities
in the future may change. The investment views, analysis and market opinions expressed may not re ect those of Investec as a whole, and different views may be expressed based
on different investment objectives. Investec
has prepared this communication based on internally developed data, public and third party sources. Although we believe the information obtained from public and third party sources to be reliable, we have not independently veri ed it, and we cannot guarantee its accuracy or completeness. Investec’s internal data may not be audited.
Except as otherwise authorised, this information may not be shown, copied, transmitted, or otherwise given to any third party without Investec’s prior written consent. © 2018 Investec Asset Management. All rights reserved. Issued by Investec Asset Management, issued June 2018.
  ]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[         20
  Is the gig up for western in ation?
  Anthony Gillham | Head of Investments | Quilter Investors
Anthony Gillham explains how changes in the way we work are now so ingrained that they’re helping to keep in ation at bay, perpetuating today’s ‘wageless’ recovery.
If you’ve wandered into a DIY store, a major supermarket car park or even your local pub in recent times then you’ll no doubt have noticed the rising tide of silver haired employees shuf ing around in the foreground. This is one of the consequences of a population that’s suddenly living much longer and healthier lives than it did just a generation ago.
The aisles of white
Whether it’s by choice or just hard necessity, millions of Britons are now donning aprons and returning to the workforce for a second innings. This in ux of willing, skilled and only partially worn-out employees is one of the clearest indicators of the new forces that are helping to keep in ation at bay.
Although they probably don’t know it, this new generation of reconditioned shop workers are part of what’s known as the ‘gig economy’. It’s been the unrestrained growth of the gig economy that has loosened up the labour market over the last decade enabling
employers to keep their wage bills under tight control. These days, there’s no end of jobs that can be done by employees on so-called ‘zero-hour’ contracts (which don’t commit the employer to offering stable hours or
bene ts) and there are already well over a million Britons who currently work via online platforms such as Uber, Deliveroo and others1.
Taking the gig
More tellingly, there are now about 50% more self-employed people in the UK than there were at the start of the century with over a million Britons reportedly taking the plunge in the 10 years since the  nancial crisis. Great swathes of these are experienced professionals who have taken advantage
of modern technology to offer freelance or consultative services in their chosen  eld.
It’s currently estimated that at least 16% of UK workers now work in the gig economy. But while it’s delivered a new degree of  exibility to the labour market, it’s also helped to cut the legs out from under UK wages and, by extension, UK in ation.
Waging war
Historically, wage increases have always been a key driver of in ation. However, in both the
 There are now about 50% more self- employed people in the UK than there were at the start of the century with
over a million Britons reportedly taking the plunge in the 10 years since the  nancial crisis.
1Source: Fullfacts
 ]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[        21
   Although they probably don’t know it, this new generation of reconditioned shop workers are part of what’s known as the ‘gig economy’. It’s been the unrestrained growth of the gig economy that has loosened up the labour market over the last decade enabling employers to keep their wage bills under tight control.
US and the UK, wage increases have been stalled for the better part of a decade. In fact, US wages actually peaked back in 2015 with recent US average hourly earnings data (the so-called ‘non-farm payrolls’) failing to hit expectations.
Meanwhile, there’s increasing evidence to show that employers in the states are looking more closely at the non-salaried part of
the package they offer such as help with accommodation or reduced working hours. Others are resorting to recruiting students or banks of distance workers to address key skills shortages that are emerging in the US.
The picture is little different over here. Skill shortages are emerging as we head ever closer to full employment – especially in those areas where the differential between average salaries and average property prices is greatest. The situation is such that the Bank of England recently advocated the need for more migrant workers to help address the problem.
Thanks to the gig economy, a growing proportion of the UK workforce is unable
to work as many hours as they might like, or for the salary they think they deserve, but are structurally incapable of negotiating improved wages. This helps to explain today’s ‘wageless’ recovery.
The gig is up
The gig economy then, when coupled with the continued rise of new technologies such as robotics and arti cial intelligence, has helped to keep in ation at bay – despite all the growth indicators that suggest it should be higher at this point in the cycle.
The quant model that we use to forecast
core CPI is among those that probably needs to be recalibrated to take account of factors such as the gig economy and the new wave of automation (referred to as ‘industry 4.0’) that’s currently revolutionising manufacturing. Like many models of its type, it looks at the level of sterling and the cost of commodities as key drivers of in ation. But sterling remains weak, which historically has meant that we end up ‘importing’ a degree of in ation, while commodity prices – most notably oil – have begun to tick up once more.
Left to its own devices, this model would suggest that core in ation (not even the full rate of in ation) could well hit 3% before it fades back. The fact that we don’t expect core CPI to go anywhere near this level in the coming months shows just how much impact the gig economy is having on labour markets and in ation.
To  nd out more about our solutions, speak to one of our Investment Directors on
0207 167 3700, email enquiries@quilterinvestors.com or visit www.quilterinvestors.com
Important information
Past performance is not a guide to future performance and may not be repeated.
The value of investments and the income from them may go down as well as up
and investors may not get back any of the amount originally invested. Because of this, an investor is not certain to make a pro t
on an investment and may lose money. The performance data do not take account of
the commissions and costs incurred on the issue and redemption of shares. Exchange rate changes may cause the value of overseas investments to rise or fall.
This communication is issued by Quilter Investors Limited (“Quilter Investors”), Millennium Bridge House, 2 Lambeth Hill, London, United Kingdom, EC4V 4AJ. Quilter Investors is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.
 ]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  22
 Escalating trade tensions: time to worry?
  Jane Davies | Fund Manager | HSBC Global Strategy Portfolios
Tensions between the US and its trading partners have contributed to
a rise in market volatility this year. A recent escalation in rhetoric by US President Trump and action on tariffs have raised investor concerns over the global economic outlook. But are these fears justi ed and at what stage should we really be worried?
If we look at the global economic impact of the US fully implementing its threatened tariffs on Chinese imports, then our economic modelling suggests that the global impact is likely to be limited and manageable. We must keep in mind that despite the tariffs being bilateral, other economies could be impacted, for example Japan, Taiwan and South Korea, re ecting their role in China’s supply chain. Overall though, it is a deterioration that the global
economy should be able to weather, particularly given that most large economies are currently growing at above-trend levels.
Given this growth backdrop and current valuations, we believe that maintaining a pro-risk stance in our multi asset portfolios makes sense as long as the dispute remains largely bilateral (between the US and China) and does not extend beyond tariffs on USD450 billon of US imports from China.
Nonetheless, we remain mindful of the possible impact on sentiment and cross-asset correlations.
However, our view could be challenged if the US decides to push ahead with its threat to impose blanket 20% auto tariffs. This is a more worrying prospect as more economies would be affected. That said, the situation may not signi cantly escalate if the US economy starts to show any signs of being adversely affected by recent measures.
In the longer term, there is scope for the global economy to counter a potentially increasingly isolationist US economy with its own push for deeper integration. Indeed, the vast majority of economies – including China – remain tied to the rules-based multilateral trading system. Recent progress with the Trans-Paci c Partnership (TPP)
and the Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership (RCEP) in Asia, as well as
 We believe that maintaining a pro-risk stance in our multi asset portfolios makes sense as long as the dispute remains largely bilateral (between the US and China) and does not extend beyond tariffs on USD450 billon of US imports from China.
 ]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 23
  If we look at the global economic impact of the US fully implementing its threatened tariffs on Chinese imports, then our economic modelling suggests that the global impact is likely to be limited and manageable.
the ongoing Belt and Road Initiative, are examples of deeper ties in a region that accounts for an ever-larger share of world GDP and trade  ows.
A pro-risk investment stance
Notwithstanding the recent investor nervousness over the trade tensions, the global economic picture remains good. Economic growth is robust, albeit more differentiated across economies this year than last. Growth has slowed in Europe and Japan, and in ation pressures have begun to build
in the US, prompting a rise in bond yields,
but the corporate sector is in good shape, globally, and the risk of recession remains low. Given current valuations, we still believe that equities represent the best way to participate in underlying economic growth. We therefore maintain our moderately pro-risk positions
in multi-asset portfolios, with a preference for global equities and emerging markets as we think they offer the best risk-adjusted prospective returns.
The in ation factor and  xed income
Investor perceptions of in ation risk have moved quite a lot since the start of the year. Even though we have seen a pick-up
in cyclical in ation (in the US), the longer- term structural environment points to a low in ation global economy. In developed market government bonds, the reward (risk premium) for taking duration risk remains negative in many of the major developed markets, such as German Bunds, UK Gilts and Japanese government bonds. We therefore remain cautious on developed market government bonds generally,
given that they continue to offer low sustainable returns and face an unfavourable environment, with building cyclical in ation and central bank policy tightening.
That said, US Treasury bonds are in a bit
of a different place, over the short term at least. After a big re-pricing of interest rate expectations over the last twelve months, the risk premium in US Treasuries is now positive. The short end of the curve yields more than the dividend yield on US equities, which has not happened in the last 10 years. The risk reward balance is certainly more attractive than previously, particularly at the short end of the yield curve.
In corporate bond markets, credit spreads are offering slightly better value than earlier in the year, but still offer only a slim margin of safety against negative shocks, so we
maintain an underweight position in our multi-asset portfolios. Whilst credit quality remains fairly stable, high leverage levels indicate vulnerabilities in some sectors.
Overall, while investors continue to digest the latest moves on trade protectionism, in ation and interest rates, volatility in markets is likely to remain.
www.assetmanagement.hsbc.co.uk
For Professional Clients only and should not be distributed to or relied upon by Retail Clients.
The value of investments and any income from them can
go down as well as up and investors may not get back the amount originally invested. Any forecast, projection or target where provided is indicative only and is not guaranteed in any way. HSBC Global Asset Management (UK) Limited accepts no liability for any failure to meet such forecast, projection or target.
This commentary provides a high level overview of the recent economic environment, and is for information purposes only.
It is a marketing communication and does not constitute investment advice or a recommendation to any reader of this content to buy or sell investments nor should it be regarded as investment research. It has not been prepared in accordance with legal requirements designed to promote the independence of investment research and is not subject to any prohibition on dealing ahead of its dissemination.
Approved for UK professional clients only under ED 0746 ex 30/09/2018
  ]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  24
 Real assets - an introduction to an alternative solution
 Mayank Markanday | CFA | Architas
Mayank is a co-manager on a number of portfolios including the Architas Diversi ed Real Assets Fund, Architas Monthly High Income Find, Architas Strategic Bond Fund and Architas Diversi ed Global Income Fund and acts as deputy portfolio manager on the Multi-Asset Blended range. He is also the sector lead on UK  xed income,  xed income alternatives such as securitised credit, as well as macro/multi asset.
1. Why are real assets important for investors in today’s market?
Real asset investments cover a broad group of sub-asset classes such as property, infrastructure, renewable energy, commodities, or asset leasing. In general, they tend to have a combination of the following three characteristics in common:
• Provide access to investments that can protect against in ation better than traditional asset classes.
• Offer attractive yields in a low interest rate environment.
• Act as a source of portfolio diversi cation; a relevant feature when both bond and equity markets are arguably expensive.
We believe that investors can improve their risk/return pro le over the long run by including real assets within their alternative allocation bucket.
2. How would you describe the Architas Diversi ed Real Assets Fund’s investment strategy and what makes this fund different?
The fund is an industry-rated* multi-manager solution for investors seeking alternative
allocations. It is designed for retail investors looking to further diversify their portfolios away from traditional equities and bonds
by combining a range of alternative sub-
asset classes and specialist underlying investment funds. With this in mind we have three on-going objectives: diversi cation
from traditional assets, attractive income generation and long-run in ation protection. Our strategy provides access to parts of the market that advisers may not be aware of or perhaps don’t have the experience of investing within. The broad universe of alternatives available means we also see many more complex asset classes that can put investors off, but to us provides opportunity. Most alternative funds target diversi cation, but not all also offer potential for income generation and in ation sensitivity.
3. Since the fund was launched in 2014, there have been a number of sell-offs in equity markets. How concerning are these bouts of volatility?
We have faced several important tests since the inception of the fund in August 2014, and not just from the equity market - the bond market has also had patches of high volatility. These have all had different drivers relevant to the speci c period. Most recently, worries over in ation concerns in the US
and an increase in political risk has marked an in ection point in market volatility. The fact that the fund is fully unconstrained means that we can construct the portfolio to shelter from the areas of market stresses and incorporate some portfolio hedges to help out.
In addition, many of our investments are more sensitive to longer economic cycles than to the shorter-term noise the equity market can bring. Managing a long-only portfolio means that it can be dif cult to generate strong positive returns when most assets are in retreat; however in each case of market volatility we have protected capital well which we see as a positive outcome for the environment.
4. What’s your outlook?
We expect equity market volatility to persist as President Trump seeks to make Americans richer at the expense of the rest of the world. This uncertainty should lead to greater demand for defensive investments, particularly real assets
that can also withstand or bene t from in ationary pressures. While this hasn’t been a priority for investors in the post-crisis period, we believe that the combination in the US of robust domestic growth, falling unemployment and greater restrictions
on cheap imports could all contribute to the in ationary pressures that have been building over the past few years.
 Our strategy provides access to parts of the market that advisers may not be aware of or perhaps don’t have the experience of investing within.
*achieving a  ve diamond rating from Defaqto for multi-asset income.
 ]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 25
  Architas puts platform clients  rst by offering super clean to all
 Sarah Ackland | Head of UK Funds | Architas
In a move to offer the best value to advisers using a platform we are making our super clean share classes available to all UK investment platforms. We are currently working closely with your platforms to extend the share classes accessibility so you can offer the best value to your clients.
Previously the super clean share class has only been available on Standard Life Elevate and Standard Life Wrap. This will mean a reduction in the annual management charge (AMC) for all other platform clients of 20 basis points (bps) on the Active* and Blended ranges, 5 bps on the Passive fund range and 10 bps on the Diversi ed Real Assets fund compared to the clean share classes.
Extending our super clean share classes across all platforms will provide better value and more consistent pricing for all clients invested in Architas via third party platforms. We now have advisers using Architas across all the main UK platforms and believe it is right to make the best value pricing available to all platform clients rather than just those using a speci c one.
During the 10 years of Architas we have seen signi cant changes in the market. This includes the growth of multi-asset and multi-manager solutions and demand from advisers for funds that balance risk with potential reward. Given the growth of the business, it is right that we continue to offer competitive and value for money solutions for our clients.
This move will also simplify the situation if you are switching clients between platforms or using multiple platforms as part of your investment proposition. Having consistent pricing also removes the additional costs you face if you wish to switch platforms and want to remain invested in Architas funds. We hope this move will be welcomed by you and your clients.
Here is a breakdown of how the charges will be reduced:
 Given the growth of the business it is right that we continue to offer competitive
and value for money solutions for our clients.
 *The AMC on the clean (A) share class for the Architas Multi-Asset Active Reserve fund is 60bps so the reduction is only 5bps for the (S) share class.
Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments, and any income, can fall as well as rise and is not guaranteed, which means your client could get back less than they invest. If you need more information on any of our funds, you can ask us for
a free copy of the Key Investor Information document (KIID) and the prospectus. You can
also view or download all of our funds’ KIIDs from our website at architas.com. Some of the fund’s portfolio is invested in non-mainstream assets, which during periods of stressed market conditions may be dif cult to sell at a fair price, which may in turn cause prices to  uctuate more sharply than usual.
Architas Multi-Manager Limited is a company limited by shares and authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority (Firm Reference Number 477328). It is registered in England: No. 06458717. Registered Of ce: 5 Old Broad Street, London, EC2N 1AD.
   ]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  26
 Making a success
of succession planning
  John Husselbee | Head of Multi-Asset | Liontrust
Any Arsenal fans who invest in the Axa Framlington UK Select Opportunities fund will be feeling a loss after their two long-standing managers decided to move on over the past few months.
Arsène Wenger and Nigel Thomas have both announced giving up long-term positions after heading their respective operations for two decades, and we can only wait to see how their successors, Unai Emery and Chris St John respectively, get on with the task of  lling some extremely large shoes.
Without stretching this comparison too far – there have been no ‘Thomas out’ banners after all – it does shine a fresh light on
the subject of succession planning in ‘star’ based industries, which has increasingly become a key concern for me as a fund selector.
We have seen the emergence of ‘retail’ fund management over the last 20 or 30 years including the rise to prominence of
so-called star managers. When I started analysing funds in the late 1980s, most investors were unlikely to know much about the individuals and teams running their money but many now have high pro les with consumers as well as advisers. And while we might have pulled back from the peak star manager era – there are no more 10-feet high managers on billboards up and down the country – the trend remains well established.
This tends to lead to intense scrutiny when particular managers leave, with widespread debate, particularly in the press, over whether investors should buy or sell. As holders of Nigel Thomas in our portfolios, we are facing such a decision now but while we often invest in funds based
on certain individuals, we have always
counselled patience when it comes to moving on if a manager departs.
Research published by Morningstar last year focuses on the aftermath of fund management departures and comes to the surprising conclusion that, on average, there is no signi cant change in future performance.
“Yet investors overreact and subsequently pull money from these funds: our  ndings suggest that the fund industry handles succession planning far better than investors react to such changes,” the group said.
Investors might disagree based on certain instances in the past – a certain high-pro le manager giving up a Special Situations fund after 25 years in the mid- 2000s for example – but I would agree there is too much knee-jerk selling when big-name managers leave.
Going back to Morningstar, the rating agency said investors need to think twice before acting on a manager change,
asking whether a fund is one of the “few remaining where the strategy and manager are outside the norm, truly run by a personality or highly specialised individual”.
 When I started analysing funds in the late 1980s, most investors were unlikely to know much about the individuals and teams running their money but many now have high pro les with consumers as well as advisers.
 ]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 27
  Research published by Morningstar last year focuses on the aftermath of fund management departures and comes to the surprising conclusion that, on average, there is no signi cant change in future performance.
In most cases, it concludes, the answer is no. The most surprising part of the paper is Morningstar’s candid reaction to its own track record on manager changes, admitting it has often been unnecessary when it has put funds on watch lists.
“From our study, we  nd that we do not need to downgrade a fund every time there is a management change if we feel con dent in the parent, the process and the cost,’” it added. “We do need
to identify cases where there is a policy change in the fund’s strategy versus simply a management change.”
For me, the key part of this statement
is the focus on the parent company and the process – and this very much chimes with our thinking about consistency of process being a prerequisite across our holdings. While a particular investment process is often associated with a speci c manager, there is nothing to suggest it cannot pass to successors if the underlying infrastructure is suf ciently robust.
As stated, fund buyers have a tendency to react negatively to manager changes, often wanting to follow the departing individual onto pastures new. But thinking twice about the succession plans in
place, particularly with funds from larger investment houses, may save more than time and additional transaction costs.
Looking at a recent example, Ed Legget left Standard Life Investments for Artemis
in 2015, passing the SLI UK Equity Unconstrained Fund back to its  rst manager Wes McCoy.
Reviewing the numbers head to head
since Legget took up the reins of Artemis UK Select puts McCoy’s fund marginally behind over the past two years. The
more interesting story, however, is the similarity in the pattern of returns, with both stockpickers underperforming in 2016 and then among the best in the peer group over the past year.
There will clearly be particular instances where selling a fund when the manager leaves is ultimately the right call for investors. But given the work many groups are putting into succession planning – particularly for top-level managers who have been in place for many years – it is worth taking time over these decisions and not immediately rushing for the exit.
Key risks & disclaimer
Liontrust Fund Partners LLP (2 Savoy Court, London WC2R 0EZ), authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority (FRN 518165) to undertake regulated investment business.
Please remember that past performance is not a guide to future performance and the value of an investment and any income generated from them can fall as well as rise and is not guaranteed, therefore you may not get back the amount originally invested and potentially risk total loss of capital.
This document should not be construed as advice for investment in any product or security mentioned, an offer to buy or sell units/shares of Funds mentioned, or a solicitation
to purchase securities in any company or investment product. Examples of stocks are provided for general information
only to demonstrate our investment philosophy. It contains information and analysis that is believed to be accurate at the time of publication, but is subject to change without notice. Whilst care has been taken in compiling the content of this document, no representation or warranty, express or implied, is made by Liontrust as to its accuracy or completeness, including for external sources (which may have been used) which have not been veri ed. It should not be copied, faxed, reproduced, divulged or distributed, in whole or in part, without the express written consent of Liontrust.
 Fund buyers have a tendency to react negatively
to manager changes, often wanting to follow the departing individual onto pastures new. But thinking twice about the succession plans in place, particularly with funds from larger investment houses, may save more than time and additional transaction costs.
 ]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  28
  The evolving pensions/ retirement market post-freedoms
 MattWard |CommunicationsDirector|AKG
AKG’s2018PensionFreedomsPaper,Graspingthenettle:Working together to achieve better retirement outcomes, outlines the direction of travel in the market, including the customer, adviser, provider
and solutions landscape. The paper discusses key challenges and opportunities, old and new, for a range of market stakeholders and participants. The paper also illustrates, through market research, the thoughts, behaviours and requirements of customers and advisers.
In this feature, we summarise some of the key themes from the paper including some headline  ndings from the adviser market research.
Freedoms are good for business
Let’s start with the easy bit. The pension freedoms changes have largely been good news for advisers. AKG’s research showed that 77% of advisers are spending more time/resource on the provision of retirement advice since the introduction of pension freedoms.
Areas of concern for advice businesses
However, advisers are clearly concerned about the potential impact of Regulatory change/challenge (77%) and Political volatility (47%) on their businesses. Advisers
also expressed concern about Investment volatility (59%), a recurring theme for the paper, and Capacity/resource for their business (28%).
New business sources for advisers - client segments
Predictably,  nding it uneconomical to do so, advisers are unlikely to service those with retirement funds of £50,000. AKG’s research indicates that the ‘sweet spots’ are those clients at retirement with funds between £100,000 to £250,000 and those with more than £250,000.
Acknowledging the changing pro le of drawdown
Historically, drawdown business was conducted solely through intermediaries and with typical minimum product
entrance requirements of c.£250,000. ABI data, however, now points towards an average drawdown fund of under £70,000. Drawdown is therefore being used by more customers with lower retirement funds than was previously the case.
Now, without the GAD framework in place for withdrawals, it will be interesting to monitor exactly how drawdown is being utilised by customers.
For example, has it been picked just because it is perceived to be more  exible than annuities? Is it being used to strip out cash, in a tax ef cient manner, over the short- to mid-term? Is it being used for the provision of income over the longer term, to be underpinned by an investment portfolio? Or a combination of these factors?
 ]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[29
   AKG’s research showed that 77% of advisers are spending more time/ resource on the provision of retirement advice since the introduction of pension freedoms.
And so, there is huge potential for advisers
to deliver comprehensive and valued retirement planning services to clients, with many of these planning strategies involving drawdown. Advisers will need to use all
their skills, and employ a range of solutions in their toolkit, to optimise these planning opportunities and achieve positive retirement outcomes for clients.
Understanding key planning concerns for advisers
But what is on advisers’ minds in relation
to their clients? In AKG’s market research with advisers we asked, “What are your main investment/planning concerns for clients at- or post-retirement?”
The top four concerns were:
1. ‘Investment volatility’ - 48%
2. ‘Running out of money’ - 45%
3. ‘Sequencing of investment return
risk’ - 41%
4. ‘Longevity risk’ - 36%
Some fundamental issues for consideration here, all arguably linked in some way to the sustainability of retirement funds. This will certainly remain an area of focus for the market, on both the adviser and provider side, during 2018/19 and beyond.
And for these reasons, despite the slightly low ebb for provision of such solutions post- freedoms, there is likely to remain a case for the role of annuities and other forms of guarantees in the market in future years.
From an investment perspective, the composition and performance of drawdown portfolios will remain front of mind.
Adviser requirements from providers
In AKG’s market research with advisers we asked, “What are the key requirements for providers to be successful with advisers in the pensions/retirement market following the introduction of pension freedoms?”
The top  ve were:
1. ‘Service delivery standards’ - 58%
2. ‘Range of product/fund solutions’ - 54% 3. ‘Financial strength/sustainability’ - 48% 4. ‘Digital/online capability and
functionality’ - 45%
5. ‘Technical support (tax/pensions)’ - 33%
The importance of being able to deliver on core business competencies and disciplines is hammered home here for providers who want to be successful with advisers.
Identifying areas for development/ improvement
AKG was also keen to explore with advisers where they would like to see further development or improvement. Our market research with advisers therefore asked, “In which areas would you most like to see further development or improvement in the pensions/ retirement market during 2018/19?”
The top  ve were:
1. ‘Drawdown products’ - 46%
2. ‘Guaranteed capital/income
solutions’ - 31%
3. ‘Cost of products/funds/portfolios’ - 29%
4. ‘Digital/online capability and
functionality’ - 25%
5. ‘Value of products/funds/portfolios’ - 24%
Despite the early dominance of drawdown post-freedoms, advisers want to see further product development. It is also interesting
to see potential appetite for development or improvement in guaranteed capital/income solutions.
It is unsurprising to see a focus on cost and value of products/funds/portfolios given the regulatory focus on value for money. We will continue to see pressure on cost across the value chain, especially on the wrapper and investment management components of drawdown.
Improved digital/online capability and functionality is  agged here, as well as in the  ndings about adviser requirements from providers, and so businesses simply cannot afford to underestimate this requirement to invest and progress capability in this area.
More experience to be gained
Without exception, the pension freedom changes caught people by surprise. The changes have also coincided with a wider period of regulatory and political change and challenge. So, what we have seen initially
is three years of adjustment to the new freedoms with further work to be done in 2018/19 and beyond.
The number of ‘baby boomers’ approaching retirement is well documented, many of whom are yet to make their retirement decisions. Advisers and providers across the market must therefore continue to learn quickly from those customers experiencing the initial stages of pension freedoms to better target future business opportunities and enhancements to services.
For a variety of reasons, the pensions/ retirement market has become, and will remain, a fascinating place in which to transact business and to serve customers over the coming years.
 ]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[      30
                             Win, lose or withdraw?
 Andrzej Pioch | Fund Manager | Legal & General Investment Management
How fast can retirees sustainably draw down their retirement funds? That is a question which has caused much debate and anxiety in recent years, especially following the introduction of ‘pension freedoms’.
We see three factors which affect the rate of drawdown as most worthy of consideration:
Asset drivers - Spending drivers -
Attitude to risk - Asset drivers
The size of funds held and their risk and return characteristics
Demands on your capital such as one-off lump sums e.g. once-in-a-lifetime cruises or  nancial support| for children or grandchildren trying to get on the housing ladder
How much risk we’re prepared to take, both in terms of short-term volatility and the longer-term risk of the fund running dry
Size of retirement fund
A fund that’s twice as big as another can support double the withdrawals (before tax) with all else being equal.
Expected return
Interest rates are a key driver of the expected return of any fund. In general, the higher interest rates are, the higher the level of income a given size of fund can support, rather like annuity rates being higher when interest rates are too.
The expected return from the chosen investment strategy over and above interest rates depends on both the asset allocation and views on those asset classes (there is no right answer). All else being equal, a higher expected rate of return affords a higher income.
Uncertain returns
However, we need to tread carefully, as higher returns generally come with higher risk. The degree of investment return uncertainty depends on the asset allocation strategy. Generally, strategies targeting higher returns will be more volatile; for example, investors allocating more to emerging market equities should typically expect a bumpier ride than
those favouring government bonds. All else being equal, greater volatility leads to an increased risk of running out of money.
Spending drivers
Age
As retirees age, it becomes safer to withdraw a greater percentage of the remaining
fund each year as the risk of outliving their retirement fund (longevity risk) decreases.
For pure income drawdown investors, the only way to protect against this longevity risk is to ‘self-insure’ by withdrawing income at a ‘prudent’ or ‘sustainable’ rate. However, the problem is that in old age the degree of
 ]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  31
                                The degree of investment return uncertainty depends on the asset allocation strategy. Generally, strategies targeting higher returns will be more volatile; for example, investors allocating more to emerging market equities should typically expect a bumpier ride than those favouring government bonds.
prudence required can become crippling, pushing the sustainable rate below that available from an annuity. This may make annuitisation appear more attractive with age. Moreover, as we age, we may also favour a greater degree of simplicity.
Health
Being in poor health could be akin to retirees effectively being older (in terms of the mortality rates they are exposed to) than their years. Plainly the diverse range of retirees’ health circumstances underlines how different pension investors can have widely- differing needs.
Spending patterns
These will vary hugely across individuals. However, most individuals are exposed to similar drivers. Some of these drivers act
to increase spending over time, such as the need for in ation protection, and long- term care costs. In contrast, others tend to decrease spending. For example, pensioners tend to become less active over time. Some advisers like to think of a U-shaped spending pattern in retirement – outgoings decreasing at  rst (adjusted for in ation) but then tending to increase in advanced age. However, some researchers have expressed doubts over this pattern.
Inheritance matters
Inheritance goals are usually only a secondary objective, other than for those with the luxury of very substantial pension funds. However, our discussions with IFAs/ wealth managers dealing with high net worth individuals suggest that inheritance objectives are becoming increasingly relevant to some investors.
Other sources of income
Many retirees will qualify for a state pension. In practice, access to such a backstop income in uences other risk preferences – investors are often more willing to take greater risks with their pension funds if they have another source of regular income to fall back on, particularly if it is guaranteed (such as a de ned bene t pension).
Attitude to risk
In the absence of annuitisation, investors bear both investment risk (given that,
in general the return that will be earned
on assets is not known in advance) and longevity risk (given that nobody knows their date of death in advance). This effectively rules out the ‘perfect’ scenario for many retirees, namely that they get to enjoy every last penny just before their time comes. Retirees need to adapt their investment strategy and their withdrawal rates over
time to handle these risks. However, exactly how they adapt will depend on their attitude to risk. A retiree who’s more willing to run the risk of exhausting their pension fund might be prepared to take money out more quickly. At the other extreme, those who want to play things ultra-safe would take the annuitisation route and accept the lower consequent income.
Important Notice:
This is not a consumer advertisement. It is intended for professional  nancial advisers and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons. The views expressed within this document are those of Legal & General Investment Management, who may or may not have acted upon them. Legal & General Investment Management is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority and is the Investment Adviser to the UK Special Situations Trust, a UK authorised unit trust. Issued by Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. This document should not be taken as an invitation to deal in Legal & General investments or any of the stated investments. Remember, the value of investments and any income may fall as well as rise and investors may get back less than they invest.
Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. Registered in England and Wales No. 1009418. Registered of ce: One Coleman Street, London EC2R 5AA. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.
  ]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[         32
                          Cash ow modelling is now the rule, not the exception
  Eric Armstrong | Client Director | Synaptic Software Limited
So much has changed around the role of the adviser over the last
few years, and much of it for the better. The importance of cash ow modelling has exploded over a short space of time to become one of the most important adviser tools-of the-trade. Its relative simplicity belies its power to produce graphs that can easily communicate complex  nancial scenarios and help resolve sophisticated compliance challenges.
There are reasons that cash ow modelling has taken centre stage and it is worth looking at a couple of these before focussing on a couple of features that help Synaptic Analyser stand out. Many advisers generate graphs from spreadsheets, and these perform just as valid a function as our software, but Synaptic Analyser does a lot more.
It should also be said that many providers and platforms have cash ow modelling tools accessible. However, in the new world, accessing resources from an organisation that will also provide you with custody/ investment solutions will create a possible con ict of interest with your research and, at least, provide an additional burden of proving that the decisions you make have not been unduly in uenced. The FCA calls it ‘channelling’ (see COBS 2.3.1 (Rules on Inducements)), and any coincidence around signi cant in ows into a provider/platform, and use of their tools will raise concerns.
In the recent report ‘An ex-regulator’s guide to cash- ow planning’ (you can buy it online and we would recommend it), Rory Percival is unequivocal about the importance of cash-  ow plans. He provided an additional couple of points of clari cation that I think will really help a lot of clients:
• “Cash- ow planning can be about any form of income and outgoings and does not have to relate to the client’s overall position.” A cash- ow plan need not be a holistic view of a client’s  nances.
• The second point is that the cash- ow plan can establish a client’s Capacity for Loss. In fact, writes the author ‘it should be the main way of assessing capacity for loss for most clients.’ Capacity for Loss is the lynchpin of compliance and meeting the funding requirements for future income is central to any plan. An adviser needs to make an expert, objective
assessment of Capacity for Loss, or using its FCA de nition, identify the level at which loss may make a ‘material impact on the standard of living’.
Something can also be said about drawdown and ‘sustainable income’. Since pension freedoms changed everything in 2015, and GAD-based guidelines are no longer used to determine suitability of drawdown strategies, advisers have had to master the research required to illustrate ‘sustainable’ retirement income strategies. Rory Percival rightly outlines the importance of ensuring the ‘longevity of funds’ to fund a retirement plan. Consistent with a client’s Capacity for Loss, he explains the role that stochastic modelling may play in demonstrating longevity. Rather than providing a stochastic analysis within Analyser itself, we prefer to direct our customers to our Modeller tool to explore longevity (sustainability) using the Moody’s model. We do however have plans to extend
 ]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[    33
                               Accessing resources from an organisation that will also provide you with custody/investment solutions will create a possible con ict of interest with your research and at least, provide an additional burden of proving that the decisions you make have not been unduly in uenced.
our stochastic analysis of the cash ow planning in Analyser in due course.
Although the cash- ow model is designed to illustrate possibilities linked to the invested elements of a plan, i.e. pensions, ISAs and GIAs, the part of the Synaptic Analyser tool that our customers seem to appreciate most is the ability to include additional sources
of income, for example state pension, buy- to-let property or wages. This makes the outputs far more useful from a client-facing perspective.
Financial planning is made easier on a number of levels with Synaptic Analyser:
• Real  exibility comes with the ability
to save multiple scenarios, which are essential to help provide stress tests and what if scenarios;
• Direct access to accurate (including enhanced) annuity quotes makes any planning around ‘secured’ income a lot easier;
• A dashboard that provides calculations on ‘investment required’ and ‘maximum income’ from investments included;
• Integration of accurate quotes from a range of providers helps complete the research process.
Coming soon
Q4 2018 will see the addition of ‘Phased drawdown’ capability for the Synaptic Analyser tool.
 The screenshot above shows how data relevant to the recommendation can be accessible in one screen, capturing all the key facets of retirement planning and allowing ‘on-the- y’ editing of inputs. Notice the ability to represent the results in ‘real’ terms, i.e. in ation adjusted - important in gaining the understanding of the client. I can use the ‘income requirements’ slider to experiment with different levels of income required from the plan.
Please call us on 0800 783 4477 to arrange a demonstration or free trial, or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk
 ]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[            34
                         This article may contain nuts - Sustainable and Responsible Investment
 Paul Quarendon | New Product Development Manager | Synaptic Software Limited
1984... A year to remember, whether for Orwellian reasons, Band Aid, or perhaps the launch of the UK’s  rst fully ethical fund, Friends Provident’s Stewardship fund.
It reminds me of the hours I spent training up on that new fund when I worked in
one of their satellite of ces. I can recall its investment criteria speci cally excluding sectors involved with tobacco, arms, alcohol and oppressive regimes but, more recently, the internet taught me something I didn’t know. Apparently, it was originally nicknamed ‘the Brazil fund’ by city experts who found the notion of ethical investment as ‘nuts’.
Fast forward to today and the Ethical, Social and Governance (ESG) landscape looks a very different place indeed. It’s not just about the odd wind turbine improving or ruining your vista. Since 1984, investment in ethical funds has come a long way. Nowadays, and as with any investment, choice, diversity and opinions are key. Ethical investors will not only want to consider the obvious impacts
of carbon emissions, renewable energy and climate change. There’s the in-vogue security of one’s data, not to mention the corruption and business ethics that we hear about.
To highlight the changing face of ethical investment, last year witnessed a record investment of around £100bn into active ethical funds, and in March this year alone, investors placed £138m into ethical funds, over 430% up on the amount invested during March 20171.
Flagged as an area of interest, this publication ran an article in January 2016, entitled ‘Ethical investing – value as well as values’. Indeed, a six-month snapshot of data taken from Synaptic’s Product & Fund tool between December 2017 and May 2018
highlighted that out of over 3,000 pieces of unit trust research conducted, 9% of cases selected the ethical  ag.
Synaptic currently maintains ethical policy data for over a thousand funds. We are seeing advisers actively encouraging more fund managers to push ethical data to us,
as they increasingly utilise Product and
Fund to screen for more ethical funds. Technological advances and enhanced analytics are allowing Synaptic to receive and provide better ethical data than ever before. This means that we can offer transparent
 Let’s take Millennials as an example. The next big  nancial event they will bene t from is the £6trn inheritance windfall heading their way over the next 20 years or so, and it is this group who have already formed strong connections with the ethical aspects of their everyday lives.
1. Source: Investment Association.
 ]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[     35
                                Can we keep pace with the demands of all ethical investors, no matter which demographic they belong to, and how much they have available to invest?
and accurate data which sits neatly with ESG research, offering an objective and  nancially relevant approach to customers’ investment strategies.
This is all great news but do your customers still fully understand their own personal objectives when it comes to ful lling their social conscience? We all want to contribute to saving our planet (beyond owning a bag for life!), but often, and I know I do this, we think “how can I, on my own, make such a difference if no-one else follows suit?”.
We are now also acutely aware of the heightened pro le new demographics such as Millennials and Generation Z enjoy. Through increasing media coverage, we are quickly learning that they are fast becoming  nancial powerhouses. Let’s take Millennials as an example. The next big  nancial event they will bene t from is the £6trn inheritance windfall heading their way over the next 20 years or so, and it is this group who have already formed strong connections with the ethical aspects of their everyday lives.
Many Millennials already donate to campaigns and charities, or volunteer their services to various social, environmental or political causes. It should come as no surprise then that they recognise investment success
should not only be measured by the  nancial performance of their portfolio, but a longer term view of sustainability.
If this is a commonly shared view, as an adviser, how often are you obliged to expand your customers’ grasp of what exactly sustainable or ethical investment means, and what the differences between ESG research and Sustainable and Responsible Investment (SRI) products are?
ESG and SRI are abbreviations often used in the same breath but they do have different roles to play. There has been an argument claiming that investments integrating with key ESG factors return poor performance, however recent studies have started to dispel that myth proving that ethical funds are demonstrating lower risk and outperforming portfolios over the medium to long term.
So, what is the difference? Put simply, ESG dictates the impact its practices have on the performance of an investment. Their integration is designed to enhance the more traditional  nancial analysis by identifying potential risks and opportunities. Only when society plays a part will  nancial performance remain the main objective of the ESG evaluation.
SRI goes one step further. Screening actively eliminates or selects investments according to speci c ethical guidelines. Underpinning this could be your customer’s religion, their personal values and/or political beliefs.
Perhaps the idea of ethical investment isn’t nuts after all. Millennials certainly don’t
think so, but the question remains, “Can we keep pace with the demands of all ethical investors, no matter which demographic they belong to, and how much they have available to invest?”.
Synaptic continues to offer up-to-date fund knowledge. The Product & Fund tool offers a section dedicated to ‘ethical’ funds and allows you to  lter results based on your customers’ investment needs and solutions.
For more information please contact us on 0800 783 4477 or visit www.synaptic.co.uk
  ]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[         36
                          Talking ‘bout my Generation... Z
  Paul Quarendon | New Product Development Manager | Synaptic Software Limited
They were born into the digital age and have never known life without the internet. They have a world of information at their  ngertips and they want it quicker than the Millennium Falcon made the Kessel run. They are Generation Z.
The children of Generation X, born into this cohort in the mid-1990’s, are now entering the workplace and developing their own opinions on  nance, politics and health in the here and now, and for the future. So far, they have been shaped by advancements
in technology, and have much more access to, and are keenly aware of, global political events and the impact these have on society. All of this will have had a fundamental impact on Gen Z’s attitude towards life and future values so it should be no surprise that they have different mindsets and behaviours to previous generations when in their early stages of life.
There are important differences between them and their Generation X parents, who sat astride the world of pre-technology and this brave new world of social media. Also known as “digital natives,” they are growing up with smartphones, tablets and laptops as omnipresent necessities in their everyday activities.
It is becoming abundantly clear that the maturity shown in their decision making
is something you would more commonly associate with those in older generations,
but Gen Z hold strong beliefs fuelled by information accessible via the internet. Their attitude to health is one. They have lived through economic downswings, so health cover has become particularly important (and extremely marketable) to them. They do seem worried or concerned about the impact technology will have throughout their lifetime, which means health and  tness will be areas they will want to focus on when thinking about sustaining an active lifestyle. Research has revealed that Gen Z are more likely to pay a premium to look after their health than any other current demographic which demonstrates clearly that this presents clear opportunities to play to one of their key characteristics – stability and security.
So, how do we successfully reach out to Generation Z? Well, they continue to make themselves constantly available via their smartphone and instant messaging apps. The perceived downside to that is they apparently have an attention span of just eight seconds,
so any messages we do get through need to be short, sharp and immediately to the point. They’re not necessarily an impatient bunch but they have a desire to make fast and valuable decisions.
Employers are already starting to get on
the front foot, recognising the potential in altering working patterns to  t with the Gen Z workforce. Businesses will look upon these changes as ideal ways to promote loyalty and support, but, beware; like Millennials, organisations must act ethically to attract Gen Z, and this will be mirrored in the way  nancial companies acquit themselves when trying to meet the needs of this new population.
Is it therefore wise to talk to Gen Z before we develop systems and procedures to meet their needs? We are blessed with so much research on the internet, it feels like we already know everything about them, but wherever our research and ingenuity takes us, at the heart of our energy should be the emotion of the purchaser, and their need to cover certain scenarios.
 ]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[    37
                               Whichever pedestal we choose to put Gen Z on, they have been known to be fully conversant in using a tablet before being able to tie a shoe lace, before being able to swim and even before they are able to tell the time!
It’s fair to say, not many of them will be purchasing their own properties quite yet, but they will be renting, presenting the  nancial services industry with a potentially lucrative protection proposition. Will this signal the boon Income Protection needs? Given it is likely that a Gen Z’s  rst job will no longer be a rite of passage into a long- term career with the same employer, (as
was the case with many Baby Boomers and some Millennials), in a couple of years’ time the career ladder will come calling, as will a higher earning capacity. Protection can play a signi cant part in providing that ‘stability and security’ they crave.
So, in summary, what are the key challenges we need to face head on if we want to tap into this future  nancial powerhouse:
• Their use of multiple media presents a challenge – what is the best way to engage them?
• Does Gen Z know what the insurance industry can offer and how it can help them in the future?
• Security is crucial, so Facebook may not be the platform to engage with them. Gen Z has seen some other generations get burned by social media scandals and identify theft. We must all be able to safeguard sensitive data.
• They will, however, still want to learn about new products via social media. The ability to personalise, streamline and simplify communications with them via quick, visual content in video will be vital.
To round off, here’s something you may  nd startling. Whichever pedestal we choose to put Gen Z on, they have been known to be fully conversant in using a tablet before being able to tie a shoe lace, before being able to swim and even before they are able to tell the time!
Synaptic has recently joined up with COVER Magazine to produce an e-book focussing on innovation in the digital space for protection. To read this visit https://www.synaptic. co.uk/research-and-opinion/blog/cover- and-synaptic-software-join-hands-gaze- future-protection-0
Watch our video illustrating how Generation Z approaches life and their need for  nancial advice at www.synaptic.co.uk/research- and-opinion/blog/synaptic-guide- generation-z
  ]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                    The Suitability Suite
Risk. Costs. Due diligence. Best advice
Proof of suitability is easier with Synaptic Research
 • The regulator is making proof of suitability the cornerstone of its enforcement policy
• Synaptic provides proof of suitability in the key areas of product features, risk and costs
         Synaptic Product and Fund Whole of market product and fund research, full suitability reporting
                       Synaptic Comparator
Detailed price analysis for platforms, products and funds including R.I.Y. calculations
                                                  RISK
Synaptic Risk A.T.R.Q. and Risk Rated funds and portfolios
            Synaptic Modeller
Models investment outcomes for new and existing holdings. Manage and assess investment risk
                                        SYNAPTIC
WEBLINE
Synaptic Webline
Protection and Annuity quotes and on-line applications (including enhanced annuities)
                 Synaptic Analyser Retirement income analysis and drawdown product comparison.
                              Synaptic Suitability offer £175 per licence, per month (excl. VAT) - rrp £309
Apply today, call us on 0800 783 4477 or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk quoting ‘Suitability Offer’.
  SAVE OVER
£130 PER LICENCE
]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                            Risk and suitability in a perfect ‘10’
         • Synaptic Modeller provides complete risk and suitability and investment risk management for head offices, paraplanners and advisers, combining Moody’s Analytics investment strategy and stochastic projections
• Accurate and consistent values for downside risk that can be used to align Capacity for Loss with risk in chosen investments
• Includes fully integrated ATR Questionnaire, Asset Allocations and stochastic engine for illustrative projections
• Synaptic Modeller offers key Moody’s probability based risk metrics: the Value at Risk in any given investment scenario and the investment outcome
• Adviser controls inputs for investment amount, term, costs including adviser charges
• Perfectly complements RSMR qualitative research, accessible through Synaptic Product and Fund Fact sheets
• Integrates with Intelliflo via iO Store
                              Synaptic Modeller is now available with 1-10 risk categories as well as 1-5, defined by Moody’s Analytics asset allocations
  Synaptic Modeller is available as a standalone module from £50 per month. Network deals can apply. Can also be deployed as part of the full Synaptic Research Suite.
 For more information call 0800 783 4477 or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk
  ]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[         40
                       Asset allocation - unlocking the value in advice
 Eric Armstrong | Client Director | Synaptic Software Limited
I sometimes wonder how much thought advisers give to the research and expertise that sits behind the asset allocation decisions that they and their clients rely upon. Without asset allocation, any consideration of risk would fall down, because there would be no basis of assumption for the likely growth of the asset classes that make up a portfolio, or their likely interaction in the various possible economic scenarios that we are able to foresee.
No expert judgement around suitability would be possible, nor would any sensible predictions of investment outcomes. All
the major trends that drive the returns of our retail customers are rooted in the asset allocation models that reside at the heart of any  rm’s investment strategy.
One beauty of asset allocation is that the framework can accommodate any style
of investment. Synaptic has had a long collaboration with RSMR, whose qualitative commentary provides insights into funds and managers that have become hugely in uential. All our major adviser groups rely on this commentary to help direct their fund choices to a greater or lesser extent. Large cap/small cap, global/local, Emerging/ Frontier, high yield, long/short duration, sovereign/corporate, convertible, hedged, smart beta, ETF/OEIC, multi asset or DFM...
these are all the everyday concerns of those seeking investment returns, but all  t into the framework provided by asset allocation, which is used to map an ef cient frontier balancing investment return forecast against risk.
The ef cient frontier was a concept that helped revolutionise investment and we still adhere to the principles today. In his Modern Portfolio Theory, economist Harry Markowitz demonstrated how the correlation co- ef cients between various asset classes could be used to optimise an asset class blend to maximise portfolio returns.
Markovitz’ research has been used as a starting point by research specialists such
as Moody’s Analytics (formerly Barrie + Hibbert), who can now produce probability- based projections of all viable economic scenarios and asset class growth trajectories.
The engine that produces these models is integrated into the Synaptic Modeller tool. By accessing these projections, advisers have access to all the metrics they need to prove suitability and hopefully delight their clients. This investment risk management approach offers:
• A consistent and proven approach to balancing risk and return;
• The extent to which losses in a bad year (1 in 20) will fall, allowing the adviser to accommodate the client’s Capacity for Loss with the chosen investment;
• Reliable, research-based portfolio growth rate assumptions, that will allow a realistic plan to be formulated in line with objectives.
 ]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[    41
                           One beauty of asset allocation is that the framework can accommodate any style of investment.
This mathematical modelling is done using simulation (Monte Carlo) where thousands of outcomes are generated and analysed,
a technique also referred to as stochastic modelling. The accuracy of the model comes from the success that Moody’s have had in building the rules that underpin
the simulation. This implies of course the truth that not every model is a good one, so be careful which one you adopt. The proof is in the pudding, and Moody’s have been proven for accuracy over many years including the 2008 downturn. Moody’s (uniquely) attributed an accurate probability and loss to the event, meaning that clients of Synaptic and Moody’s should not have been unduly concerned with losses as they occurred at that time and remain invested, in line with the FCA’s guidance on risk and Capacity for Loss. The model is presented to advisers in terms of Value at Risk and these measurements form the boundaries of the Synaptic risk categories. Value at Risk is a more valuable metric to advisers than drawdown or volatility per se.
As well as having access to a framework constructed of Strategic Asset Allocations, advisers can review asset allocations
of existing investments and project on recommendations that they wish to make. The ability to illustrate the risk and return characteristics of these investments, and frame them in the context of a company’s investment strategy, makes the challenge of compliance in the MiFID age manageable.
How is a strategic asset allocation created? The graph (above right) shows output of simulation, hot off the press, used to de ne the Level 1, Cautious Portfolio in the new Synaptic 1-10 range.
For Portfolio 1 we had four candidates. Portfolio ‘test 10’ was selected as it had the best risk/return characteristics (i.e. target was 4.4% 1year VAR, this was lower and had the better projected return).
 To identify the Synaptic Risk strategic asset allocation boundaries, Moody’s uses 6 core asset classes (although the Synaptic version of the engine can process up to 22 asset classes including various  xed income asset classes which include high yield corporate bonds and index-linked bonds, global equities, commodities, infrastructure and hedge funds).
Processing these strategic asset allocations creates our ef cient frontier based on risk metrics that look like this:
 Asset allocation name
 Term
 Type
 Boundaries - Min Gain
   Max Gain
 Mean Gain
 Risk Rating
  Cautious
  10
   Strategic
 -5.27
   11.44
 2.93
   < 2.0
 Moderately Cautious
 10
 Strategic
 -10.71
 18.25
 3.92
 < 3.0
 Balanced
  10
  Strategic
  -14.7
  23.99
  5.22
  < 4.0
  Moderately Adventurous
 10
  Strategic
-18.19
  28.85
6.15
  < 5.0
 Adventurous
  10
  Strategic
  -22.6
  36.43
  7.36
  < 6.0
  The ef cient frontier for the Moody’s/Synaptic model has the advantage of being constructed around potential loss (so Value at Risk), rather than the more usual volatility bands.
 ]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 42
 The bene t of the Moody’s approach is that the model represents every viable investment outcome, including all sequence of returns. The simulation aspect of the exercise harnesses the power of probability through the generation of thousands of scenarios.
                              MiFID watchers will have been horri ed
at the guidance put forward in those directives that allows for investment growth assumptions to be made by averaging previous years’ performance. Just looking
at a table of asset class returns shows how impossible it is to predict returns in the short term by looking at past performance. It is only by stretching the term and capturing the trends and behaviours correctly that our projections become meaningful.
The bene t of the Moody’s approach is that the model represents every viable investment outcome, including all sequence of returns. The simulation aspect of the exercise harnesses the power of probability through the generation of thousands of scenarios. Stochastic modelling was a bit of a joke a few years ago in the mainstream (though certainly not at institutional level
– for example Moody’s have been used by Royal London for years). Not anymore, as practitioners start to appreciate that the probabilistic approach leads to far more reliable forecasting, and the ability to embed a transparent process means that advice becomes consistent and reporting is made possible for compliance purposes.
Asset allocation becomes a prism to evaluate any and every portfolio. In the rear pages of this magazine, you will see a wide range of fund groups who have participated in our risk rating. The Synaptic Risk Ratings are calculated by verifying the asset allocation
of the investment with the asset manager, and projecting using the Moody’s stochastic engine. This is mapped to the Moody’s ef cient frontier, giving us a risk pro le that can be correctly mapped to the risk appetite of the client. The Strategic Asset Allocations have been developed to align perfectly with the ATRQ provided.
Notice that the methodology is different
to the others in the market, who are less con dent of their ability to project asset classes and therefore provide a committee- based ‘rating’ rather than a research-based rating. The problem of this, in our view, is that it removes the perspective of the adviser or investment committee, who should be providing the ‘qualitative overlay’ (with the assistance of RSMR’s insights). The Moody’s approach also means that the adviser
has an objective means of monitoring an investment, rather than relying on a rating agency whose culture is to obscure the underlying dynamics and play down the  uidity of the risk universe.
See above for an example of how the Risk metrics make up the Synaptic risk ratings for Brewin Dolphin MPS portfolios. The ‘min gain’ is used to map to the boundaries of the risk categories. It is also the Value at Risk which must be matched to the client’s Capacity for Loss.
   ]]></page><page Index="43" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                              Another great bene t of working with Moody’s stochastic model is the ability to model in ation. This is a thorny challenge for advisers, because
of the dif culty of gaining a useful model for in ation, and illustrations that accurately capture the ravages of in ation are not useful sales aids(!), unless the adviser is shown the likely impact of in ation on a cash holding as a point of comparison. This focusses the mind on the value of investment as a means of protecting wealth over the long term. Moody’s calculate the impact of in ation historically to average 4.5% loss per year, in any 10-year period. The illustration (top right) indicates an 85% likelihood of losing money on 10-year cash investment (without costs!). The average return in the model at £8.6k is not as
bad as in real life, as we are using the investment de nition of cash as short dated bonds (1-year government bonds which have a greater growth potential than cash in the bank).
Putting it all together, for research purposes
you can combine the projections of the asset allocations that underpin your advice. We are looking at the Strategic Asset Allocation, the allocation of the recommended investment, and we are overlaying costs and in ation for the full, beautifully compliant picture.
The next results (right) show the value of advice
– an 85% chance of losing money has become
an 60% chance of making money. Now if some charges could be shaved off, the picture starts
to look more like our nominal projection (over 90% chance of gains)... but that is another story. The recommendation here was using a 10-year projection with 1.1% costs (adviser charges, platform and fund). Remember the ‘min gain value’ is our Value at Risk amount, the extent of the losses expected in a ‘bad year’, de ned as 1 in 20 (5%) – enabling us to make our Capacity for Loss assessment with credible values. The blue
line shows the projected returns of our strategic Balanced allocation. The green line shows the asset allocation of our recommended investment. The red line is the latter includes costs and in ation.
For more information on any of the above, including access to the Synaptic Modeller tool or the Risk ratings (free), please call us on 0800 783 4477 or email us on sales@synaptic.co.uk.
   43
]]></page><page Index="44" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ MA Passive Prudent
MA Passive Reserve
MA Passive Moderate MA Passive Intermediate MA Passive Progressive MA Passive Growth
MA Passive Dynamic
MA Blended Reserve
MA Blended Moderate MA Blended Intermediate MA Blended Progressive MA Blended Growth
MA Active Reserve
MA Active Moderate Income MA Active Intermediate Income MA Active Progressive
MA Active Growth
MA Active Dynamic
Newton Multi-Asset Diversified Return Newton Multi-Asset Income
Newton Multi-Asset Balanced Newton Multi-Asset Growth
Newton Global Balanced
Newton Global Dynamic Bond Newton Global Dynamic Bond Income Newton Real Return
Cautious Moderately Cautious
MAF I MAF II MAF III MAF IV MAF V
F&C MM Lifestyle Foundation
F&C MM Lifestyle Defensive Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Cautious Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Growth Fund Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling) F&C MM Navigator Distribution
F&C MM Navigator Moderate
F&C MM Navigator Progressive
F&C MM Navigator Select
F&C MM Navigator Boutiques
BMO Universal MAP Cautious
BMO Universal MAP Balanced
BMO Universal MAP Growth
Synaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:
Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation
Balanced
Moderately Adventurous
Adventurous
]]></page><page Index="45" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                MPS Low Risk (Defensive Income)
MPS Low Medium Risk (Income & Growth) MPS Low Medium Risk (Income)
MPS Medium Risk (Income)
MPS Medium Risk (Income & Growth) MPS Medium Risk (Passive)
MPS Medium High Risk
MPS Medium High Risk (Passive)
MPS High Risk (Income & Growth)
MPS High Risk (Growth)
IFSL BM Defensive Income
IFSL BM Cautious Growth
IFSL BM Balanced
IFSL BM Strategic Growth
IFSL BM Defensive Capital
MPS Low Medium Risk (Passive)
                                                                                                                                              Cautious MPS
Income MPS
Balanced MPS Growth MPS
Global Equity MPS Cautious Passive+ Income Passive+ Balanced Passive+ Growth Passive+ Global Equity Passive+
                                                                                                                       LF Canlife Portfolio III LF Canlife Portfolio IV LF Canlife Portfolio V LF Canlife Portfolio VI LF Canlife Portfolio VII Canlife Portfolio 3 Canlife Portfolio 4 Canlife Portfolio 5 Canlife Portfolio 6 Canlife Portfolio 7
LF Canlife Managed 0%-35% Canlife Managed 0%-35%
                         Carmignac Portfolio Sécurité
Carmignac Portfolio Patrimoine
Carmignac Portfolio Capital Plus
Carmignac Portfolio Commodities
Carmignac Portfolio Emergents
Carmignac Portfolio Unconstrained Global Bond
Carmignac Portfolio Euro-Entrepreneurs Carmignac Portfolio Capital Cube
Carmignac Portfolio Investissement
Carmignac Portfolio Long-Short European Equities
Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Discovery Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Patrimoine Carmignac Portfolio Grande Europe
                        Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk
]]></page><page Index="46" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Dynamic Passive 1 Dynamic Passive 2 Dynamic Passive 3 Dynamic Passive 4 Dynamic Passive 5
Close Managed Growth Fund
Close Tactical Select Passive Growth Fund
Close DMS Growth
Close Managed Balanced Fund
Close Tactical Select Passive Balanced Fund
Close DMS Balanced
Close Managed Income Fund
Close Managed Conservative Fund
Close Tactical Select Passive Conservative Fund
Close DMS Income Plus
Close DMS Conservative
Close Bond Income Portfolio Fund Close Growth Portfolio Fund
Close Balanced Portfolio Fund
Close Conservative Portfolio Fund Close Diversified Income Portfolio Fund
HSBC Global Strategy Cautious HSBC Global Strategy Conservative HSBC Global Strategy Balanced HSBC Global Strategy Dynamic HSBC Global Strategy Adventurous
Multi Manager Income 1 Multi Manager Income 2 Multi Manager Income 3 Multi Manager Income 4 Multi Manager Income 5 Multi Manager Total Return 1 Multi Manager Total Return 2 Multi Manager Total Return 3 Multi Manager Total Return 4 Multi Manager Total Return 5
GS Wealthbuilder Multi Asset Conservative Portfolio
GS Wealthbuilder Multi Asset Balanced Portfolio
GS Wealthbuilder Multi-Asset Growth Portfolio
Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Defensive Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Cautious Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Balanced Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Growth Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Aggressive Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Distribution MI Hawksmoor Vanbrugh
MI Hawksmoor Distribution
Dynamic Passive
Multi Manager
]]></page><page Index="47" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                              Invesco Perpetual Asian Fund
Invesco Perpetual Corporate Bond Fund
Invesco Perpetual Distribution Fund
Invesco Perpetual Global Bond Fund
Invesco Perpetual Global Smaller Companies Fund
Invesco Perpetual Global Targeted Returns Fund
Invesco Perpetual High Income Fund Invesco Perpetual High Yield Fund
Invesco Perpetual Hong Kong & China Fund Invesco Perpetual Income Fund
Invesco Perpetual Latin American Fund
Invesco Perpetual Managed Growth Fund
Invesco Perpetual Managed Income Fund
Invesco Perpetual Monthly Income Plus Fund
Invesco Perpetual Pacific Fund
Invesco Perpetual Tactical Bond Fund
Invesco Perpetual UK Smaller Companies Equity Fund
Invesco Perpetual UK Strategic Income Fund Summit Growth 1
Summit Growth 2
Summit Growth 3
Summit Growth 4 Summit Growth 5
                                                         Diversified Income Fund
Investec Cautious Managed Fund
Diversified Growth Fund
MAP
Investec Global Multi-Asset Total Return Fund
                                                           Henderson Cautious Managed Henderson MM Absolute Return Henderson MM Distribution Henderson MM Income & Growth Henderson MM Managed Henderson MM Active Henderson Core 3 Income Henderson Core 4 Income Henderson Core 5 Income Henderson Core 6 Income
                                                                                                                                               Multi-Index 3 Multi-Index 4 Multi-Index 5 Multi-Index 6 Multi-Index 7 Multi-Index Income 4 Multi-Index Income 5 Multi-Index Income 6
                                                                                   MPS - Defensive
MPS - Cautious
MPS - Balanced
MPS - Growth
MPS - Adventurous MPS - Strategic Income
          Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk
]]></page><page Index="48" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                         MPS
  MPS Growth 1
MPS Growth 2
MPS Growth 3
MPS Growth 4
MPS Growth 5
MPS Growth 6
MPS Growth 7
MPS Growth 8
MPS Income 1
MPS Income 2
MPS Income 3
MPS Income 4
MPS Income 5
MPS Income 6
MPS Dynamic Beta 1 MPS Dynamic Beta 2 MPS Dynamic Beta 3 MPS Dynamic Beta 4 MPS Dynamic Beta 5 MPS Dynamic Beta 6 MPS Dynamic Beta 7 MPS Dynamic Beta 8
                                            WSS
       WSS Risk Grade 1 WSS Risk Grade 2 WSS Risk Grade 3 WSS Risk Grade 4 WSS Risk Grade 5 WSS Risk Grade 6 WSS Risk Grade 7 WSS Risk Grade 8 WSS Risk Grade 9 WSS Risk Grade 10 WSS Income 1
WSS Income 2
WSS Income 3
WSS Income 4
WSS Income 5
WSS Income 6
WSS Dynamic Beta 1 WSS Dynamic Beta 2 WSS Dynamic Beta 3 WSS Dynamic Beta 4 WSS Dynamic Beta 5 WSS Dynamic Beta 6 WSS Dynamic Beta 7 WSS Dynamic Beta 8 WSS Dynamic Beta 9 WSS Dynamic Beta 10
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       Flexible Guaranteed Funds Cautious Flexible Guaranteed Funds Balanced Flexible Guaranteed Managed Growth
          MP3 MP4 MP5 MP6 MP7
         ]]></page><page Index="49" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Premier Multi-Asset Conservative Growth Premier Multi-Asset Absolute Return Fund Premier Multi-Asset Distribution Fund Premier Multi-Asset Monthly Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Growth & Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Global Growth Fund Premier UK Money Market Fund
Premier Defensive Growth Fund
Premier Corporate Bond Monthly Income Fund
Premier Diversified Fund Premier Diversified Income Fund Premier Liberation IV Fund Premier Liberation V Fund Premier Liberation VI Fund Premier Liberation VII Fund
PruFund Cautious
PruFund Protected Cautious PruFund Growth
PruFund Protected Growth PruFund 0-30
PruFund 10-40
PruFund 20-55
PruFund 40-80
WP Optimum Return Focused 0-30
Focused 10-40
Focused 20-55
Focused 40-80
Focused 60-100
Dynamic 0-30
Dynamic 10-40
Dynamic 20-55
Dynamic 40-80
Dynamic 60-100
Premier Capital Builder Portfolio Premier Capital Builder Plus Portfolio Premier Income and Growth Portfolio Premier Income Portfolio
Premier Conservative Portfolio Premier High Income Portfolio Premier Balanced Portfolio
Premier Balanced Plus Portfolio Premier Growth Portfolio
Premier Growth Plus Portfolio Premier Dynamic Growth Portfolio
MPS Global Growth MPS Growth
MPS Balanced
MPS Global Income MPS Income
MPS Conservative MPS Cautious IDX Growth
IDX Balanced
IDX Income
IDX Conservative
MPS Global Growth (Platform) MPS Growth (Platform)
MPS Balanced (Platform)
MPS Global Income (Platform) MPS Income (Platform)
MPS Conservative (Platform) IDX Growth (Platform)
IDX Balanced (Platform)
IDX Income (Platform)
IDX Conservative (Platform)
Funds
MPS Portfolios
]]></page><page Index="50" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                               Quilter Generation 3
Quilter Generation 4
Quilter Generation 5
Quilter Cirilium Conservative Fund Quilter Cirilium Balanced Fund Quilter Cirilium Moderate Fund Quilter Cirilium Dynamic Fund Quilter Cirilium Adventurous Fund Creation Conservative
Creation Balanced
Creation Moderate
Creation Dynamic
Creation Adventurous
CRA 3 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 4 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 5 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 6 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 7 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 8 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 9 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 10 Active Managed Portfolio
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       Bespoke
   Strategy 1 Strategy 2 Strategy 3 Strategy 4 Strategy 5 Strategy 6
                  Managed Portfolios
  Cautious Balanced Income Balanced Plus Equity
Equity Plus
              RMAP Total Return RMAP Strategic Growth RMAP Enhanced Growth RMAP Strategic Income
Multi Asset
                      Global Multi Asset Portfolios
  RL GMAP Conservative RL GMAP Defensive
RL GMAP Balanced
RL GMAP Growth
RL GMAP Adventurous RL GMAP Dynamic
           ]]></page><page Index="51" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                           RL Governed Portfolio 1 RL Governed Portfolio 2 RL Governed Portfolio 3 RL Governed Portfolio 4 RL Governed Portfolio 5 RL Governed Portfolio 6 RL Governed Portfolio 7 RL Governed Portfolio 8 RL Governed Portfolio 9 RL GRIP 1
(l)
(s) (l)
(s) (l)
(s)
RSMR Rfolio Defensive RSMR Rfolio Cautious RSMR Rfolio Prudent RSMR Rfolio Balanced RSMR Rfolio Growth RSMR Rfolio Dynamic RSMR Rfolio Adventurous RSMR Rfolio Income RSMR Rfolio SRI Cautious RSMR Rfolio SRI Balanced RSMR Rfolio SRI Dynamic
Russell Investments Secure Portfolio Russell Investments Cautious Portfolio Russell Investments Conservative Portfolio Russell Investments Moderate Portfolio Russell Investments Balanced Portfolio Russell Investments Progressive Portfolio Russell Investments Adventurous Portfolio Russell Investments Growth Portfolio Russell Investments Aggressive Portfolio Russell Investments Aggressive Plus Russell Investments Defensive Assets Fund Russell Investments Real Assets Fund Russell Investments UK Growth
Russell Investments International Growth Russell Investments MA Growth 1
Russell Investments MA Growth 2
Russell Investments MA Growth 3
Russell Investments MA Growth 4
Russell Investments MA Growth 5
Russell Investments MA Income
Governed Portfolios
                                                                                                                                                          RL GRIP 2
RL GRIP 3
RL GRIP 4
RL GRIP 5
RLP Deposit
RLP Global High Yield Bond RLP Global Managed
RLP Long (15 yr) Corporate Bond RLP Long (15 yr) Gilt
RLP Long (15 yr) Index Linked
RLP Medium (10 yr) Corporate Bond RLP Medium (10 yr) Gilt
RLP Medium (10 yr) Index Linked RLP Property
RLP Short (5 yr) Corporate Bond RLP Short (5 yr) Gilt
RLP Short (5 yr) Index Linked
RLP Short Duration Global High Yield RLP Sterling Extra Yield Bond
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       ]]></page><page Index="52" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Conservative Portfolio Defensive Portfolio Moderate Portfolio Progressive Portfolio Positive Portfolio
Positive Plus Portfolio Adventurous Portfolio Adventurous Plus Portfolio
Pension Portfolio 1
Pension Portfolio 2 Pension Portfolio 3 Pension Portfolio A Pension Portfolio B Pension Portfolio 4 Pension Portfolio C Pension Portfolio 5 Premier Pension Portfolio 1 Premier Pension Portfolio 2 Premier Pension Portfolio 3 Premier Pension Portfolio A Premier Pension Portfolio B Premier Pension Portfolio 4 Premier Pension Portfolio C Premier Pension Portfolio 5
Santander Atlas 3 Santander Atlas 4 Santander Atlas 5 Santander Atlas 6 Santander Atlas 7 Santander Atlas Income
Cautious
Moderately Cautious
Cautious
Income
Moderately Cautious Balanced
Moderately Adventurous Adventurous
Personal Injury
Balanced Moderately Adventurous Adventurous
Synaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:
Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation
Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder
MM Diversity
MM Diversity Balanced MM Diversity Income
MM Diversity Tactical
MM International
MM UK Growth
Mixed Distribution Fund Global Multi Asset Income Dynamic Multi Asset Managed Balanced
]]></page><page Index="53" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ S&W Defensive Portfolio - 3
S&W Defensive Income Portfolio - 4 S&W Balanced Income Portfolio - 5 S&W Balanced Growth Portfolio - 6 S&W Growth Portfolio - 7
S&W Dynamic Growth Portfolio - 8
Thesis Optima Income Thesis Optima Balanced Thesis Optima Growth Thesis Collectives 1 of 7 Thesis Collectives 2 of 7 Thesis Securities 3 of 7 Thesis Securities 4 of 7 Thesis Securities 5 of 7 Thesis Securities 6 of 7 Thesis Securities 7 of 7
Commercial Freehold Fund
MyFolio Market I
MyFolio Market II
MyFolio Market III
MyFolio Market IV
MyFolio Market V
MyFolio Managed I
MyFolio Managed II
MyFolio Managed III
MyFolio Managed IV
MyFolio Managed V
MyFolio Multi-Manager I
MyFolio Multi-Manager II
MyFolio Multi-Manager III MyFolio Multi-Manager IV MyFolio Multi-Manager V MyFolio Managed Income I MyFolio Managed Income II MyFolio Managed Income III MyFolio Managed Income IV MyFolio Managed Income V MyFolio Multi-Manager Income I MyFolio Multi-Manager Income II MyFolio Multi-Manager Income III MyFolio Multi-Manager Income IV MyFolio Multi-Manager Income V
Vanguard LifeStrategy 20% Vanguard LifeStrategy 40% Vanguard LifeStrategy 60% Vanguard LifeStrategy 80% Vanguard LifeStrategy 100%
]]></page><page Index="54" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                               Portfolios
       HC Verbatim Portfolio 3
HC Verbatim Portfolio 4
HC Verbatim Portfolio 5 Growth HC Verbatim Portfolio 6
HC Verbatim Portfolio 7
HC Verbatim Portfolio 5 Income
                                                             VDS
      VDSJH3 VDSJH4 VDSJH5 VDSJH6 VDSJH7 VDSJH8 VDS RSMR 2 VDS RSMR 3 VDS RSMR 4 VDS RSMR 5 VDS RSMR 6 VDS RSMR 7 VDS RSMR 8 VDS RSMR 9 VDS RSMR 10 VDS TCF 3 VDS TCF 4 VDS TCF 5 VDS TCF 6 VDS TCF 7 VDS TCF 8 VDS S&W 3 VDS S&W 4 VDS S&W 5 VDS S&W 6 VDS S&W 7 VDS S&W 8 VDSHR3 VDSHR4 VDSHR5 VDSHR6 VDSHR7 VDSHR8
                                                                                          RSMR
      RSMR Model Portfolio 2 RSMR Model Portfolio 3 RSMR Model Portfolio 4 RSMR Model Portfolio 5 RSMR Model Portfolio 6 RSMR Model Portfolio 7 RSMR Model Portfolio 8 RSMR Model Portfolio 9 RSMR Model Portfolio 10
                                                                                               Total Clarity
      HC Verbatim Multi-Index Portfolio 3 HC Verbatim Multi-Index Portfolio 4 HC Verbatim Multi-Index Portfolio 5 HC Verbatim Multi-Index Portfolio 6
                                       (s) These portfolios were constructed with short investment timelines (5 year) in mind.
(l) These portfolios were constructed with longer investment timelines (15 year) in mind. Otherwise Synaptic Risk Ratings assume a 10 year investment horizon. You should consult Royal London directly for further information before recommending.
About the service: Synaptic Risk Ratings are worked out by analysing the underlying asset classes within the fund or portfolio. Synaptic Software have requested asset allocation information from participating providers in a specific format aligned to the risk framework of the system. These asset classes are used by the model to determine the risk rating, a process that may result in a level of approximation though in most cases this will be insignificant. It is also possible that certain asset classes may not be represented exactly in the manner that providers would prefer.
Reasonable endeavours are made to provide accuracy and consistency, however neither participating providers nor Synaptic Software can be held responsible for any errors or omissions. No recommendation should be made solely on the basis of the Synaptic Risk Ratings, and additional research should be undertaken for any case. This service is intended for use by investment professionals only.
]]></page><page Index="55" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[      SYNAPTIC RISK
Provides fund and portfolio risk ratings underpinned by the industry’s leading risk expertise
                        Synaptic Risk is an integral part of the Synaptic Suite available to all financial advisers. Offers objective research to complement your firm’s qualitative fund analysis.
 • ATRQ - The industry’s most widely used Attitude to Risk Questionnaire
• Risk Ratings table - a comprehensive table of the providers’ funds and portfolios represented in the ratings, available to download and/or print
• Risk Fact Sheets - all participating DFM, managed or model portfolio, multi-asset or other funds have unique fact sheets, these show risk ratings in decimalised format, risk metrics from the stochastic modelling and asset allocation data
•
• •
An objective risk measure for your investment recommendations - achieved via access to the industry’s leading stochastic engine from Moody’s Analytics
Better advice outcomes - from superior risk analysis and management
Achieve ‘Informed’ consent – quantify possible investment loss and gain using a meaningful and consistent measurements of risk
RISK RATING4 RISK RATING5
You can use the Synaptic Risk Ratings to meet FCA requirements around risk and present to clients using attractive and comprehensive risk metrics.
          SYNAPTIC SYNAPTIC
RISK RATING1 RISK RATING2
SYNAPTIC
RISK RATING3
SYNAPTIC SYNAPTIC
 Cautious
 Moderately Cautious
  Balanced
Moderately Adventurous
  Adventurous
   The Synaptic Risk proposition offers the leading risk analysis in a simple, complete package to assist your compliance and ensure buy-in from your clients. This will compliment any qualitative or volatility based research or analysis that you may be relying upon. And its free!
 Eric Armstrong, Client Director, Synaptic Software Limited
 For more information about Synaptic Risk please visit www.synaptic.co.uk or call 0800 783 4477
                                   What does it include?
How does it work ?
What difference will it make to my clients?
]]></page><page Index="56" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                 Income protection made easy
9 reasons why we’re di erent
                No automatic medical underwriting limits at any age
Only 1 year UK residency required
Hazardous pursuits considered
       Generous BMI limits
Reviewable exclusions
Type 2 Diabetes considered
   Maximum bene t £60,000
Guaranteed income level
Keeping life colourful
 holloway.co.uk
Premium discounts considered
 0800 716 654 We’re here to help.  advisers@holloway.co.uk
Contact us.
Holloway Friendly is the trading name of The Original Holloway Friendly Society Ltd. Holloway Friendly is registered and incorporated under the Friendly Societies Act 1992, registered No. 145F. Registered o ce: Holloway Friendly, Holloway House, 71 Eastgate Street, Gloucester, GL1 1PW. Authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority and the Prudential Regulation Authority. FRN 109986.
]]></page></pages></Search>