<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="56"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Connection
                           Issue:
Q4 2019
 Selection of industry features for the professional adviser
  (pre-empting) the state of the adviser nation
Steve Nelson, the lang cat
Why defence makes sense
Jason Borbora-Sheen & John Stopford, Investec Asset Management
To ESG or not to ESG? That is the question
Gareth Harries, HSBC Global Asset Management
How do we make life ‘better’?
Jacqui Gillies, Guardian
 >> Bestpracticeforfundselection.Smith&Williamson
>> Thegeopoliticsbehindoil.Fidelity
>> EstateTrust.KingsCourtTrust
>> Macropain,marketgain.Invesco
>> ThePariahStockmarket.RaynerSpencerMills
>> Investorsarevotingwiththeirfeet.VanguardAssetManagement
>> Achievingtheperfectblendinretirement.NOVIA
>> PensionFreedom.CharlesStanley
>> What to do with the 40%. Waverton
>> Robo:friendorfoe?Munnypot
 FREE
  Avoiding panic
John Husselbee,Verbatim
Download the Synaptic Risk White Paper at www.synaptic.co.uk/risk
Features Synaptic Risk table inside, plus:
• You are lost without costs
Eric Armstrong delves into Comparator
• MiFID requires us to look again at investment risk measurement Eric Armstrong discusses risk measures & MiFID
• Webline Play is not just for Christmas ...
Paul Quarendon explores the latest member of the Synaptic range
                                                                        ]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                For financial adviser use only. Not approved for use with customers.
It’s always planning for whatever’s next
And protecting what matters right now
We know you’re committed to supporting your clients in every area of life. That’s why we’re so proud to keep on supporting you. Together, we can offer comprehensive protection that prepares them for whatever tomorrow brings – and fits with the life they have today.
Find out more at aviva-for-advisers.co.uk
Protection. It’s our lives
Aviva Life & Pensions UK Limited. Registered in England No. 3253947. Registered Office: Aviva, Wellington Row, York, YO90 1WR. Authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority and the Prudential Regulation Authority. Member of the Association of British Insurers. Firm Reference Number 185896.
PT15991 09/2019
        ]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  Avoiding panic 4 John Husselbee,Verbatim
(pre-empting) the state of the adviser nation 6 Steve Nelson, the lang cat
Why defence makes sense 8 Jason Borbora-Sheen & John Stopford,
Investec Asset Management
To ESG or not to ESG? That is the question 10 Gareth Harries, HSBC Global Asset Management
(UK) Limited
Best practice for fund selection 12 Mickey Morrissey, Smith & Williamson
The geopolitics behind oil 14 Ayesha Akbar, Fidelity
Estate Trust 15 Neil Scott, Kings Court Trust
Macro pain, market gain 16 John Pellegry, Invesco
The Pariah Stockmarket 18 Robin Ghosh, Rayner Spencer Mills
Investors are voting with their feet 20 Vanguard Asset Management
Achieving the perfect blend in retirement 22 Paul Boston, Novia
Pension Freedom 24 John Porteous, Charles Stanley
What to do with the 40% 26 Luke Hyde-Smith,Waverton
Knowing Me: Paul Quarendon, Knowing You: 28 Tiina Stephens. A-ha!
Synaptic Software Limited
Don’t be a lobster pot. How? 32 Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software Limited
Synaptic Risk Table 36
Webline Play is not just for Christmas, 50 it’s for Life ...
Paul Quarendon, Synaptic Software Limited
How do we make life ‘better’? 52 Jacqui Gillies, Guardian
Robo: friend or foe? 54 Andrew Fay, Munnypot
 3
 2020 will see Synaptic’s new software launch
CONTENTS
 Contact Details
Synaptic Software Limited
Fusion 1, Parkway, Solent Business Park Whiteley, Hampshire PO15 7AA
Sales: 0800 783 4477
To sign up for Connection magazine visit
www.synaptic.co.uk
All editorial or advertising enquiries should be directed to:
Eric Armstrong
eric.armstrong@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882994
Sarah Miller
marketing@synaptic.co.uk 0800 783 4477
Christmas is a natural break in the rhythm for any business, and MiFID and other reforms that have rocked financial services mean that the forthcoming break is more welcome than ever. I think however that challenges have been met by the resilience and quality of the work that is going on in our industry generally, and that quality is evidenced in the contributions in this publication.
For Synaptic, Christmas marks a more significant transition than usual, as we will have completed the design and most of
the testing for our new software, which we refer to as Synaptic 2.0. We were lucky to be backed by our parent who recognised the demand for 21st Century quality applications. Given our profile of technology, software
and financial services, significant resources have been deployed to assist us in creating
a solution capable of automating the due diligence and research required from firms to meet their MiFID obligations in full. The new software reflects the MiFID approach and is designed to help configure and deliver a firm’s Central Investment Proposition.
It is a bold ambition, and one that has the potential to improve the options for not
only regulated firms providing advice, but also platforms, product providers and asset managers of all types seeking to improve how our new software proposition is deployed. Furthermore, we have designed solutions to complement a firm’s back office and improve the quality of data available.
We have a diverse range of firms working with us to bring our ideas to life in services of their business processes. We are of course keen to hear from anyone in respect of what our innovation and investment may mean to them. So, let us know what you think.
Eric Armstrong
Editor
  If you no longer wish to receive a copy of this publication, please email marketing@synaptic.co.uk
The Connection magazine is published by Synaptic Software Limited. The views expressed throughout do not necessarily reflect the views of Synaptic or any other party affiliated to Synaptic, and no liability can be assumed for the accuracy or completeness of the content, nor should any of the content be used as the sole basis of any advice offered or received.
Content is offered on an information only basis, and intended only for an audience of professional advisers regulated by the FCA. Content is published with all rights reserved and any reproduction of content, wholly or in part, can be made with the written permission of the publishers. This applies to all forms of the magazine - digital and print, and any part thereof.
]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  4
 Avoiding Panic
  John Husselbee | Co-Fund Manager | HC Verbatim Portfolio Growth Funds
As an industry, investment is certainly not short of data; the challenge can come when interpreting that information as so many of us fall into the traditional behavioural traps.
There is a basic equation about creating panic that goes as follows: high stakes plus major events where the causes are confusing or unknown can lead to some irrational behaviour, even among the supposedly smartest people.
In recent months, we have seen plenty of this with fears around Brexit and trade wars repeatedly pushing investors into decisions that could be potentially detrimental to their long-term wealth. Political volatility has contributed to this environment, with this panic mode spreading across the supposed governing class in recent months.
In forming his government, Boris Johnson dismissed 11 senior ministers and accepted the resignations of six others – described by MP Nigel Evans as “not so much a reshuffle as a summer’s day massacre”. The mass dismissal was the most extensive Cabinet reorganisation without a change in ruling party in post-war Britain, exceeding the seven Cabinet ministers dismissed in Harold Macmillan’s ‘Night of the Long Knives’ in 1962.
Meanwhile, in the 2017 to 2022 Parliament (so far), around 50 MPs have changed party affiliation (with several switching more
than once), either voluntarily or through expulsion. That compares to just six in New Labour’s first term in office from 1997 to 2001 and 18 during its controversial second term, a period that included the Second Gulf war and its aftermath.
Before looking at what this febrile environment means for investors, it is worth recognising this behaviour is littered through human history (with a tip of the hat here to US commentator Morgan Housel). Take a trip back to early sixteenth century London for example, where we can see this panic equation in full effect.
In the 1520s, the major astrologers of the day were predicting a huge flood would engulf London, based on something known as the Grand Conjunction, when all the planets would align and cause huge tides. They had an exact date for this – 1 February 1524 – and this led to a huge exodus from the city, largely those with the financial
capacity to do so, with figures showing a drop in the population from 120,000 in 1523 to 80,000 the following year.
As we know, this flood never materialised, highlighting the panicked behaviour that can come from misinterpreting data. There have been significant floods in the capital in the subsequent centuries however, most recently in 1928 and 1953, leading to the introduction of the Thames Barrier in Woolwich in 1982. Since then, the barrier has been in frequent use, closing more than 50 times in 2013-14 for example, and we would see this as a strong example of risk management. Prepare for all conditions with a well-diversified portfolio rather than panicking and running for the hills at the first sign of troubling data.
A couple more examples add some gloss. Few of you, I suspect, will have heard of Archibald Hill, a pioneering physiologist who won a Nobel prize for his work on the production of heat and mechanical work
in muscles. Hill’s work with professional athletes worked out exactly how fast each one could run based on their physiology but
 ]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 5
  Focusing on the wrong data or misinterpreting the growing amount of market noise can send investors running for the hills in fear of a flood while we continue to ignore the noise as much as possible and stay invested.
ultimately proved an ineffective predictor of success on the track as it fails to take the emotional side of competition into account.
A similar story can be read across to investment when attempting to work out future equity market returns. Calculating returns requires three basic elements and two of these are easily accessible in the shape of dividend yield and earnings growth. The problem comes with the third of the trio, change in valuation, as this is where sentiment and the proverbial animal spirits come into play.
Another name few people are likely to
have heard of is Hungarian mathematician Abraham Wald, another figure who highlighted the importance of looking at data in different ways. Part of the Statistical Research Group at Columbia University during the Second World War, Wald was among those asked to find ways to minimise bomber losses to enemy fire.
Officers came to Wald with what they felt was useful information – most of the bullet holes were in the fuselage and very few in the engines so surely extra armour should
be concentrated on this area of greatest need where the planes were getting hit the most. Wald turned this on its head and said that in fact, the extra armour should not go where the bullet holes are but where they are missing: on the engines.
His insight was to ask where the missing holes were – and the answer was on the missing planes. The reason planes were coming back with fewer hits to the engine is that those taking damage in that area were not getting back at all: the large number returning with a bullet-riddled fuselage was strong evidence that hits to this part of
the plane could (and therefore should) be tolerated.
What all these stories show is the dangers of misinterpreting data and we continue
to warn against in the increasingly short- termist mindset of many investors. One of our key roles as a multi-asset manager is sifting through the masses of data produced by the investment industry to find a core
of managers we believe can add long-term value – and we continue to repeat the message that focusing too much on short- term performance numbers and persistency of returns can lead to major mistakes.
As we wrote in a recent piece, recent
data from Morningstar showed that from 1926 to 2018, US stocks owed all their outperformance to just 51 months, or less than 5% – and if investors had owned those companies for all 1,063 months apart from those 51, they would have failed to beat cash.
Even for the very best funds – the top 10% of all those that beat their benchmarks over 15 years to the end of October 2018 – the outperformance was due to just 16 months of excess returns, one year and four months out of 15 years.
For us, this continues to stress the important of our mantra than consistency of performance is impossible for fund managers but consistency of process is essential. Focusing on the wrong data or misinterpreting the growing amount of market noise can send investors running for the hills in fear of a flood while we continue to ignore the noise as much as possible and stay invested.
John Husselbee is the co-fund manager for the HC Verbatim Portfolio Growth Fund range, part of the Verbatim range of risk- managed multi-asset investment solutions.
To find out more about Verbatim visit www.verbatimassetmanagement.co.uk or contact us on 0808 12 40 007.
The value of investments and any income from them can go down as well as up and
is not guaranteed. Your clients could get back less than they originally invested.
Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The portfolios’ investments are subject to normal fluctuations and other risks inherent when investing in securities. Verbatim Asset Management has taken
due care and attention in preparing this document, which is solely for the use of professional advisers. Verbatim cannot be held responsible for any inaccuracies arising out of information detailed within and will not accept liability for any loss arising out of or in connection with its use. This article is for information only and should not be deemed as advice.
  ]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  6
           (pre-empting) the state of the adviser nation
  Steve Nelson | Head of Research | the lang cat
Hello again. Last time round you may recall that I used this column to talk about something completely different; mental health in the workplace. It’s to the good people at Synaptic’s credit that they gave me free reign to talk about a difficult subject.
This time round it’s back to familiar subject territory but I’m still going to play with convention and do a different kind of article.
In late 2018 the lang cat launched its inaugural adviser census work. Called ‘State of the Adviser Nation’ it gathered data and opinion from 235 of the very finest minds from all throughout the advice profession. Planners, compliance, admin, investment management, advisers, paraplanners - irrespective of role, we wanted to hear their views towards many aspects of the advice profession and the wider financial services sector that we all know and love.
As I write this, the second wave of this research has just gone live in the field but when the time comes to write my next article, we’ll be sat on the next mountain
of insight from the sequel. So, I’m going to turn the format on its head and make some predictions as to what the results are going to be whilst revisiting some of the conclusions from last time round. Then, next article, I’ll take a look at how hopelessly wrong I was,
or indeed how much I have my finger on the pulse. Nostradamus or not-so-brightus? Time will tell.
Centralise, rinse, repeat
Last time round, the overwhelming majority (around 85% or so) of respondents said
that their firm ran a centralised investment proposition (CIP). When asked about a centralised retirement proposition (CRP) though, the majority stated that there was no real change in the investment vehicles used. Instead, it was all about having a different
set of processes. Increased use of cashflow, more in-depth review process, use of cash management and core income provision were key, as opposed to any meaningful change in the actual investment ranges used. Based on recent conversations with advisers I reckon this pattern will hold firm and I also reckon a year is too short a length of time for such a complex issue like this to shift. That’s prediction #1.
You need educating
One of our themes in last year’s study looked at trust in the sector and how we could try and foster a better level of trust with the general public towards the work we all do.
 We got people to rate each platform in the sector based on their gut instinct towards their reputation, irrespective of whether they used them or not (i.e. their ‘favourably’). We got a huge range of responses, commensurate with the various levels of momentum or indeed disruption that each platform was facing.
 ]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 7
            One of the parts of the advice profession that interests me the most is how firms stitch together the various bits and bobs of software that they need to use to form their advice processes; back office, cashflow, investment research, reporting, platforms and risk profiling being the main suspects among more than a few others.
We presented participants with a range of statements and asked them to rate how strongly they agreed or disagreed with them. These ranged from whether we’re all tarred with the same brush from some questionable behaviour at certain large organisations (i.e. the banking sector) to whether the level of trust is actually better than we all believe. Surprisingly (to me anyway) one theme that came through strongly was the need for financial education in schools.
This year, we’re presenting people with a range of statements in the context of the advice
gap in the UK. One statement proposes that financial education would help people realise the benefit of financial advice. My prediction is that this will come through strongly again, despite this being a topic of fierce debate and despite me not being sure if I agree with it. In particular, being married to a teacher, I can see the challenges of adding yet-another-thing into the curriculum.
Can I ask a favour?
The lang cat being the lang cat, we naturally asked a few things about our heartland;
the platform sector. In one particularly interesting section, we got people to rate each platform in the sector based on their gut instinct towards their reputation, irrespective of whether they used them or not (i.e. their ‘favourably’). We got a huge
range of responses, commensurate with
the various levels of momentum or indeed disruption that each platform was facing. We’re asking the same this time round and my prediction is that overall mean average scores will have reduced year on year. I think there are pockets of success in the sector (AJ Bell and Parmenion are flying, Transact are Transact, Aviva are recovering) but by and large it’s been a tricky old year. Naturally, I hope I’m wrong with this one.
CTRL-ALT-DELETE
One of the parts of the advice profession that interests me the most is how firms stitch together the various bits and bobs of software that they need to use to form their advice processes; back office, cashflow, investment research, reporting, platforms and risk profiling being the main suspects among more than a few others. Last year’s study threw up a few clear conclusions:
• the majority of advice firms have a preference to use ‘off-platform’ best of breed tools as opposed to integrated software;
• back office tools are the most embedded within a business and the least likely to change; and
• most firms stated that they review their platform adoption at least once a year.
My prediction is that I reckon all of these will hold firm. But from my conversations with advisers, I think we’ll hear more grumbles from a data and reporting perspective. I speak to lots of firms who have grown increasingly tired of the disconnect between something as simple (from a client perspective) as cashflow modelling and the increasingly rigid reporting obligations they have. I speak to few advisers who are completely happy with the output they get from providers and I believe there’s huge opportunity there for software to do a lot better.
So, there we have it. I’ll be back next quarter with a report card on how I’ve done on the prediction front, along with other interesting headlines that crop up.
See you next quarter.
Visit www.langcatfinancial.co.uk for more from Steve and the rest of the lang cats.
  ]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  8
 Why defence makes sense
 Jason Borbora-Sheen and John Stopford | Co-Portfolio Managers | Investec Diversified Income Fund
AT A GLANCE...
• The worst drawdowns typically happen in recessions. Investors have experienced even worse drawdowns in this bull market
than previous ones.
• This is particularly harmful to investors with nearer-term horizons, who are relying on assets they have built up previously,
such as retirees who need attractive, sustainable income in their later years – especially now they’re living longer.
• Why is this happening now? We believe a changing market structure caused by slower economic growth, central bank
intervention and more passive investors in the market could be the culprit.
Recession obsession
Many commentators are talking about an increasing risk of recession. Our own recession probability models agree, with Figure 1 showing more than a 50% chance of a recession happening in the next two years. As recessions are typically associated with much worse market returns, this increasing risk has led investors to look for defensive strategies that emphasise drawdown management.
We believe that even outside of periods of increased recession risk, defence makes good sense for investors – particularly for those whose investment horizon is limited
US recessions and Investec two year ahead recession probability model
Misbehaving drawdowns
We think the nature of markets has evolved since the global financial crisis. Our analysis of markets since 1987 (the year of the Black Monday crash) shows that before 2009, outside of the ‘bear markets’ often associated with recessions – when stock markets drop 20% or more from recent highs – investors tended to see drawdowns that were ‘well-behaved’: an equal weighted bond-equity portfolio suffered very few drawdowns of more than 5%, and never as much as 10%.
By contrast, in the current cycle we have so far seen six episodes of more than 5% drawdown including one of more than 10% – an unprecedented frequency and magnitude of drawdown for a bull market over the last 30 years. This can be seen in Figure 2.
Drawdown of an equal weighted bond/equity portfolio
  Forecasts are inherently limited and not a reliable indicator of future results. Source: Investec Asset Management, 31 August 2019.
Source: Bloomberg and Investec Asset Management, 31 July 2019. Drawdown of equal weighted portfolio refers to MSCI ACWI & WGBI.
 ]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 9
  Source: Redburn and Investec Asset Management, 31 August 2019.
 Is a changing market structure to blame?
We think there may be multiple drivers of this increased fragility across asset classes:
• Therateofeconomicgrowthhasbeensloweroverthiscyclethaninpastcycles,meaning the global economy has teetered closer to the edge of recession (and therefore to the risk of severe drawdowns) than it did before,
• Todealwiththis,centralbankmarketinterventionhasbecomemoresignificantandcreative than it was previously, potentially leading to a ‘feast or famine’ environment for liquidity,
• Theabilityofprivatesectorbankstoabsorbriskhasbeencurtailedbyregulationand shareholder demand for their business models to become more dependable,
• PassiveETFs/trackerindicesmakeupagreaterproportionoftheinvestorbase,potentially leading to more herding into and out of positions, thereby exacerbating market moves.
The impact of these changes is evident in the number of ‘flash crashes’ – instances when asset values changed significantly over a short period of time – seen in this bull market. These flash crashes aren’t just confined to equity markets (as can be seen in the timeline) and are likely a consequence of liquidity becoming more susceptible to drying up than before.
Why defence makes sense
The Investec Diversified Income Fund focuses on defensive returns, which we define as having a lower downside capture than upside. We believe this focus makes sense irrespective of the market backdrop to investments.
This chart shows the peak-to-trough performance of the Fund and its peers in the most severe recent drawdown episodes. The blue line shows the least dramatic falls during these challenging periods, meaning our approach shielded against capital losses more so than any of our comparative peers. By then ‘un-hedging’ risk when appropriate, we were able to recover losses more quickly and so avoided the worst of the negative impact.
Peak to trough performance during drawdown episodes
Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future results, losses may be made. Performance is net of fees (NAV based, including ongoing charges), gross income reinvested (net of UK basic rate tax pre 5 April 2016) in GBP.
Calendar year % returns for the Fund, Index and Sector, respectively 2018: 0.41, -9.47, -2.97. 2017: 4.82, 13.10, 3.89. 2016: 5.92, 16.75, 2.18. 2015: 1.97, 0.98, 2.30. 2014: 5.32, 1.18, 3.15. 2013: 6.19, 20.81, 7.93. Source: Morningstar, 31 August 2019.
Conclusion
For investors, the benefit of investing in
a defensive fund during a recessionary period should be clear, as the aim to reduce drawdowns in significantly falling markets makes it easier to regain capital in the future.
However, with market structure changes leading to the increased frequency and magnitude
of bull market drawdowns and flash crashes,
a defensive strategy has an important role in
an investor’s portfolio throughout the cycle, particularly for those investors with nearer-term liabilities and needs.
We believe this is why defence always makes sense.
For further information, please visit
www.investecassetmanagement.com/DIF
  The value of investments, and any income generated from them, can fall as well as rise. Where charges are taken from capital, this may constrain future growth. Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future results. Investment objectives and performance targets are subject to change and may not necessarily be achieved, losses may be made. The Fund may invest more than 35% of its assets in securities issued or guaranteed by a permitted sovereign entity, as defined in the definitions section of the Fund’s prospectus.
]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[          10
                      To ESG or not to ESG? That is the question
 Gareth Harries | Director Nationals & Networks | HSBC Global Asset Management
Greta Thunberg, Extinction Rebellion, David Attenborough and extreme weather events are just a number of things that have raised awareness of the impact of climate change. These have made us consider the implications of everyday choices we make in areas such as food, fashion and transport. But what does it mean for investment choices, how do these affect IFAs and what can asset managers do to help?
Whilst negative publicity has made people question the effect of their investment impact, the question remains ‘what changes should be made to a portfolio of investments?’. Against the backdrop of ethical investing with approaches such
as negative and positive screening, the proliferation of Environmental, Social and Governance (ESG) products has only added to the list of questions with a multitude
of metrics/methodologies which may put people off investing in them altogether.
Then vs now
In the last 30 years or so, we’ve seen large shifts in many different areas of society
as we move towards cleaner and healthier solutions. Unsubsidised renewable energy is now most frequently the cheapest source of energy generation according to a report by the International Renewable Energy Agency (IRENA). We’ve seen the smoking
ban and the 5p charge for plastic bags (and the subsequent use of re-usable ones) which now seem standard. Whilst many of these changes may appear ‘sensible’ it could be argued ‘why wasn’t this done before?’. In fact, whilst there is pressure to reduce plastic further (e.g. single use plastic straws) some might say we still lag behind some countries and their war on plastic. For example, Rwanda bans all plastic bags from entering their country, and that includes the security plastic you may have paid to have your suitcase wrapped in as you left the UK!
The changing consumer
The world’s consumer is changing, meaning companies, IFAs and asset managers need to be aware of how this impacts investment opportunities. Social and environmental concerns that have risen to prominence
in recent years, from the aforementioned headline grabbing protests to more small
scale activities such as plogging (more on this later). This groundswell of sentiment will continue to play a bigger role in the decisions of firms, with those that can best adapt being more likely to boost sales, benefit
from good PR and be considered for ESG investments.
Another dimension to consider is the demographic of the consumer. Researchi found that 53% of millennials stated that they often or always buy from companies that make an effort to reduce their environmental impact (vs 27% amongst Boomers). However, a significant finding
in this research was that respondents with children and grandchildren articulated that whilst they had previously placed less value on sustainability issues, a concern for the world younger generations will live in was driving them to consider sustainability more in their lives.
 ]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[        11
                      Whilst there is varied demand across
the demographics, millennials are set to inherit an estimated £1.2 trillion windfall from Boomers in the next 30 years, it’s only a matter of time before it filters into mainstream advice.
Our solution for IFAs
We are able to offer the benefits of our established multi-asset investment approach through a sustainable lens with our HSBC Global Sustainable Multi-Asset Portfolios which prioritise:
(1) effective portfolio diversification,
(2) use of measurable sustainability criteria across all asset classes, and
(3) cost-efficient implementation of the asset allocations.
In common with our other multi-asset solutions, the objective is to maximise risk- adjusted returns with the additional benefit of reducing ESG-related risks.
We believe that sustainability issues can have a material impact on company fundamentals and performance over the longer-term. These issues are linked to opportunities
and risks that financial markets may not be pricing appropriately. ESG scores provide
a way to measure the sustainability of a company, country, index or fund. Carbon intensity provides another dimension when considering sustainable investment as it measures the impact of a company on the environment. By focusing on a combination of these sustainability metrics (i.e. higher ESG score and lower carbon intensity than the market average) portfolio holdings can be tilted towards companies and markets with higher sustainability qualities.
There has been the perception in the past that performance may need to be sacrificed for the benefit of doing good. There is now a growing body of evidence that ESG focused investment does not compromise financial returns and you could even argue that ESG investment is actually a way to future-proof investments because companies that run with ESG principles are more likely to remain
solvent and prosper. To this end, an ESG solution may also be a method of future proofing an adviser business too, as well as accommodating the demands of clients who might be more inclined to invest in a company that is trying to cure cancer as opposed to cause it!
So what is plogging? It’s a term for when
a group of joggers combine their run with picking up litter. Will this change the world? No, but it once again shows the desire of ordinary people to make a difference. As asset managers and IFAs offer investment solutions for this growing sentiment, we
can help to influence companies and have a positive impact on our planet and the people in it. So in answer to the question in the title, I’d argue it’s the former!
The two HSBC Global Multi Asset Sustainable Portfolios (Conservative and Balanced) are risk rated with Synaptic and available on all major platforms.
i TWC Responsible Investment and the Retail Investor: Is the Industry Missing an Open Goal? Online survey, October 2017, n=1,000
ii Study by Sanlam UK http://www.morningstar.co.uk/uk/ news/169114/millennials-lead-responsible-investing-movement. aspx
Important information:
For professional clients only.
This commentary is for information purposes only. It is a marketing communication and does not constitute investment advice or a recommendation to any reader of this content to buy or sell investments nor should it be regarded as investment research. It has not
been prepared in accordance with legal requirements designed to promote the independence of investment research and is not subject to any prohibition on dealing ahead of its dissemination.
www.assetmanagement.hsbc.com/uk
Copyright © HSBC Global Asset Management (UK) Limited 2019. All rights reserved.
Any views expressed were held at the
time of preparation and are subject to change without notice. While any forecast, projection or target where provided is indicative only and not guaranteed in any way. HSBC Global Asset Management
(UK) Limited accepts no liability for any failure to meet such forecast, projection
or target. These portfolios are sub-funds
of HSBC OpenFunds an Open Ended Investment Company that is authorised in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority. The Authorised Corporate Director and Investment Manager is HSBC Global Asset Management (UK) Limited.
All applications are made on the basis of the prospectus, Key Investor Information Document (KIID), Supplementary Information Document (SID) and most recent annual and semiannual report, which can be obtained upon request free of charge from HSBC Global Asset Management
(UK) Limited, 8, Canada Square, Canary Wharf, London, E14 5HQ, UK, or the local distributors.
Investors and potential investors should read and note the risk warnings in the prospectus and relevant KIID and additionally, in the case of retail clients, the information contained in the supporting SID.
Where overseas investments are held the rate of currency exchange may also cause the value of such investments to fluctuate. Investments in emerging markets are by their nature higher risk and potentially more volatile than those inherent in
some established markets. Stock market investments should be viewed as a medium to long term investment and should be held for at least five years.
To help improve our service and in the interests of security we may record and/
or monitor your communication with us. Approved for issue in the UK by HSBC Global Asset Management (UK) Limited, who are authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.
  ]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  12
 Best practice for fund selection and monitoring
  Mickey Morrissey | Partner and Head of Distribution | Smith & Williamson Investment Management
Parts of the fund management industry are facing a turbulent
time. While some have taken this as a sign of the inherent flaws in active management, we believe it should instead serve to illuminate best practice in the selection and ongoing monitoring of funds. In particular, it should finally lay to rest the idea that selecting funds is just about finding a manager with a good track record and sticking to them like glue.
Recent events serve to highlight a number of under-the-radar elements of fund selection and monitoring. These elements may seem like a side-show for much of the time, but recent developments in the industry have shown how important they can be at certain moments in preventing losses for clients.
Liquidity
Portfolio liquidity is not a key concern for most funds. However, when it becomes
an issue, it can have a profound effect
on performance and may even prevent unitholders temporarily getting their money back in the short term.
In selecting investments, we always consider whether the liquidity of a fund’s portfolio matches the liquidity being offered to unitholders. To our mind, open-ended funds with daily dealing should not be holding
illiquid assets. Investment companies are more robust vehicles for areas such as private equity, infrastructure or commercial property. While the discount on an investment company may widen due to selling, investors can still get their capital back, but most importantly the manager
is not a forced seller of the assets in the portfolio for this to occur. This is critical for ongoing shareholders who are in for the long-term and willing to ride out short-term price volatility.
With this in mind, we believe our having expertise in closed-ended funds is a real advantage. It means that investors can
get access to these illiquid assets – some
of which offer real diversification and growth potential – but without some of the associated risks.
Equally, it is worth bearing in mind that liquidity is not static – it can change as an asset class falls in and out of favour. Liquidity will often dry up in a bear market. As such, it’s important to monitor it regularly. We
are yet to see a sustained fall in markets since the Global Financial Crisis, but when one does invariably occur, we believe that liquidity in all areas, from sovereign bonds to emerging market equities, will be tested due to lower liquidity on bank trading books.
Fund flows
Fund flows, both in and out of a fund,
can change the make-up of a portfolio. Significant inflows can force managers to compromise their investment process, buying companies that they wouldn’t otherwise. Outflows can force them to sell their most popular and liquid holdings, leaving a rump of less liquid or underperforming assets. In
 ]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 13
  Investors need regular contact with the fund manager to discuss any problems openly and honestly. Dealing with a difficult situation can be resource-intensive and may require daily monitoring. It helps to have ready access to the fund manager to discuss concerns and formulate a solution.
both cases, fund managers aren’t buying and selling based on those stocks in which they have most conviction. This can create style drift and introduce unwelcome skews into a portfolio.
Equally, fund managers with significant inflows or outflows may find that the market starts to conspire against them. Hedge funds may short stocks in their portfolio, leaving them selling under pressure and exaggerating the falls in their portfolio. Alternatively, those with inflows may find the shares they want to buy are bid up, leaving them paying a higher price.
We are always alert to significant changes
in fund size and also of the concentration
of unitholders in a specific fund. If a fund
has a number of large unitholders, it can be vulnerable to them withdrawing their holding.
Access matters
Investors need regular contact with the fund manager to discuss any problems openly and honestly. Dealing with a difficult situation can be resource-intensive and may require daily monitoring. It helps to have ready access to the fund manager to discuss concerns and formulate a solution.
We value an open dialogue with fund managers, looking at the team dynamic and considering how they interact with their compliance function. We believe that
understanding these elements of a fund manager’s process and resources, leads to better judgements.
Proprietary research
It is easy to get swept along with a popular manager, however, our view is that you
need to do your own research and have independence of thought. This means that
we have the flexibility to adjust our asset allocation or holdings when the situation changes and are not reliant on industry ratings on funds which are often backward looking.
This type of intensive research and monitoring of funds can be difficult and time consuming if you are also meeting the day to day demands of clients. It is our belief that the outsourcing model will go some way
to circumventing the high-profile problems seen in the fund management sector
whilst instilling confidence in the adviser market that there is a robust and repeatable investment process which they can access on behalf of their clients.
For further information, please contact Mickey Morrissey, Head of Distribution
t: 020 7131 4693
e: mickey.morrissey@smithandwilliamson.com w: www.sandwdfm.com
Important information
By necessity, this briefing can only provide
a short overview and it is essential to seek professional advice before applying the contents of this article. No responsibility
can be taken for any loss arising from action taken or refrained from on the basis of this publication. Details correct at time of writing.
Investment does involve risk. The value of investments and the income from them can go down as well as up. The investor may not receive back, in total, the original amount invested. Past performance is not a guide
to future performance. Rates of tax are those prevailing at the time and are subject to change without notice. Clients should always seek appropriate advice from their financial adviser before committing funds for investment. When investments are made in overseas securities, movements in exchange rates may have an effect on the value of that investment. The effect may be favourable or unfavourable.
Smith & Williamson Investment Management LLP is part of the Smith & Williamson group. Smith & Williamson Investment Management LLP is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.
  ]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[     14
              The geopolitics behind oil
 Ayesha Akbar | Co-manager | Fidelity Multi Asset
Oil has a habit of reminding investors of the geopolitical risk premium attached to its price. Following a sophisticated attack on two major facilities in Saudi Arabia, the oil price spiked nearly 20 per cent in September for its largest one day move since the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait in 1990. However, spikes of this nature are significant only if they are sustained - Fidelity Multi Asset take a look at the impact if we see a more meaningful gain in the price over time.
The direct effect of the oil price on the global macroeconomic picture is far from clear. While oil does affect inflation and growth it is far from the primary driver, and higher oil prices can impact countries in very different ways.
A fluid situation
If higher oil prices persist due to major supply shortages this would be a headwind for global growth, but even this would be unlikely to tip the balance on the overall growth trajectory. Similarly, some investors fear the impact of oil on inflation. But while the relatively subdued oil price has certainly contributed to lower inflation since mid-2014, low inflation is a structural issue and oil is not the determining factor here. In the US, a higher oil price does negatively impact the consumer, but it also boosts capital expenditures in the US energy sector, effectively reducing the impact of oil’s inflationary pressures.
That is not to entirely discount the effects of the oil price on growth, but any sustained upward shift would have disparate effects globally. There are two sides to the coin. Firstly, oil producing nations benefit from
higher oil prices, and the currencies of major oil producers like Russia and Canada jumped on the news. Conversely, major consumers
in emerging markets, such as India, South Africa, Turkey, and Indonesia are hurt by a higher oil price (unless this is largely growth rather than supply driven), as this exacerbates current account deficits and weakens already vulnerable currencies. The decline of over
40 per cent in the crude price in the fourth quarter of 2018 was a major tailwind for emerging markets in the early part of this year, and while the price has recovered from the $42 trough, we aren’t seeing prices at the point where they have a major impact.
Saudi Arabia
As with any commodity, supply and demand factors are also very important, and it was fears over supply disruption that led to the spike. However, Saudi Arabia
has significant capacity, and the country’s willingness to maintain supply should not be underestimated. The US also affirmed its commitment to the supply side, with President Donald Trump’s first response to the attack stressing willingness to use the
Strategic Petroleum Reserve “to keep markets well supplied.” The demand side of the equation is a key factor as well. Weaker global growth could very well result in a reduction in demand for petroleum products and minimize the risk of oil prices remaining high.
While the possibility for short-term spikes is never absent, investors should avoid fixating too much on one day moves. It is more important to build resilient portfolios that can withstand the pressures of a price at much higher or much lower levels for a sustained period, instead of trying to predict intraday volatility.
Important information
This information is for investment professionals only and should
not be relied upon by private investors. Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future returns. Investors should note that the views expressed may no longer be current and may have already been acted upon. Changes in currency exchange rates may affect the value of investments in overseas markets. Investments in small and emerging markets can also be more volatile than other more developed markets. Reference to specific securities should not be construed as a recommendation to buy or sell these securities and is included for the purposes of illustration only.
 ]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 15
 How to add value to your business with estate administration
 Neil Scott | Head of Corporate Partnerships | Kings Court Trust
Today it’s important for advisers to act in order to overcome the challenges associated with increases in intergenerational wealth transfers and ageing client banks. Our experience suggests that advisers are looking for ways to retain the funds they currently have under management and introduce new clients into their customer base. Introducing an outsourced, fixed fee estate administration service to your current business model can help you to achieve this.
Estate administration is the process of handling a person’s affairs after they’ve died. It is traditionally thought of as a legal service, though it can now be utilised as
a financial support service. As an adviser, you are responsible for advising your clients throughout their lifetime but this shouldn’t change when they pass away. Their assets still need to be managed effectively and distributed to the next generation; that’s where estate administration comes in.
Kings Court Trust are the UK’s leading specialist provider of probate and estate administration. In this article, Kings Court Trust will explore how introducing estate administration into your service offering will enhance the value of your proposition, give you a significant opportunity to protect funds under management, and provide you with the chance to add new clients to your customer base. This can be achieved with minimal impact on the day-to-day running of your business.
Benefits of outsourcing estate administration with Kings Court Trust
1. Add value to your service proposition
By including estate administration as a key part of your service offering, you are in
the best position to offer your clients and their families support and care during a difficult time. Kings Court Trust works with businesses to develop mutually beneficial partnerships, with a common goal of providing support for your clients.
We can offer your clients a market-leading estate administration service that removes the stress, effort and liability of dealing with their loved one’s affairs themselves. You can, therefore, enhance your proposition and provide your clients with a fully holistic service.
2. Protect funds under management
The UK’s wealth is concentrated in the hands of the older generation. If a proportion of your clients are in the older generation
and you don’t have a strategy in place
to support their families when they pass away, you could end up losing assets under management if these beneficiaries do not become clients. With every referred estate Kings Court Trust administer, we will refer beneficiaries back to your practice. Therefore, you can open the conversation about ongoing advice in a natural and professional way.
3. Gain new clients
On average, there will be three or more beneficiaries named in a Will. Our introduction to the beneficiaries of the estates we administer presents you with
an opportunity to gain new clients and
reduce the average age of your client bank. Additionally, you have the chance to retain the funds from your deceased client and gain new money from the beneficiaries’ own wealth.
If your clients are in need of probate or estate administration advice, please get in touch with Neil Scott by calling 07738 835006
This article was written by Kings Court Trust, an award-winning probate and estate administration provider.
 In the next thirty years, it is predicted that £5.5 trillion will be passed down through the generations, which presents the financial services industry with a huge opportunity.
   ]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  16
 Macro pain, market gain
  John Pellegry | Asian and Emerging Market Equities Product Director | Invesco
World trade is weakening, and regional economic growth is slowing – so how could this be good news for Asian exposure?
World trade is weak. It used to grow twice as fast as global GDP and is now no longer growing. The JPM global manufacturing PMI is now below 50, a sign that industries are contracting. Unsurprising in this context that the IMF is again downgrading its global growth forecast (3% for 2019). All these indicators have hit post-GFC lows.
That’s a difficult backdrop for Asian equities given their strong manufacturing base and large exposure to exports, which in turn tends to affect earnings growth expectations (currently 2% for 2019; 14% for 2020).
The 2019 earnings downgrades have eased but the asset class is still susceptible to swings in sentiment – with trade tensions the obvious overhang. Also, domestically, Asian economies have been slowing, notably China and India given the clamp down on shadow banking which has tightened funding sources for smaller firms. If all this sounds
a bit gloomy, there are two reasons to be optimistic.
Firstly, history shows us that the best returns are to be made following weak points in the cycle and peak pessimism
and there certainly isn’t a lot of optimism for Asia and EM right now. Figure 1 shows the negative correlation between US ISM Manufacturing PMI and subsequent 12 month returns in Asian equities. There’s certainly no guarantee that this pattern will repeat itself, but it shouldn’t necessarily be ignored, especially when combined with relatively low valuations which typically lead
to better future returns. Asia, as measured
by the MSCI Asia ex Japan index, has already underperformed the S&P 500 by 45% over the last 5 years, leading to the steepest P/B valuation discount since 2001 (55% discount). The forward P/E discount is 25%. The P/B ratio of our Asian portfolios is slightly above book value which is unusually low.
Figure 1: Contrarian strategies of buying on low ISM readings have historically led to good subsequent 12 month returns in Asia
 Source: Datastream, as at 30/09/19.
 ]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  17
 History shows us that the best returns are to be made following weak points in the cycle and peak pessimism and there certainly isn’t a lot of optimism for Asia and EM right now.
 Secondly, it is worth keeping in mind that
when data is at its worst, policy action tends to be most significant. We are not contemplating a global coordinated policy response given how self-centered politicians have become but Asia still has some ammunition in the short term and structural drivers in the long term.
Indeed, we have seen a series of interest rate cuts across Asia this year. This has been made easier with the ‘Fed pivot’, allowing Asian central banks to at least match the Fed’s interest rate cuts without compromising their currencies. In fact, Asian currencies had already corrected meaningfully since 2018 making this risk less potent. Non-Asia EM currencies have adjusted even more with Argentina and Turkey well known basket cases.
Also, thanks to prior interest rates hikes and much contained inflationary pressures, Asia’s real interest rates are still positive – around 1 or 2% compared to the negative real rates seen across advanced nations. This provides Asian central banks still some room for manoeuvre.
The People’s Bank of China has already trimmed prime lending rates and cut banks’ reserve requirements (RRR) several times this year. RRR is still a high 13% suggesting more cuts are possible as a way to inject liquidity into the system. The Yuan has also been allowed to depreciate against the US dollar and the trade weighted basket of currencies. The Chinese authorities have shown no appetite to re-lever, let alone bail out the global economy, however, more ‘fine-tuning’ is not out of the question if the unemployment rate deteriorates (currently 5.2% in urban areas).
This could include Fiscal policy action. So far: • In China, around RMB2 trillion of
tax cuts were announced to support consumer demand and manufacturers,
• More recently, the Indian government cut its corporate tax rate from
30% to 22% – providing an uplift
to earnings and boosting India’s competitiveness in the medium
term. The Modi Government is also entertaining the possibility of cutting income taxes as an immediate support to consumption,
• Weakness in global growth still affects Asia (and EM) significantly and that
is unlikely to change anytime soon. However, it is when sentiment and valuations are depressed relative to history and other asset classes that
it’s a good time to re-consider one’s exposure to Asia. The region is likely
to become increasingly prominent in
a more polarized world: it currently represents 1/3 of global GDP; 2/3 of global GDP growth; it is technologically competitive; has a massive consumer base; and is increasingly self-reliant, with China at its epicenter.
We continue to hold a portfolio of around 60 Asian companies who we believe can benefit from Asia’s strong attributes, and we can find opportunity during periods of pessimism.
For more information on our key Asian equity fund, please visit invesco.co.uk/asianfund
Investment risks
The value of investments and any income will fluctuate (this may partly be the result of exchange-rate fluctuations) and investors may not get back the full amount invested.
As a large portion of the strategy is invested in less developed countries, you should
be prepared to accept significantly large fluctuations in value.
Important information
This article is for Professional Clients only and is not for consumer use. All information as at 25 October 2019, unless otherwise stated.
This article is marketing material and is not intended as a recommendation to invest in any particular asset class, security or strategy. Regulatory requirements that require impartiality of investment/investment strategy recommendations are therefore not applicable nor are any prohibitions to trade before publication. The information provided is for illustrative purposes only, it should not be relied upon as recommendations to buy or sell securities.
Where individuals or the business have expressed opinions, they are based on current market conditions, may differ from those of other investment professionals and are subject to change without notice. By accepting this document, you consent to communicate with us in English, unless you inform us otherwise.
Invesco Asset Management Limited, Perpetual Park, Perpetual Park Drive, Henley- on-Thames, Oxfordshire RG9 1HH, UK. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.
 ]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  18
 The Pariah Stock Market
 Robin Ghosh | Portfolio & Research Manager | RSMR
Ever since the UK voted to leave the European Union in the summer of 2016, global investors have looked upon the UK as a pariah stock market with almost continual and indiscriminate selling. A recent survey by Bank of America Merrill Lynch of over 200 global fund managers, found that the UK was the least favoured of the global markets, with a net 28% underweight. Fundamental valuation analysis doesn’t seem to have played a part in this judgement, with a sentiment-driven approach linked to the expected impact of Brexit being much more likely.
 The UK weighting in a global context is quite minor, as it represents 4.75% of the MSCI ACWI Index, so decisions by global managers to allocate away from the region can be easily reached. This option is not as readily available to the UK investor, where UK allocations have historically tended to be up to 40% for a balanced portfolio. The question is, what are the implications of this home market bias for UK investors?
UK Revenues & Global Factors
A typical UK investor is likely to have exposure to the FTSE 100 index, which is a market capitalised, weighted index of the leading companies listed in the UK. This is not the same as gaining exposure to the UK economy, as the London stock market has long been a place for foreign companies to raise capital and list their shares. This is due to ease of raising capital, the strong legal and regulatory framework and the depth
of the capital market. The current market comprises a range of global companies that generate most of their revenues, not from the domestic UK economy, but from global overseas markets. This includes the likes of the oil stocks majors, BP and Royal Dutch Shell, the global drinks company Diageo, and the mining companies BHP Biliton and Rio Tinto. Many of these companies have no UK revenues and are driven by global factors, rather than domestic consideration. To gain exposure to the domestic UK economy, investors may be better looking to mid or smaller cap stocks.
Positioning in a Portfolio
There are many reasons why private investors tend to have a bias to their home market. It makes sense to limit the currency risk and to provide protection against local inflation by having a higher weighting to UK equities. The UK has historically been one of the least volatile stock markets globally and so can be used to dampen risk in the equity element of a portfolio.
Although the Rfolios models have a strategic asset allocation to UK equities, we have
the flexibility to take large overweight or underweight positions if we see value, or if the risks are appropriate. Currently, the UK market is one of the cheapest major stock markets in the world and consequently allows us to gain exposure to a number of quality, global stocks at attractive valuations and a host of undervalued UK domestic companies.
If you’d like to find out more about our Rfolios discretionary portfolios, just drop us a line: enquiries@rsmr.co.uk or call us on 01535 656555.
  There are many reasons why private investors
tend to have a bias to
their home market. It makes sense to limit the currency risk and to provide protection against local inflation by having a higher weighting to UK equities.
  ]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                       Our best ideas for your clients
                                    Rfolios
RSMR independently researched portfolios, risk-rated by Synaptic
 01535 656 555 | enquiries@rsmgroup.co.uk | rsmr.co.uk
Important Notice
This is intended for investment professionals and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons. Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments and any income from them can fall as well as rise, is not guaranteed and your clients may get back less that they invest. RSMR Portfolio Services Limited is a limited company registered in England and Wales under Company number 07137872. Registered office at Number 20, Ryefield Business Park, Belton Road, Silsden BD20 0EE. RSMR Portfolio Services Limited is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority under number 788854. © RSMR 2018. RSMR is a registered Trademark.
 ]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  20
 Investors are voting with their feet on costs
New Vanguard research has highlighted the migration of investors from high-cost investments to lower-cost funds as awareness of the impact of fees on returns grows.
 In many areas of life, the more you pay
for something, the better the product you expect to get. But in investing, there’s no reason to assume that you get more if you pay more. The more you pay in management fees or trading commissions, the less there is earning a potential return.
In contrast with the unpredictable returns from financial markets, cost is one aspect investors can control. And it seems increasing numbers of them are focusing on what
they pay to invest, allowing them to keep a greater share of investment returns.
New Vanguard research has shed light on the extent to which investors in the US are migrating from high-cost investments to lower-cost funds, and the findings could hint at what’s in store for the industry in Europe.
The shift to low cost
The new Vanguard Research Insight highlights a clear trend that is emerging in the US as investors increasingly vote with their feet on investment costs. In a stark message to the industry, net cash flows going back more than a decade demonstrate how more and more investors are taking
control of how much they pay asset managers.
The research shows that, over the past 15 years, investors have displayed a striking preference for low-cost funds over high-cost funds.
Among US equity funds and ETFs, those with the lowest-quartile expense ratios garnered around $1.25 trillion in assets between 2003 and 2018 (see chart 1). This is in marked contrast with the three quartiles of funds with higher expense ratios, which all experienced negative cash flows during the same period.
Chart 1: Relationship between net cash flow and expense-ratio quartile of U.S. equity and fixed income funds and ETFs
The lowest-cost quartile of funds had a median expense ratio of 0.21%, while the higher-cost second, third and fourth quartiles had median expense ratios of 0.72%, 0.95% and 1.49% respectively.
A similar trend is evident in bonds, where nearly all net cash flows into taxable bond funds over the 15-year period went into lower-cost options.
US bond funds and ETFs with the lowest- quartile expense ratios received around $1.48 trillion of inflows. This was some way ahead of the second-lowest cost quartile of funds, which gathered just $110 billion of inflows, while the two quartiles of funds with higher expense ratios suffered net outflows.
  ]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[   A clear trend that is emerging in the US as investors increasingly vote with their feet on investment costs.
21
 Here, median expense ratios ranged from 0.14% for the lowest-cost quartile of bond funds through to 0.45%, 0.63% and 1.07% for the second, third and fourth quartiles respectively.
Why the exodus to low-cost funds? It all comes down to returns.
Here, median expense ratios ranged from 0.14% for the lowest-cost quartile of bond funds through to 0.45%, 0.63% and 1.07% for the second, third and fourth quartiles respectively.
Why the exodus to low-cost funds? It all comes down to returns.
The message is clear. Investors in low-cost funds are keeping more of what they pay for, and it highlights why fees represent such a crucial consideration in fund selection.
High cost is among the biggest enemies of successful investing. A significant body of research suggests that not only is high cost a major impediment to success, but low cost is actually the best predictor of future outperformance .
It is especially vital that investors control costs over the long term. Just like returns, the impact of costs compounds over
time, slowing investors’ progress towards their goals. And the importance of cost to investment outcomes applies to all funds, no matter whether they are actively managed or indexed.
Keeping more of the returns
The research also revealed the disparity in investment performance between the lowest- and highest-cost funds. Over the ten years ending December 31, 2018, low-cost funds outperformed high-cost funds across every category of equity and bond funds analysed (see chart 2).
Chart 2: Difference in ten-year annualized return between median funds in lowest- and highest-cost quartiles
  Cost-consciousness in Europe
This shift to low-cost funds by US investors has potential lessons for the industry in Europe.
European investors are also becoming increasingly cost-conscious. New regulations with a greater emphasis on fees, such as Mifid II and the UK Retail Distribution Review (RDR), are accelerating the move towards lower-cost options. The rising use of online cost and performance comparison tools is also giving investors a clearer understanding of the impact that high costs can have on investment returns.
The emergence of exchange-traded funds (ETFs) is raising awareness of costs, too. As an investment vehicle that mainly focuses on indexed strategies, ETFs have allowed investors to gain simple, low-cost access to a range of markets.
1See for example Financial Research Corporation (2002), Morningstar (Kinnel, 2010), James J. Rowley Jr., CFA; David J. Walker, CFA; Carol Zhu, 2019. The case for low-cost index-fund investing. Valley Forge, Pa.: The Vanguard Group
Investment risk information:
The value of investments, and the income from them, may fall or rise and investors may get back less than they invested. Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future results.
Other important information:
This article is for educational purposes only and is not a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell investments.
The opinions expressed in this article are those of the author and individuals quoted and
may not be representative of Vanguard Asset Management, Ltd or Vanguard Investments Switzerland GmbH.
Issued by Vanguard Asset Management, Ltd, which is authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority. In Switzerland, issued by Vanguard Investments Switzerland GmbH.
www.vanguard.co.uk/adviser
 ]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  22
  Achieving the perfect blend in retirement
 Paul Boston | Director of Sales | Novia
When picturing the perfect retirement there are an infinite set of scenarios with some of us looking forward to a simple life pottering in the garden with the grandkids, while others envisage wild World trips and second homes in sunnier climes!
Despite these very different visions, the underlying concern remains the same for most retirees - nobody wants to run out
of money! In fact, most of us also harbour the desire to help our loved ones meet their goals, such as getting their foot on the property ladder, paying for education or simply knowing that we can leave a legacy when the time comes.
Pension Freedoms opened up a world of opportunity for clients entering retirement but it also put extra pressure on the advice process. With options comes complexity, and with complexity comes risk. So how does an Adviser guide their client through the maze of options now available whilst ensuring they protect both themselves and the client?
The FCA’s Data Bulletin March 2018 showed that clients are taking varied approaches to accessing their retirement savings, with 55% of accessed pots being full withdrawals, 30% income drawdown and 12% annuity.
Where once only a binary choice was available – Income Guarantees (such as
DBs) or Pension Freedoms, there are now a multiplicity of options that allow for change over time and for the balance of preservation and longevity to shift as the client’s needs change. All of this requires ongoing review to ensure that the approach you advised
last year is still valid now. With the FCA recommending that all drawdown clients require regular reviews, at least annually, covering advice on complex accumulation and decumulation strategies, it is important to consider the factors that must be covered as a minimum. These include changes in legislation as well as for the client’s age, circumstances, tax status, health, capacity for loss and attitude to risk. Indeed, the PFS Best Practice Guide builds on this and asks the critical question;
‘How do you decide if the time has come
to consider a partial, phased or full exit from a drawdown plan (for example, to buy an annuity when a client gets older and the impact of mortality drag means their
drawdown strategy becomes progressively less effective)?’
Clearly Advisers need to protect their clients and themselves, from the risk of clients running out of money before they die and ensuring that their clients are offered the opportunity to secure a guaranteed income is essential.
Capacity for loss
The FCA defines ‘capacity for loss’ as the customer’s ability to absorb falls in the value of their investment. If any loss of capital would have a materially detrimental effect on their standard of living, this should be taken into account in assessing the risk that they are able to take.
According to the FCA’s Data Bulletin from March 2018, only 46% of consumers who made a retirement income decision in the last two years actually considered their health or life expectancy. Without taking these factors into account it’s impossible to ensure that clients are investing to cover their essential spend.
 ]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 23
  Pension Freedoms opened up a world of opportunity for clients entering retirement but it also put extra pressure on the advice process. With options comes complexity, and with complexity comes risk.
 Covering essential spend
On reaching full retirement, clients generally have their state pension plus a finite pot
of money to see them, and possibly their spouse, through their retirement years and this could be a long period. While it’s great news that people are living longer, it does present a financial challenge. A 65-year-old man now has a 50% chance of living until the age of 87 and a 65-year-old woman to the age of 90. So ensuring there is enough income to last throughout retirement is key.
The ability to keep adding to that secure pot can also be crucial as health fails or the ability to make complex financial decisions reduces with age. Nobody wants to be scrimping and saving in their retirement to protect the longevity of their income.
Reckless conservatism
It has been easy to see in countries such
as Australia, where pension freedoms have been part of the retirement landscape for far longer than in the UK, that the desire
to maintain control over ones’ retirement savings rather than locking it into an annuity can mean living a far more frugal existence than necessary. Clients not wanting to hand over their entire pension pot (Super Annuation) into secure guaranteed income, will often live in the fear of running out of money in retirement. It requires confidence to make the jump from a reliance on human capital to a reliance on investment capital.
For retirees in the UK there remain various options to enable a pension pot to be split between an annuity and other more flexible
options as within a SIPP, but a single provider offering these along with open architecture flexibility has proved elusive.
Research by PwC Research commissioned by Just in 2017, shows that ensuring some secure income is by far the most desired route for all groups surveyed.
Securing an income to cover essential spend without sacrificing flexibility
With people living longer in retirement it
is likely their needs will change over time. So the challenge for Advisers is to deliver
a solution that balances longevity with flexibility. The answer seems to be obvious: combine the security of guaranteed income with the flexibility of a SIPP – ideally all in one place with open architecture allowing a wide range of investment options.
Using the Novia SIPP you can now offer both, on the one hand, a medically underwritten secure lifetime income complete with 100% FSCS guarantee to cover the essentials
plus, on the other, the flexibility to invest
in a wide range of asset types to cover the discretionary spend and potentially grow
the portfolio. Holding the Guaranteed Income as an asset of the SIPP retains all of the IHT and income tax benefits of a SIPP with the added flexibility of choosing when to draw the income. Providing all of this in one place makes it possible to deliver the secure income underpin (which also provides a death benefit and cash-value in the early years) whilst the wider portfolio can be tailored to suit your client’s changing needs in retirement. In fact, if they choose to de- risk their portfolio further over time they can simply purchase more Guaranteed Income.
To find out more about how you can deliver Guaranteed Income within the Novia SIPP, contact the team today on 0345 600 3055 or enquiries@novia-financial.co.uk.
 For Financial Advisers only.
registered in England & Wales. Register Number: 06467886. Novia Financial plc is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Register Number: 481600.
Novia Financial is a limited company
 ]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  24
Pension freedom means holistic financial planning is vital
 John Porteous | Group Head of Distribution | Charles Stanley Wealth Managers
Many advisers have started to enhance their business model through the development of a centralised retirement proposition.
Since pension freedoms was introduced in April 2015, many advisers have started to enhance their business model through the development of a centralised retirement proposition (CRP).
Building investment solutions that are sufficiently flexible to adjust to changing needs and circumstances is particularly challenging in retirement. Here at Charles Stanley we seek to support financial advisers in delivering a wide range of investment services to support your propositions.
I recently took part in an Akademia session alongside Mike Barrett from the lang cat discussing the topical subject of Centralised Retirement Proposition – our discussion focused on three broad areas:
• The core issues facing customers and risks in retirement,
• How best to go about building a centralised retirement proposition,
• If a centralised retirement proposition can exist yet still be independent.
Visit www.asset.tv/player/akademiaclient- distribution-player/106377 to watch the video and collect CPD. I hope you find this debate interesting and thought provoking.
My key takeaways are listed below:
John’s takeaway 1 - Retirement is a journey not a destination
Pension freedom has introduced such a degree of flexibility around the use and deployment of an investors pension assets that what
used to be a pension specific discussion is
now more of a ‘holistic’ financial planning engagement. This gives rise to a broader and deeper goals-based discussion between client and adviser.
John’s takeaway 2 - Your advice discussion needs to evolve throughout time
With advances in medical science, people are living longer – this creates two key retirement planning challenges for clients; the money will likely need to last longer, and accumulated wealth will have to support different needs as an individual’s mobility, lifestyle and reliance on others starts to change. This has a wider impact that extends beyond investment strategy into enhanced client communication and intergenerational wealth transfer.
   ]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 25
  Building investment solutions that are sufficiently flexible to adjust to changing needs and circumstances is particularly challenging in retirement. Here at Charles Stanley we seek to support financial advisers in delivering a wide range of investment services to support your propositions.
John’s takeaway 3 - There is no such thing as a ‘safe withdrawal’
There is often temptation to apply ‘rules of thumb’ when thinking through a sustainable withdrawal rate in retirement. In reality, circumstances change as do reliance and the need to access capital (especially in later life). A robust retirement planning strategy is not just build on a withdrawal factor – it considers a much wider range of issues.
How can Charles Stanley support you?
Charles Stanley understands that advisers are expected to build a standardised approach
for their clients, but still want an investment solution to be tailored to their client’s ambitions, concerns and attitude to risk. We offer a wide range of solutions including Model Portfolio Service, Inheritance Tax Portfolio, Court of Protection and Bespoke Discretionary Managed; standardisation doesn’t have to mean no personalisation to their client’s unique needs.
Get in touch with Charles Stanley today, call 02039305453, email ist@charles-stanley.co.uk or visit www.charles-stanley.co.uk/professional- adviser-services
Disclaimers
Charles Stanley is not a tax adviser. Information contained in this article is based on our understanding of current HMRC legislation. Tax reliefs are those currently applying and the levels and bases of taxation can change. Tax treatment depends on the individual circumstances of each person or entity and may be subject to change in the future. If you are in any doubt, you should seek professional tax advice.
The value of investments can fall as well as rise. Investors may get back less than invested.
Charles Stanley is a trading name of Charles Stanley & Co. Limited, which is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.
 At Charles Stanley, our investment services are designed to give you the time to look after the personal and professional relationship with your clients whilst we, operating within your agreed parameters, take over the responsibility of looking after your client’s investments. With more than 200 years’ proven experience, we have created financial security for many tens of thousands of people, and as at
30 June 2019 manage and administer in excess of £24 billion.
Depending on your requirements, we will work with you to implement an investment solution that is right for your client via our Bespoke Discretionary Fund Management service, Passive model portfolios or Inheritance Tax Portfolio service.
  ]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  26
 What to do with the 40%?
 Luke Hyde-Smith | Head of third party fund selection | Waverton
The first in a new Insight series focused on how investors should consider portfolio positioning to assets other than equities.
How should investors approach the allocation within a traditional balanced portfolio to the ‘40%’ not invested in the equity market and why might investors consider an allocation to alternative investments?
The chart below helps explain asset
returns since 1980. Each line represents a discrete cumulative 10-year excess return of a traditional 60:40 balanced portfolio consisting of 60% global equities and 40% US government bonds. We use MSCI World and Barclays US Treasury as the two market indices.
The grey dashed line is the 10-year period up to December 2018. You will note that this was the best period for a balanced portfolio for nearly 40 years, a cumulative excess return, over cash, of just under 70% or 5.3% annualised.
That was until end June 2019, when the cumulative return for this ‘traditional’ portfolio of 60% equity and 40% bonds, delivered an impressive 85%, a compound annual return of 6.3%, the best 10 year period since 1980.
Bear in mind, this return is in USD, so
for a Sterling based investor, as GBP has depreciated over the period, returns have been even more impressive, adding an approximate 2% pa to this cumulative return.
In short, whether you are looking at traditional asset class returns in USD or GBP, the last 10 years have been an exceptional period.
Turning to what has driven these returns. Unsurprisingly, global equities have
been excellent long-term investments delivering 8.4% annualised over the last 35 years. However, this has come with large drawdowns, namely the declines post the Dot-com bubble of late 1990’s and the global financial crisis.
   In short, whether you
are looking at traditional asset class returns in USD or GBP, the last 10 years have been an exceptional period.
Source: Datastream, Waverton. Data from 31.01.79 to 30.06.19
 ]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  27
 What may be more surprising is the strength in government bonds over this period. Looking at the chart below, we have plotted the return of four developed market, government bond indices, in conjunction with equities, represented by the yellow line.
Source: Bloomberg, Waverton. Data from 31.12.85 to 31.08.19
In Japan, a market where yields where low by global standards in 1985, government bonds yielded 6%. Over time, this has steadily fallen
to the current 0%, and the market has delivered a respectable 3.9% compound annual return.
There have been equally impressive returns from German Bunds, 5.7% pa and US treasuries, 6.2% compound.
However, these pale in comparison with the UK gilt market, where investors have been rewarded with an 8% pa total return from lending money to the UK government, a return not dissimilar to equities.
What is also clear from this chart is that this return has been delivered with significantly less volatility. UK gilts over this period have a 6.4% annualised volatility, versus 15% for global equities. In short, government bonds have been fantastic investments, delivering excellent long term risk adjusted returns. In our view, this is unlikely to be repeated and one should consider the role alternative investments can play in both helping diversify risk, but also importantly, deliver returns.
Why do we believe the return profile of UK Gilts is unlikely to be repeated?
The below chart, focusing on just the UK gilt market, shows what has driven these returns and why risks in the bond market have risen significantly.
The green line shows the declining trend in UK gilt yields, falling from 11% in 1985 to the current 0.8%.
This has resulted in duration, the measure of interest rate risk inherent in a bond, represented by the grey line in the chart, steadily moving in the opposite direction, rising from 5 to the current 14. This means for a one percent move higher in interest rates, an investor in the broad UK gilt market may lose 14% of their capital.
Equally, if we take the measly 0.8% yield available on the UK gilt index and compare this with duration, we can deduce that it would take 16 years of income for investors to recover from a 1% move higher in yields. This infers UK gilts appear extremely richly valued versus history.
We are not suggesting investors carry no exposure to governments bonds, indeed the US treasury market continues to look relatively attractive, while we also believe there are opportunities across the credit market. However, we are highlighting the risks inherent within sections of the fixed income market and in forthcoming insight series articles we will detail how an allocation to selective alternative assets across the real asset and absolute return universe can help investors navigate the uncertain outlook and improve portfolio risk adjusted returns.
For more information contact Mark Barrington at mbarrington@waverton.co.uk or call 0207 484 2058
Risk Warnings
The views and opinions expressed are the views of Waverton Investment Management Limited and are subject to change based
on market and other conditions. The information provided does not constitute investment advice and it should not be relied on as such. All material(s) have been obtained from sources believed to be reliable, but its accuracy is not guaranteed. There is no representation or warranty as to the current accuracy of, nor liability for, decisions based on such information.
Changes in rates of exchange may have an adverse effect on the value, price or income of an investment.
Past performance is no guarantee of future results and the value of such investments and their strategies may fall as well as rise. Capital security is not guaranteed
The information relating to ‘yield’ is for indicative purposes only. You should note that yields on investments may fall or rise dependent on the performance of the underlying investment and more specifically the performance of the financial markets. As such, no warranty can be given that the expressed yields will consistently attain such levels over any given period.
16 Babmaes Street, London, SW1Y 6AH +44 (0)20 7484 7484
waverton.co.uk
Issued by Waverton Investment Management Limited. Registered in England No 2042285.
Authorised & Regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority
    Source: Bloomberg, Waverton. Data from 31.12.85 to 31.08.19
]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  28
 Knowing Me: Paul Quarendon, Knowing You: Tiina Stephens. A-ha!
  Tiina Stephens | Chief Operating Officer | Synaptic Software Limited
You would have previously read in Q2’s edition of Connection my interview with Richard Tailby, Synaptic’s Head of Sales. Now, continuing that series of interviews, we find out what makes Tiina Stephens, our new COO, tick. Tiina has spent 15 years in financial services. Let’s find out more.
What are your short and long- term goals for Synaptic?
Short term is to focus the business on core capabilities and simplify what we do for
the benefit of our customers. Long-term objectives for Synaptic is to deepen our product expertise in our chosen sectors, focus on user needs and design thinking.
What have you learned so far that you will take into the next year?
The focus of advice has been shifting for a long time. The pace of the change whilst continuous is ever more relentless and our users and partners all feel this. Technology drives the adoption of change and we (as industry suppliers and software providers) have noticed the opening of the closely guarded secrets of our partners’ and customers’ technology stacks and most
people are ready to adopt more collaboration and partnering. I see this as a great opportunity for our industry to unlock the value within the advice chain. More of it in 2020, please!quote t
How do you keep your staff keen and motivated?
Interesting question and they should probably answer this one rather than me! At Synaptic we have been working on creating a happy culture for a while now. The pace of change impacts not just our clients, but also everyone who works at Synaptic and every leader needs to make it clear why each colleague is significant, why their work matters, creating
a belonging to the organisation and making people feel refreshed even after a rough day; I want people to know what they have achieved. We have changed a lot of things based on one simple question; how happy do you feel coming to work? We are not finished as it is a continuous learning cycle and everyone as an individual is motivated differently, but we are continuously progressing and moving forward.
 We have a very strong view on how we improve our customers’ experience as a whole, and enable advisers to become more efficient and grow their business with the help of our software.
 ]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 29
  Software development is all about understanding user needs and figuring out what are the value creators and pain removers for the user, for the firm, for the industry – that’s what we are focusing on going forwards.
How do you foresee software having to change with an everchanging financial services industry?
I think now it is all about the retail technology experience – everyone expects software to look fantastic, provide fantastic results, drive value and benefit the user by being intuitive, innovative and free. Can’t do everything, right? Software development
is all about understanding user needs and figuring out what are the value creators and pain removers for the user, for the firm, for the industry – that’s what we are focusing on going forwards.
What’s the biggest risk you’ve ever taken?
Overall my risk profile is moderately cautious, however any increased risk needs to be weighted by the goal, potential returns and time horizon. I have set myself different
goals over time with variant levels of risk, but perhaps the biggest risks have been related to where I have chosen to live. I studied in Russia for a while, travelled around the world for a year on a very limited budget and moved to the UK 18 years ago, all of which, in hindsight, have paid off. Risk taking also needs to be
balanced with ‘what if’ scenarios – hence
the reason I took out a bigger life insurance policy the day before I gave birth to my son! It felt too risky a thing to go through without having sufficient cover in place.
Who is your role model, and why?
This has to be my grandmother; she taught me to be an individual and think for myself. She was also blazing the trail for women
in 1950’s Finland by working as the sole woman on a sawmill amongst 1000’s of male colleagues. All because she had a choice to do so and she never thought it wasn’t her place. Her philosophy was very gender neutral, we’re all just people with different capabilities and levels of experience.
Richard Tailby mentioned ‘talented people’ in his interview in the last edition of Connection. What do you see as the obvious ways to nurture talent in your business?
I think to nurture talent is to take everyone
as an individual and do your utmost to create opportunities for them to grow, if they have the drive or the opportunity to do so. It is an environment that you need to create where people are willing and able to take chances and try things and not be afraid to fail.
If you could make one change to a piece of Synaptic Software right now, what would it be?
We have a very strong view on how we improve our customers’ experience as a whole and enable advisers to become more efficient and grow their business with the help of our software. To pick one thing would be to speed up our go to market plans around Modeller Risk Explorer app, which will be really exciting to launch as well as our MiFID compliant reporting capabilities – these innovations create more engaging interactions between the adviser and the client, as well as driving efficiencies at practice level. We are solely focused on improving the tools to aide advisers, whether within the protection and investment or retirement advice, engagement and user experience with technology as well as enabling them to focus more of their time to build great relationships with their clients.
 ]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                            Risk and suitability in a perfect ‘10’
         • Synaptic Modeller provides complete risk and suitability and investment risk management for head offices, paraplanners and advisers, combining Moody’s Analytics investment strategy and stochastic projections
• Accurate and consistent values for downside risk that can be used to align Capacity for Loss with risk in chosen investments
• Includes fully integrated ATR Questionnaire, Asset Allocations and stochastic engine for illustrative projections
• Synaptic Modeller offers key Moody’s probability based risk metrics: the Value at Risk in any given investment scenario and the investment outcome
• Adviser controls inputs for investment amount, term, costs including adviser charges
• Perfectly complements RSMR qualitative research, accessible through Synaptic Product and Fund Fact sheets
• Integrates with Intelliflo via iO Store
                              Synaptic Modeller is now available with 1-10 risk categories as well as 1-5, defined by Moody’s Analytics asset allocations
  Synaptic Modeller is available as a standalone module from £50 per month. Network deals can apply. Can also be deployed as part of the full Synaptic Research Suite.
 For more information call 0800 783 4477 or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk
  ]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                Attract new protection customers with Webline Play
                                   • NEW protection lead-generation web app
• Provide tailored advice
& better financial outcomes
• Easily integrated embedded form that sits within your website, customisable
with your own brand.
 Visit www.synaptic.co.uk/webline-play
Call 0800 783 4477 or email sales@synaptic.co.uk
           ]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  32
 Don’t be a lobster pot. How?
  Eric Armstrong | Client Director | Synaptic Software Limited
Lobster-potting is a bane in our industry. Mark Polson of the lang
cat used this descriptive term as part of the presentation linked
to the recent research report with Origo ‘A disconnected world’, documenting some of the appalling consequences to firms that come from reluctance of tools and systems to share data effectively. Data may be assimilated by an application, but like a lobster in a pot, does not re-emerge in a useful manner.
Incredibly, there are (in Mark’s view) ZERO effective 2-way data-passing integrations that will support firms in real time. The lobster
pot is a great metaphor for the phenomenon whereby the majority of technological entities in our industry restrict the flow of data between applications, and is the reason why:
- administrators can manage a maximum of £20m of assets-under-advice;
- firms are re-keying data into an average of 5 systems (not including platforms);
- advice is struggling to transcend its cottage-industry status and embrace higher levels of service and transparency;
Lobster potting is imbedded through decades of competing interests vying for control of adviser-originated inflows into their custody. Pre-RDR, product providers maintained the levers of control of clients’ assets by payment of commission to advisers. Today the vested interests may have been transformed by regulation, but the bad practices live on in the reluctance of propositions to share data openly to assist in streamlining and reducing friction in advice. They still do not necessarily see it is in their interests to do so. The publication by Origo and the lang cat, ‘A Disconnected World’
is document that can be searched for and downloaded and is a brilliant description of the problem.
 Lobster potting
is imbedded through decades of competing interests vying for control of adviser-originated inflows into their custody.
 ]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 33
  A typical firm in our research uses 5 standalone systems in the delivery of advice, planning and portfolio management, and 2 investment platforms.
Not a single business process was available to our firms on a real-time, 2-way basis. None. Not one.
Origo and the lang cat: ‘A Disconnected World: the Numbers’
We wholeheartedly agree with the way the problem was framed, and are proposing a radical solution for firms, with assistance for platforms and back office systems in making available the data that firms need. We believe that facilitating the research around suitability is the key to meeting the challenge. Our new proposition is designed post-MiFID II and
is based on three pillars: our independence and ability to present an even playing field in support of firms’ preferences; our ability to apply a consistent and proven methodology across competing propositions and thirdly, our historic role of collecting and the relevant data, a role now critical to successful disclosure to MiFID standards.
Much as the government grew tired of cajoling the industry to reform its bad habits around the purchase of annuities and pulled out
the sledge hammer of pension reforms (or freedoms) in 2015, MiFID’s reforms of 2018 now biting, presented a sledge hammer to issues relating to disclosure and safeguards
to consumers that arguably should have recognised more fairly the trust that advisers earn from their customers and the high standard of the advice that they can point to historically.
But MiFID is here to stay and has put enormous strain on the advice process
before and after transaction (ex-ante and ex-post). In simple terms, the requirement to prove Suitability at Point-of-Sale and review represents a new world of difficulty as at a minimum, the following need to be addressed:
a. Relying on the platform (or provider) for objective research that will lead to direction of inflows into their custody cannot support any kind of independent due diligence;
b. Relying on the back-office system
for financial-planning-based research won’t work, as back offices are repositories of client and holdings data, mainly designed to facilitate payments. They do not maintain data exclusively for research purposes, meaning that due diligence needs
to be performed outside of the back office;
c. The research tools that they ‘integrate’ tend to be specialist tools not aligned to a central investment strategy that can encompass all the layers of costs in a recommendation, including product, platform and fund costs at share-class level;
d. Firms must look to enhance the core capabilities of their back-office systems and platforms to establish robust and repeatable independent research.
1.
2. 3.
4.
Are the client’s circumstances and objectives still current?
Has the client’s risk profile changed?
Is the recommended strategy still intact?
Is the recommended investment still aligned to all of the above?
This challenge is not something that can
be completed with a few tick-boxes or confirmation over the phone. The lang
cat research concludes that an average administrator in a firm can manage £20m of investments. MiFID may have just halved that.
At the heart of the problem lie irreconcilable conflicts of interest:
 ]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 34
 The lang cat research concludes that an average administrator in a firm can manage £20m of investments. MiFID may have just halved that.
 Problems for firms
Where tools offered by the platform are relied upon for ex-ante or ex-post reporting, generally their methodology cannot be applied as basis of comparison outside their own universe of investments reflecting their own custody arrangements. Even advisory businesses that channel all investments onto a single platform have to address the fact that often, many of the firm’s assets-under-advice remain under third party custody.
They then run into the challenge that the fund data feeds are limited to unitised funds, preventing them from modelling platform, product or portfolio costs and charges
that are relevant to their analysis. They are then condemned to multiple phone calls and requests for information from multiple providers and subsequent re-keying.
The threat of enforcement in the event of bias
For any firms doubting the responsibilities
of firms to show their due diligence extends beyond the information provided by their favourite platforms, should read/reflect on the ‘COBS 6.1F ‘Client’s best interests rule and using a platform service’:
If the current approach condemns a firm to a slow death of research, re-keying, error, omission and stitching together reports manually, what does the perfect solution offer?
In short, full automation of the following:
1. A Central Investment Strategy that can form the basis of all personal recommendations, including comparisons between ceding schemes or investments, that configure not just funds or portfolios, but also products and platforms;
2. Model-driven ability (preferably stochastic) to risk profile all investments, without need to reference committees of experts for
qualitative overview. It is impossible to prove suitability of an investment if you do not have access to a reliable risk profile for that investment, and that investment may be a bespoke portfolio, including funds that may not be risk-rated by the agencies;
3. Ability to access the relevant pricing for ex-post as well as ex-ante illustrations, accessing the whole-of-market platform, product and portfolio costs, extending to discretionary managed portfolios (MPS);
4. Ability to perform due diligence at proposition or segment level as required by MiFID on independent basis that is not reliant on information and conclusions provided by a preferred platform or product provider;
5. Valuations from a full range of providers, not just those investments in custody of a preferred platform or provider;
6. Ability to report extensively to assist governance, to the standards and requirements of the Senior Management Regime.
 ]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  What is Synaptic offering?
To circumvent the challenges of lobster- potting, there are two initiatives underway at Synaptic, drawing on our traditional role of collecting and providing access to data to firms to support their compliance.
The first initiative is to complete the data- sets that represent the gaps in the advisory landscape available to firms via API. The second is to launch in 2020 a comprehensive
research suite that will enable firms to manage fully-compliant and fully automated ex-ante and ex-post reporting (includes automated valuations), creating an even playing field for due diligence, transparency for the regulator and customers.
To meet 21st Century user-experience expectations, one of the UK’s leading design agencies, OrangeBus, known for their work on the HMRC website among other accolades, have designed the user journey.
Supporting the firm’s back office
Our philosophy is to reduce the burden for proving suitability for products and platforms whilst supporting back office systems as the repositories of customer and holdings data and own research that supports the proof of suitability for firms.
The following APIs are now available to third parties, in many cases representing unique datasets within the industry:
 If you are interested in learning more about the Synaptic suite of APIs, or the 2020 launch of Synaptic 2.0, full suitability research and due diligence solution, please contact us in 0800 783 4477
35
]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ CMPS 1 CMPS 2 CMPS 3 CMPS 4 CMPS 5
MyPortfolio Index I MyPortfolio Index II MyPortfolio Index III MyPortfolio Index IV MyPortfolio Index V MyPortfolio Index Plus I MyPortfolio Index Plus II MyPortfolio Index Plus III MyPortfolio Index Plus IV MyPortfolio Index Plus V MyPortfolio Select I MyPortfolio Select II MyPortfolio Select III MyPortfolio Select IV MyPortfolio Select V
Aegon Conservative Core Portfolio Aegon Cautious Core Portfolio Aegon Balanced Core Portfolio Aegon Balanced Plus Core Portfolio Aegon Growth Core Portfolio Aegon Growth Plus Core Portfolio Aegon Adventurous Core Portfolio
Investments
VT AJ Bell Passive Cautious fund
VT AJ Bell Passive Moderately Cautious fund
VT AJ Bell Passive Balanced fund
VT AJ Bell Passive Moderately Adventurous fund
VT AJ Bell Passive Adventurous fund VT AJ Bell Passive Global Growth fund VT AJ Bell Income fund
VT AJ Bell Income & Growth fund
AJ Bell Passive MPS 1
AJ Bell Passive MPS 2
AJ Bell Passive MPS 3
AJ Bell Passive MPS 4
AJ Bell Passive MPS 5
AJ Bell Passive MPS 6
AJ Bell Passive MPS Income 1
AJ Bell Passive MPS Income 2
AJ Bell Active MPS 1
AJ Bell Active MPS 2
AJ Bell Active MPS 3
AJ Bell Active MPS 4
AJ Bell Active MPS 5
AJ Bell Active MPS 6
AJ Bell Active MPS Income 1
AJ Bell Active MPS Income 2
AJ Bell Pactive MPS 1
AJ Bell Pactive MPS 2
AJ Bell Pactive MPS 3
AJ Bell Pactive MPS 4
AJ Bell Pactive MPS 5
AJ Bell Pactive MPS 6
Capital
]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                                   MA Passive Prudent
MA Passive Reserve
MA Passive Moderate MA Passive Intermediate MA Passive Progressive MA Passive Growth
MA Passive Dynamic
MA Blended Reserve
MA Blended Moderate MA Blended Intermediate MA Blended Progressive MA Blended Growth
MA Active Reserve
MA Active Moderate Income MA Active Intermediate Income MA Active Progressive
MA Active Growth
MA Active Dynamic
Architas Positive Future
                                            MAF I
MAF II
MAF III
MAF IV
MAF V
Smooth Managed Fund
                                                                              BMO MM Lifestyle 3 Fund
BMO MM Lifestyle 4 Fund
BMO MM Lifestyle 5 Fund
BMO MM Lifestyle 6 Fund
BMO MM Lifestyle 7 Fund
Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling) BMO MM Navigator Distribution Fund BMO MM Navigator Cautious Fund BMO MM Navigator Balanced Fund BMO MM Navigator Growth Fund BMO MM Navigator Boutiques Fund BMO Universal MAP Cautious
BMO Universal MAP Balanced BMO Universal MAP Growth BMO Universal MAP Adventurous BMO Universal MAP Income BMO Universal MAP Defensive
                                                                                                                                                                                              BNY Mellon Multi-Asset Diversified Return BNY Mellon Multi-Asset Income
BNY Mellon Multi-Asset Balanced
BNY Mellon Multi-Asset Growth
BNY Mellon Multi-Asset Global Balanced BNY Mellon Global Dynamic Bond
BNY Mellon Global Dynamic Bond Income BNY Mellon Real Return
              Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk
]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Cautious
Cautious Higher Equity
Income
Income Higher Equity
Balanced MPS
Growth MPS
Global Equity MPS
Cautious Passive+
Cautious Higher Equity Passive+ Income Passive+
Income Higher Equity Passive+ Balanced Passive+
Growth Passive+
Global Equity Passive+
LF Canlife Portfolio III LF Canlife Portfolio IV LF Canlife Portfolio V LF Canlife Portfolio VI LF Canlife Portfolio VII Canlife Portfolio 3 Canlife Portfolio 4 Canlife Portfolio 5 Canlife Portfolio 6 Canlife Portfolio 7
LF Canlife Managed 0%-35% Canlife Managed 0%-35%
LF Canlife Managed 20%-60%
MPS Low Risk (Defensive Income)
MPS Low Medium Risk (Income & Growth) MPS Low Medium Risk (Income)
MPS Medium Risk (Income)
MPS Medium Risk (Income & Growth) MPS Medium Risk (Passive)
MPS Medium High Risk
MPS Medium High Risk (Passive)
MPS High Risk (Growth)
IFSL BM Defensive Income
IFSL BM Cautious Growth
IFSL BM Balanced
IFSL BM Strategic Growth
IFSL BM Defensive Capital
MPS Low Medium Risk (Passive)
MPS RIS Low Medium Risk
MPS RIS Medium Risk
MPS RIS Medium High Risk
Carmignac Ptf Unconstrained Euro Fixed Income
Carmignac Portfolio Patrimoine
Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Discovery
Carmignac Portfolio Sécurité
Carmignac Portfolio Commodities
Carmignac Portfolio Emergents
Carmignac Portfolio Unconstrained Global Bond
Carmignac Portfolio Long-Short European Equities
Carmignac Portfolio Euro-Entrepreneurs Carmignac Portfolio Investissement Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Patrimoine Carmignac Portfolio Grande Europe
]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                            Cazenove Cautious Portfolio
Cazenove Balanced Portfolio
Cazenove Balanced Income Portfolio
Cazenove Growth Portfolio
Cazenove Aggressive Portfolio
Cazenove Equity Risk Portfolio
Cazenove Cautious Active/Passive Portfolio
Cazenove Balanced Active/Passive Portfolio
Cazenove Growth Active/Passive Portfolio
Cazenove Aggressive Active/Passive Portfolio
Cazenove Equity Risk Active/Passive Portfolio
                                                                       Dynamic Passive
   Dynamic Passive 1 Dynamic Passive 2 Dynamic Passive 3 Dynamic Passive 4 Dynamic Passive 5
                Multi Manager
   Multi Manager Income 1 Multi Manager Income 2 Multi Manager Income 3 Multi Manager Income 4 Multi Manager Income 5 Multi Manager Total Return 1 Multi Manager Total Return 2 Multi Manager Total Return 3 Multi Manager Total Return 4 Multi Manager Total Return 5
                                                                 Close Managed Growth Fund
Close Tactical Select Passive Growth Fund
Close DMS Growth
Close Managed Balanced Fund
Close Tactical Select Passive Balanced Fund
Close DMS Balanced
Close Managed Income Fund
Close Managed Conservative Fund
Close Tactical Select Passive Conservative Fund
Close DMS Income Plus
Close DMS Conservative
Close Bond Income Portfolio Fund Close Growth Portfolio Fund
Close Balanced Portfolio Fund
Close Conservative Portfolio Fund Close Diversified Income Portfolio Fund
                                                                                                                                                                                         8AM Clever MPS 3 8AM Clever MPS 4 8AM Clever MPS 5 8AM Clever MPS 6 8AM Clever MPS 7
        Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk
]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Multi Asset Allocator Defensive Multi Asset Allocator Strategic Multi Asset Allocator Growth Multi Asset Allocator Adventurous Multi Asset Allocator World
Multi Asset Open Defensive Multi Asset Open Strategic Multi Asset Open Growth Multi Asset Open Adventurous Open World
Multi Asset Income
Multi Asset Balanced Income Multi Asset Income & Growth
HSBC Global Strategy Cautious
HSBC Global Strategy Conservative
HSBC Global Strategy Balanced
HSBC Global Strategy Dynamic
HSBC Global Strategy Adventurous
HSBC Global MPS Cautious
HSBC Global MPS Conservative
HSBC Global MPS Balanced
HSBC Global MPS Dynamic
HSBC Global MPS Adventurous
HSBC Global Sustainable Multi-Asset Conservative Portfolio
HSBC Global Sustainable Multi-Asset Balanced Portfolio
Cautious
GS Global Multi Asset Conservative Portfolio
GS Global Multi Asset Balanced Portfolio GS Global Multi Asset Growth Portfolio
Invesco Asian Fund (UK)
Invesco Corporate Bond Fund (UK)
Invesco Distribution Fund (UK)
Invesco Global Bond Fund (UK)
Invesco Global Smaller Companies Fund (UK)
Invesco Global Targeted Returns Fund (UK) Invesco High Income Fund (UK)
Invesco High Yield Fund (UK)
Invesco Hong Kong & China Fund (UK) Invesco Income Fund (UK)
Invesco Latin American Fund (UK) Invesco Managed Growth Fund (UK) Invesco Managed Income Fund (UK) Invesco Monthly Income Plus Fund (UK) Invesco Pacific Fund (UK)
Invesco Tactical Bond Fund (UK)
Invesco UK Smaller Companies Equity Fund (UK)
Invesco UK Strategic Income Fund (UK) Invesco Summit Growth 1 Fund (UK) Invesco Summit Growth 2 Fund (UK) Invesco Summit Growth 3 Fund (UK) Invesco Summit Growth 4 Fund (UK) Invesco Summit Growth 5 Fund (UK)
Funds
Synaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:
Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation
Moderately Cautious
Balanced Moderately Adventurous Adventurous
]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                  MPS
       MPS 1 Income MPS 2 Income MPS 3 Income MPS 4 Income MPS 5 Income MPS 6 Income MPS 7 Income MPS 8 Income MPS 9 Income MPS 10 Income MPS 11 Income MPS 1 Growth MPS 2 Growth MPS 3 Growth MPS 4 Growth MPS 5 Growth MPS 6 Growth MPS 7 Growth MPS 8 Growth MPS 9 Growth MPS 10 Growth MPS 11 Growth
                                                                                         Diversified Income Fund
Investec Cautious Managed Fund
Diversified Growth Fund
MAP
Investec Global Multi-Asset Total Return Fund
Investec UK Special Situations Investec UK Alpha
Investec Global Strategic Equity
                   Janus Henderson Cautious Managed Janus Henderson MA Absolute Return Janus Henderson MM Distribution Janus Henderson MM Income & Growth Janus Henderson MM Managed
Janus Henderson MM Active
Janus Henderson Core 3 Income
Janus Henderson Core 4 Income
Janus Henderson Core 5 Income
Janus Henderson Core 6 Income & Growth
                                                           Jupiter Absolute Return
Jupiter Strategic Bond
Jupiter Distribution
Jupiter Monthly Alternative Income Jupiter Merlin Conservative Portfolio Jupiter Merlin Income Portfolio Jupiter Merlin Balanced Portfolio Jupiter Merlin Growth Portfolio Jupiter Merlin Worldwide Portfolio
                                                                                                    Multi-Index 3 Multi-Index 4 Multi-Index 5 Multi-Index 6 Multi-Index 7 Multi-Index Income 4 Multi-Index Income 5 Multi-Index Income 6
                                                                                 ]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                 MPS – Defensive
MPS – Cautious
MPS – Balanced
MPS – Growth
MPS – Adventurous
MPS – Strategic Income Volare Defensive Fund Volare Cautious Fund
Volare Balanced Fund
Volare Growth Fund
Volare Strategic Income Fund Sustainable MPS – Cautious Sustainable MPS – Balanced Sustainable MPS – Growth
                                                                                                                                          WSS
  WSS Risk Grade 1 WSS Risk Grade 2 WSS Risk Grade 3 WSS Risk Grade 4 WSS Risk Grade 5 WSS Risk Grade 6 WSS Risk Grade 7 WSS Risk Grade 8 WSS Risk Grade 9 WSS Risk Grade 10 WSS Income 1
WSS Income 2
WSS Income 3
WSS Income 4
WSS Income 5
WSS Income 6
WSS Dynamic Beta 1 WSS Dynamic Beta 2 WSS Dynamic Beta 3 WSS Dynamic Beta 4 WSS Dynamic Beta 5 WSS Dynamic Beta 6 WSS Dynamic Beta 7 WSS Dynamic Beta 8 WSS Dynamic Beta 9 WSS Dynamic Beta 10
                                                                Flexible Guaranteed Funds Cautious Flexible Guaranteed Funds Balanced Flexible Guaranteed Managed Growth Balanced Index
                                                 MP3 MP4 MP5 MP6 MP7
                                                 ]]></page><page Index="43" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                          Morningstar Cautious Active Portfolio
Morningstar Moderately Cautious Active Portfolio
Morningstar Moderate Active Portfolio
Morningstar Moderately Adventurous Active Portfolio
Morningstar Adventurous Active Portfolio
Morningstar Cautious Passive Portfolio
Morningstar Moderately Cautious Passive Portfolio
Morningstar Moderate Passive Portfolio
Morningstar Moderately Adventurous Passive Portfolio
Morningstar Adventurous Passive Portfolio
Morningstar Moderately Cautious Income Portfolio
Morningstar Moderate Income Portfolio
Morningstar Multi-Asset Real Return 100
Morningstar Multi-Asset Real Return 300
Morningstar Multi-Asset Real Return 500
Morningstar Multi-Asset Real Return Flexible
Governed Portfolio – Cautious Growth
Governed Portfolio – Moderately Cautious Growth
Governed Portfolio – Moderate Growth
Governed Portfolio – Moderately Adventurous Growth
Governed Portfolio – Adventurous Growth
Governed Portfolio – Moderately Cautious Income
Morningstar ESG – Cautious Portfolio
Morningstar ESG – Moderately Cautious Portfolio
Morningstar ESG – Moderate Portfolio
Morningstar ESG – Moderately Adventurous Portfolio
Morningstar ESG - Adventurous Portfolio
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        MPS
  MPS Growth 1
MPS Growth 2
MPS Growth 3
MPS Growth 4
MPS Growth 5
MPS Growth 6
MPS Growth 7
MPS Growth 8
MPS Income 1
MPS Income 2
MPS Income 3
MPS Income 4
MPS Income 5
MPS Income 6
MPS Dynamic Beta 1 MPS Dynamic Beta 2 MPS Dynamic Beta 3 MPS Dynamic Beta 4 MPS Dynamic Beta 5 MPS Dynamic Beta 6 MPS Dynamic Beta 7 MPS Dynamic Beta 8
                                           Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk
]]></page><page Index="44" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                Portfolios
  Premier Capital Builder Portfolio Premier Capital Builder Plus Portfolio Premier Income and Growth Portfolio Premier Income Portfolio
Premier Conservative Portfolio Premier High Income Portfolio Premier Balanced Portfolio
Premier Balanced Plus Portfolio Premier Growth Portfolio
Premier Growth Plus Portfolio Premier Dynamic Growth Portfolio
                      Funds
      Premier Multi-Asset Conservative Growth Premier Multi-Asset Absolute Return Fund Premier Multi-Asset Distribution Fund Premier Multi-Asset Monthly Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Growth & Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Global Growth Fund Premier UK Money Market Fund
Premier Defensive Growth Fund
Premier Corporate Bond Monthly Income Fund
Premier Diversified Balanced Growth Fund Premier Diversified Cautious Growth Fund Premier Diversified Dynamic Growth Fund Premier Diversified Growth Fund
Premier Diversified Income Fund Premier Liberation IV Fund Premier Liberation V Fund Premier Liberation VI Fund Premier Liberation VII Fund
                                                                                                                                              PruFund Cautious
PruFund Protected Cautious PruFund Growth
PruFund Protected Growth PruFund Risk Managed 1 PruFund Risk Managed 2 PruFund Risk Managed 3 PruFund Risk Managed 4 PruFund Risk Managed 5 WP Optimum Return
Risk Managed Active 1
Risk Managed Active 2
Risk Managed Active 3
Risk Managed Active 4
Risk Managed Active 5
Risk Managed Passive 1
Risk Managed Passive 2
Risk Managed Passive 3 Risk Managed Passive 4 Risk Managed Passive 5
                                         Bespoke
        Strategy 1 Strategy 2 Strategy 3 Strategy 4 Strategy 5 Strategy 6
                                                                    Multi Asset
      RMAP Total Return RMAP Strategic Growth RMAP Enhanced Growth RMAP Strategic Income
                                      ]]></page><page Index="45" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ MPS Global Growth MPS Growth
MPS Balanced
MPS Global Income MPS Income
MPS Conservative MPS Cautious IDX Growth
IDX Balanced
IDX Income
IDX Conservative
MPS Global Growth (Platform) MPS Growth (Platform)
MPS Balanced (Platform)
MPS Global Income (Platform) MPS Income (Platform)
MPS Conservative (Platform) IDX Growth (Platform)
IDX Balanced (Platform)
IDX Income (Platform)
IDX Conservative (Platform)
Cautious Balanced Income Balanced Plus Equity
Equity Plus
Managed Portfolios
Quilter Investors Generation CPI+ 3 Portfolio
Quilter Investors Generation CPI+ 4 Portfolio
Quilter Investors Generation CPI+ 5 Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Conservative Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Balanced Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Moderate Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Dynamic Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Adventurous Portfolio
Quilter Investors Creation Conservative Portfolio
Quilter Investors Creation Balanced Portfolio
Quilter Investors Creation Moderate Portfolio
Quilter Investors Creation Dynamic Portfolio
Quilter Investors Creation Adventurous Portfolio
WealthSelect Active Managed Portfolio 3
WealthSelect Active Managed Portfolio 4
WealthSelect Active Managed Portfolio 5
WealthSelect Active Managed Portfolio 6
WealthSelect Active Managed Portfolio 7
WealthSelect Active Managed Portfolio 8
WealthSelect Active Managed Portfolio 9
WealthSelect Active Managed Portfolio 10
WealthSelect Blend Managed Portfolio 3
WealthSelect Blend Managed Portfolio 4
WealthSelect Blend Managed Portfolio 5
WealthSelect Blend Managed Portfolio 6
WealthSelect Blend Managed Portfolio 7
WealthSelect Blend Managed Portfolio 8
WealthSelect Blend Managed Portfolio 9
WealthSelect Blend Managed Portfolio 10
Quilter Investors Monthly Income Portfolio
Quilter Investors Monthly Income and Growth Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Conservative Blend Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Balanced Blend Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Moderate Blend Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Dynamic Blend Portfolio
Quilter Investors Cirilium Adventurous Blend Portfolio
]]></page><page Index="46" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ RL GMAP Conservative RL GMAP Defensive
RL GMAP Balanced
RL GMAP Growth
RL GMAP Adventurous RL GMAP Dynamic
RSMR Rfolio Defensive RSMR Rfolio Cautious RSMR Rfolio Prudent RSMR Rfolio Balanced RSMR Rfolio Growth RSMR Rfolio Dynamic RSMR Rfolio Adventurous RSMR Rfolio Income RSMR Rfolio SRI Cautious RSMR Rfolio SRI Balanced RSMR Rfolio SRI Dynamic
2 Portfolio
2 Income Portfolio 3 Portfolio
3 Income Portfolio 4 Portfolio
4 Income Portfolio 5 Portfolio
5 Income Portfolio 6 Portfolio
7 Portfolio
RL Governed Portfolio 1 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 2 RL Governed Portfolio 3 (s) RL Governed Portfolio 4 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 5 RL Governed Portfolio 6 (s) RL Governed Portfolio 7 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 8 RL Governed Portfolio 9 (s) RL GRIP 1
RL GRIP 2 RL GRIP 3 RL GRIP 4 RL GRIP 5
Russell Investments Secure Portfolio Russell Investments Cautious Portfolio Russell Investments Conservative Portfolio Russell Investments Moderate Portfolio Russell Investments Balanced Portfolio Russell Investments Progressive Portfolio Russell Investments Adventurous Portfolio Russell Investments Growth Portfolio Russell Investments Aggressive Portfolio Russell Investments Aggressive Plus Russell Investments Defensive Assets Fund Russell Investments Real Assets Fund Russell Investments UK Growth
Russell Investments International Growth Russell Investments MA Growth 1
Russell Investments MA Growth 2
Russell Investments MA Growth 3
Russell Investments MA Growth 4
Russell Investments MA Growth 5
Russell Investments MA Income
Global Multi Asset Portfolios
Governed Portfolios
]]></page><page Index="47" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Schroder MM Diversity Schroder MM Diversity Balanced Schroder MM Diversity Income Schroder MM Diversity Tactical Schroder MM International Schroder MM UK Growth Schroder Monthly Income Fund Schroder Dynamic Multi Asset Schroder Managed Balanced
ASI MyFolio Market I
ASI MyFolio Market II
ASI MyFolio Market III
ASI MyFolio Market IV
ASI MyFolio Market V
ASI MyFolio Managed I
ASI MyFolio Managed II
ASI MyFolio Managed III
ASI MyFolio Managed IV
ASI MyFolio Managed V
ASI MyFolio Multi-Manager I
ASI MyFolio Multi-Manager II
ASI MyFolio Multi-Manager III
ASI MyFolio Multi-Manager IV
ASI MyFolio Multi-Manager V
ASI MyFolio Multi-Manager Income II ASI MyFolio Multi-Manager Income III ASI MyFolio Multi-Manager Income IV ASI MyFolio Index I
ASI MyFolio Index II ASI MyFolio Index III ASI MyFolio Index IV ASI MyFolio Index V
ASI
Cautious
Income
Moderately Cautious Balanced
Moderately Adventurous Adventurous
Personal Injury
Pension Portfolio 1
Pension Portfolio 2 Pension Portfolio 3 Pension Portfolio A Pension Portfolio B Pension Portfolio 4 Pension Portfolio C Pension Portfolio 5 Premier Pension Portfolio 1 Premier Pension Portfolio 2 Premier Pension Portfolio 3 Premier Pension Portfolio A Premier Pension Portfolio B Premier Pension Portfolio 4 Premier Pension Portfolio C Premier Pension Portfolio 5
S&W Defensive Portfolio – 3
S&W Defensive Income Portfolio – 4 S&W Balanced Income Portfolio – 5 S&W Balanced Growth Portfolio – 6 S&W Growth Portfolio – 7
S&W Dynamic Growth Portfolio – 8
]]></page><page Index="48" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Strategy 1 (Defensive)
Strategy 2 (Conservative)
Strategy 3 (Income)
Strategy 4 (Balanced)
Strategy 5 (Growth)
Strategy 6 (Adventurous)
Strategy 7 (Maximum Growth)
Tilney Platform Model Defensive
Tilney Platform Model Conservative Tilney Platform Model Cautious
Tilney Platform Model Balanced
Tilney Platform Model Growth
Tilney Platform Model Adventurous Tilney Platform Model Maximum Growth Tilney Platform Model Strategic Income Tilney Platform Model Income & Growth
Waverton Conservative Model Portfolio Waverton Defensive Model Portfolio Waverton Cautious Model Portfolio Waverton Balanced Model Portfolio Waverton Growth Model Portfolio Waverton Multi-Asset Income
Commercial Long Income PAIF
Vanguard LifeStrategy 20% Vanguard LifeStrategy 40% Vanguard LifeStrategy 60% Vanguard LifeStrategy 80% Vanguard LifeStrategy 100%
VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 3 VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 4 VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 5 VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 6 VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 7
Vitality Investec Multi-Asset Moderate Vitality Investec Multi-Asset Balanced Vitality Investec Multi-Asset Growth Vitality Investec Multi-Asset Income Vitality Investec Dynamic Multi-Asset
(s) These portfolios were constructed with short investment timelines (5 year) in mind.
(l) These portfolios were constructed with longer investment timelines (15 year) in mind. Otherwise Synaptic Risk Ratings assume a 10 year investment horizon. You should consult Royal London directly for further information before recommending.
About the service: Synaptic Risk Ratings are worked out by analysing the underlying asset classes within the fund or portfolio. Synaptic Software have requested asset allocation information from participating providers in a specific format aligned to the risk framework of the system. These asset classes are used by the model to determine the risk rating, a process that may result in a level of approximation though in most cases this will be insignificant. It is also possible that certain asset classes may not be represented exactly in the manner that providers would prefer.
Reasonable endeavours are made to provide accuracy and consistency, however neither participating providers nor Synaptic Software can be held responsible for any errors or omissions. No recommendation should be made solely on the basis of the Synaptic Risk Ratings, and additional research should be undertaken for any case. This service is intended for use by investment professionals only.
]]></page><page Index="49" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                            THE NEW WHITE PAPER
Enabling better outcomes in financial planning by optimising investment risk and reward using stochastic modelling
Download your free copy today
www.synaptic.co.uk/risk
How to improve your
Synaptic Modeller is now available
with 1-10 risk categories as well as 1-5, defined by Moody’s Analytic’s
investment performance
and optimise risk
asset allocations
  Featuring industry-leading suitability research from
Moody’s Analytics
  ]]></page><page Index="50" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                50
                        Webline Play is not just for Christmas, it’s for Life ...
  Paul Quarendon | Product Manager | Synaptic Software Limited
...Critical Illness, Mortgage Protection and Income Protection as well! If there’s one financial planning tool that should be on your Santa list this year, it is the second iteration of Webline Play. This new version, out in time for the Christmas market, focuses on life cover, critical illness and mortgage protection and complements the earlier launch of Webline Play for Income Protection.
Aptly named Webline Play Life, it provides real-time quotes and helps consumers understand the cost of protection for single and joint life cases before making any decision to purchase, thus creating a warmer lead for your business. Webline Play is a hosted form solution which allows you to quickly and easily implement a client friendly protection quotes engine into your website or mobile app. Quick to install, it uses a simple iFrame and gives flexibility, through a variety of customisations, to create the user journey you want for your customers.
The best technologies evolve in line
with changing adviser and consumer requirements, and Synaptic works with its client base to understand and develop solutions that will best fit these evolving needs. As a consequence, adapting and providing advisers with end-to-end capabilities to service their customers is paramount to our product development
strategy. We particularly value our trusted customer partnerships which help us ensure we continue to deliver responsive software solutions to meet the needs of the market, ultimately helping advisers in the delivery of responsible and holistic financial advice.
Webline Play requires very little technical expertise to install and is ideal for small to medium-sized financial advisers, being cost- effective and easy to set up and maintain
– you just embed the iframe element of Webline Play to your web page and play.
So how can you direct people towards choosing policies they would benefit from? One factor preventing consumers from purchasing insurance is that they don’t always understand what would be covered under the policy. Many worry that they’ll
pay their regular monthly premiums, only to discover in a time of need that they’re not actually covered for the particular situation they find themselves in. As one of the UK’s leading web service providers, we were confident our range of products could be enhanced to help. As a result, we’ve extended Webline Play to offer more products, those that your customers will have a need for.
 Since the launch
of Webline Play for Income protection Webline has seen a 10% increase in Income Protection quotations
 ]]></page><page Index="51" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[        51
                                Webline Play requires very little technical expertise to install and is ideal for small to medium-sized financial advisers, being cost- effective and easy to set up and maintain – you just embed the iframe element of Webline Play to your web page and play.
Whether your customer is planning to start a family, buy a house, get married or when illness is a worry, Webline Play will give them immediate access to personalised quotations via your own website. Designed to help
you create better financial outcomes for customers by offering an alternative way of accessing the benefits of Synaptic’s Webline, Webline Play brings you closer to customers with real-time information. You’ll know more about them, enabling more personalised
support to build stronger, collaborative relationships and, with a clear picture of the products on offer, consumers are more likely to buy the protection.
A leader in the financial web services sector, Synaptic has applied the latest technology to develop Webline Play, the new protection lead generation app. With all the functionality of Webline but in an easily integrated, embedded form, advisers and distributors can offer a more direct,
improved customer experience and have the information they need to provide effective, tailored advice. Available as a customisable web app, Webline Play blends seamlessly into any website. It’s so easy to use that you’ll be able to generate more warm leads, increasing your take-up rate whilst freeing resources to grow your business.
Visit www.synaptic.co.uk/webline-play or call us on 0800 783 4477 to arrange a demonstration.
  ]]></page><page Index="52" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[              52
How do we make life ‘better’?
 Jacqui Gillies | Marketing and Proposition Director | Guardian
We’ve deliberately departed from some of the conventional norms
in protection product design. We’ve done this because we believe we should respond to what advisers and their clients need rather than be constrained by industry practice.
In line with our brand promise ‘Life. Made better.’, we aim to challenge the ‘typical’ way things are done and make ‘better’ a reality. For us ‘better’ isn’t about changing one big thing. It’s about constantly improving lots
of little things that collectively make a big difference.
Crystal-clear critical illness definitions
Our biggest challenge to the norm is
our critical illness definitions. Typically, providers define the quality of their critical illness policies by the number of illnesses they cover. At Guardian, we’re focused on offering the best possible cover for the most common illnesses. We’ve done this
by simplifying our policy wording, making
it easy for advisers and their clients to understand what they’re covered for. And, in most cases, confirmation from a UK Consultant is all we need for a claim. That means no detailed medical evidence to prove if a critical illness is serious enough. Our crystal clear policy wording means customers know exactly what they’re covered for – creating certainty and building trust.
A few highlights:
• Heart attack: Typically, providers ask for detailed medical reports to assess if a heart attack is serious enough. At Guardian, confirmation from a UK Consultant is all we need.
• Cancer: Most providers don’t pay out on all malignant skin cancers. But surely all malignant skin cancers are critical? We think so. That’s why a Guardian policy pays out on all malignant skin cancers – no ifs,
no buts.
• Multiple sclerosis: Typically, providers want to see evidence that someone’s suffering symptoms of multiple sclerosis at the time the claim is made. We think that’s a little unfair when you consider symptoms can come and go. At Guardian,
we pay out if a UK Consultant Neurologist says there ‘has been’ an impairment due to multiple sclerosis, even if the symptoms aren’t apparent when they make a claim.
Our cover upgrade promise
On top of that, to make sure all our critical illness policies are future proofed, we offer our existing customers a unique promise. At claim, we check both the definitions they bought and the definitions for new customers. And we pay out if the claim
is valid under either. Occasionally, we
may introduce changes that we won’t automatically upgrade. If this happens, we’ll offer existing customers the chance to pay to add them.
These are just two examples of how the Guardian brand intends to make sure every family has protection that they truly believe in. Find out more at guardian1821.co.uk/advisers
   ]]></page><page Index="53" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                THE LIFE INSURANCE BRAND TRUSTED BY FAMILIES FOR 198 YEARS
Find out more at: adviser.guardian1821.co.uk/about
Guardian Financial Services Limited is an appointed representative of Scottish Friendly Assurance Society Limited which is authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority and Prudential Regulation Authority. Registered office: Scottish Friendly House, 16 Blythswood Square, Glasgow G2 4HJ. Registration number 110002. Guardian Financial Services Limited is registered in England and Wales under number 11115769. Registered office: 11 Strand, London WC2N 5HR.
 GFS A 0161 0919
                                                                                GRY_027_Guardian Brand_ad_A4_AW.indd 1 03/10/2019 12
]]></page><page Index="54" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  54
 Robo: friend or foe?
  Andrew Fay | CEO and co-founder | Munnypot Enterprise
New generations of customers are demanding more flexibility at their fingertips when managing their financial affairs. Not only do they want fully personalised experiences, they want digital services and 24/7 access. Munnypot Enterprise can offer all of this and more. Its solution sits alongside your face-to-face advisors, providing digital financial planning advice that is fully automated and immediately accessible to your customers.
Digitaladviceisgrowingfast
By 2025 it is estimated that $16 trillion in assetswillbemanagedbyRobo-Advisory services, roughly three times the amount managed by BlackRock1. UK robo-advisors currently manage almost $15 billion in assets, and the predicted annual growth in AuM is 41.7%.2 Should you worry about the disruptive nature of these new competitors?
Introducing digital advice to your business may seem like a risk. But there are enormous potential rewards to gain from offering such a service to some segments of your existing client base. An opportunity of this kind can also allow you to attract new clients while significantly cutting your operating costs.
Digitaladvicecanbenefit your business
1. Increaseprofitabilityofexistingclients
Reducing the operational costs of servicing existing clients frees up capacity to better service high net worth customers. This can increase the profitability of all customers, regardless of wealth bracket.
2. Getthenextgenerationinthedoor
Millennials are looking for fast, readily available,digitalsolutionstostartsaving and investing now. Attracting future generations enables you to develop a direct client relationship from early on in their investment journey. As their net worth grows, you can reach out directly to offer higher value and more complex personal face-to-face advice.
 With Munnypot Enterprise, you can access the
c. 74% of UK households who are currently unadvised3. Offering this invaluable service can help you to make existing clients more profitable, to engage the next generation and to access the mass market.
 ]]></page><page Index="55" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  55
 Offering simple, personalised advice via a digital solution enables you to instantly multiply your target market and generate revenues at very low cost.
3. Provideadvicetoall,regardlessofwealth
Only 11% of UK adults can afford to receive face to face financial advice from an IFA3. The solution for servicing customers in the lower wealth bracket is digital. Offering simple, personalised advice via a digital solution enables you to instantly multiply your target market, and generate revenues at very low marginal cost.
We believe Munnypot Enterprise complements your service and is the right solution for you
1. 100% automated FCA compliant financial advice
Add value to your client’s investment experience by providing them with a digital tool to increase their confidence when it comes to making the right investment decisions. With a customer journey that prioritises financial education and suitability reporting, you can rest assured your clients are in safe hands.
2. Automatedannualreviews
The Munnypot Enterprise solution can automatically reach out to clients on a yearly basis to provide annual reviews. The review can be entirely personalised based on both investment performance and wealth bracket, as well as including all required suitability checks.
3. Customer-centricgoal-basedinvesting
Munnypot Enterprise enables clients
to save towards personalised, tangible goals. It will automatically notify them when they hit important milestones on the way to achieving their goal. If the investment veers off track, the service will provide further advice on the options available to get them back on track.
With Munnypot Enterprise, you can access the c. 74% of UK households who are currently unadvised3. Offering this invaluable service can help make existing clients more profitable, engage the next generation
and access the mass market. In a world of evolving technology, this is the perfect tool to complement the products and services you currently offer.
Get in touch with us today to launch your tailored white labelled online investment advice solution. Let us help you to generate significant revenues at minimum marginal cost, bring on new customers, and free up advisors
to focus on complex arrangements for HNW customers.
FormoreinformationonMunnypot Enterprise or to arrange a demo, please email andrew.fay@munnypot.com or contact us on 01293 224 281
Important Information
Munnypot Enterprise is a trading name of Munnypot Limited which is an Appointed Representative of Resolution Compliance Limited which is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.
FRN 574048.
1 Source: Deloitte, The expansion of Robo-Advisory in Wealth management https://www2.deloitte.com/content/dam/Deloitte/ de/Documents/financial-services/Deloitte-Robo-safe.pdf
2 Source: Statista https://www.statista.com/outlook/337/156/ robo-advisors/united-kingdom
3 Source: Deloitte, The next frontier, The future of automated financial advice in the UK https://www2.deloitte.com/content/ dam/Deloitte/nl/Documents/financial-services/deloitte-nl-fsi- the-future-of-automated-financial-advice-in-the-uk.pdf
 ]]></page><page Index="56" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                 YOURS NOT OURS
The lifeblood of an IFA’s business is the strength of their relationship with their clients. They are your clients and we understand how important that it is to you. We are committed to supporting the IFA by providing low cost discretionary fund management without compromising investment standards or an adviser’s relationship with their clients.
We’re available on 13 platforms, compatible with all the leading risk profilers and offer 29 portfolios across a range of strategies – including ethical portfolios.
www.tattoninvestments.com
CONTACT US
020 7139 1470
All calls to and from our office are recorded for regulatory purposes.
enquiries@tattonim.com
                           This content is for financial advisers only.
Tatton is a trading style of Tatton Investment Management Limited, which is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Financial Services Register number 733471. Tatton Investment Management Limited is registered in England and Wales No. 08219008. Registered address: Paradigm House,
Brooke Court, Wilmslow, Cheshire, SK9 3ND.
]]></page></pages></Search>