<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="52"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Connection
                           Issue:
Q1 2019
  Selection of industry features for the professional adviser
  Reckless Cautious. Nick Dixon, Aegon
Platforms or SIPPs? BPS or flat fees? Jessica List, Curtis Banks The future of portfolio management. Steve Nelson, the lang cat
 ›› Market outlook. Vanguard
›› Where next for investors? John Stopford, Investec Asset Management
›› 2019: The year of sustainable investing? Phoebe Stone, LGT Vestra
›› Active investing – passive pricing. Mark Parry, BMO Global Asset Management
›› Give your CIP a PROD! John Lycett, RSMR
PROTECTION
›› Five good reasons. Jacqui Gillies, Guardian
›› Digging deeper into Protection policies. Mark Cracknell, Aviva ›› Is it true that insurers try not to pay claims? Aviva
›› Choice. Ian Berrett, Old Mutual Wealth
 FREE
        How to avoid FOMO investing
John Husselbee, Verbatim
Download the Synaptic Risk White Paper for free
           • White Paper at www. synaptic.co.uk
• Stochastic modelling, risk and retirement
• What do we know about risk? Eric Armstrong • Kids and money. Paul Quarendon
                            ]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                         Our best ideas for your clients
  The RSMR Discretionary Portfolio Service - Rfolios - has been created to deliver improved investor outcomes, simplify the advice process and enhance the overall client experience.
 We recognise that financial advisers continue to be challenged in an evolving regulatory environment. Selecting and managing investments requires specialised knowledge and time to maintain suitable client portfolios.
The RSMR Discretionary Portfolios can be mapped to match existing risk profiling tools with choice and flexibility being key for the investor and adviser alike.
Offering a choice of income and growth and SRI options with active and passive strategies all the portfolios are backed by RSMR’s unrivalled experience and track record in supporting UK advisory firms.
For more information, call us on 01535 656 555 or email us at enquiries@rsmgroup.co.uk
Important Notice
This is intended for investment professionals and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons. Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments and any income from them can fall as well as rise, is not guaranteed and your clients may get back less that they invest. RSMR Portfolio Services Limited is a limited company registered in England and Wales under Company number 07137872. Registered office at Number 20, Ryefield Business Park, Belton Road, Silsden BD20 0EE. RSMR Portfolio Services Limited is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority under number 788854. © RSMR 2018. RSMR is a registered Trademark.
Number 20, Ryefield Business Park, Belton Road, Silsden BD20 0EE
01535 656 555 | enquiries@rsmgroup.co.uk | rsmr.co.uk
      ]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  How to avoid FOMO investing 4 John Husselbee,Verbatim
Is ’reckless caution’ having a negative impact 6 on your clients’ savings?
Nick Dixon,Aegon
Platforms or SIPPs? BPS or flat fees? 8 Jessica List, Curtis Banks Group
The future of portfolio management 10 Steve Nelson, the lang cat
US Fed policy update: A single rate hike likely 12 in 2019
Joe Davis,Vanguard
Where next for Investors? 14 John Stopford, Investec Asset Management
2019:The year of sustainable investing? 16 Phoebe Stone, LGT Vestra
Active investing - passive pricing 18 Mark Parry, BMO Global Asset Management
Humans and Investing 20 Dan Norman, TCF Investments & MAPS
Give your CIP a Prod! 22 Jon Lycett, RSMR
Five good reasons 24 Jacqui Gillies, Guardian
Look a little closer 26 Mark Cracknell, Aviva
Is it true that insurers try not to 27 pay out on claims?
Aviva
Choice 28 Ian Berrett, Old Mutual Wealth
Money doesn’t grow on trees ... 30 Paul Quarendon, Synaptic Software Limited
What do we know about risk? 34 Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software Limited
Stochastic modelling, risk and retirement 36 Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software Limited
Synaptic Risk Rating Table 39
 3
 Synaptic Risk: White Paper
CONTENTS
 Contact Details
Synaptic Software Limited
Fusion 1, Parkway, Solent Business Park Whiteley, Hampshire PO15 7AA
Sales: 0800 783 4477
To sign up for Connection magazine visit
www.synaptic.co.uk
All editorial or advertising enquiries should be directed to:
Eric Armstrong
eric.armstrong@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882994
Sarah Miller
marketing@synaptic.co.uk 0800 783 4477
We are delighted to be able to announce the publication of our White Paper on risk – covering the full process from client risk-profiling through to investment risk-rating.
The role of risk has always been important, but prior to ‘open architecture’ and the advent of platforms, the main custodians
of risk were the providers, large insurance companies for the main part. In the modern era, risk has taken centre stage, forming
the basis of the suitability for the personal recommendations made by advisers of all types. MiFID II has finally set the bar at its highest level ever, where suitability must be proven at ‘Point of Sale’, but also at annual review. MiFID II also states that firms should know how their tools work:
“... ensuring all tools, such as risk assessment profiling tools or tools to assess a client’s knowledge and experience, employed
in the suitability assessment process are fit-for-purpose and are appropriately designed for use with their clients, with any limitations identified and actively mitigated through the suitability assessment process.” COBS9A.29EU
Without effective tools the adviser cannot function effectively. And without an objective measure for risk or forecast for investment growth, it is impossible to create a meaningful plan around a client’s objectives or gain ‘informed consent’. We at Synaptic believe that the forward-looking methodology of the Moody’s Analytics (Moody’s) stochastic engine offers the best framework for consistent application of risk.
Our Paper explains some of the background to risk as the driver of investment returns and the core consideration (alongside management of costs) of retail investment management.
The good news is that advisers can now consider putting the Moody’s investment strategy at the heart of their risk assessments by accessing the Synaptic Risk proposition ... at our cost (so free to you). More information on this offer is available at www.synaptic.co.uk
Eric Armstrong
Editor
  If you no longer wish to receive a copy of this publication, please email marketing@synaptic.co.uk
The Connection magazine is published by Synaptic Software Limited. The views expressed throughout do not necessarily reflect the views of Synaptic or any other party affiliated to Synaptic, and no liability can be assumed for the accuracy or completeness of the content, nor should any of the content be used as the sole basis of any advice offered or received.
Content is offered on an information only basis, and intended only for an audience of professional advisers regulated by the FCA. Content is published with all rights reserved and any reproduction of content, wholly or in part, can be made with the written permission of the publishers. This applies to all forms of the magazine - digital and print, and any part thereof.
]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  4
  How to avoid FOMO investing
 John Husselbee | Co- Fund Manager | HC Verbatim Portfolio Growth Funds
Politically speaking, recent years have been among the most divisive and volatile in decades – with Brexit, Donald Trump taking the White House and a swathe of populist parties winning power around the world.
And yet, for the most part, stock markets have charted an upward path against this backdrop, breaking and re-breaking records for all-time highs several times over.
For me, a major impetus behind this has been what we call FOMO investing – and for those not up to date with their text acronyms, that means fear of missing out. This is basically the feeling of anxiety that an exciting event may currently be happening elsewhere:
what drives people to move into the other, apparently faster-moving, supermarket queue or motorway lane.
As everyone knows, such action often results in that new queue grinding to a halt and the one recently vacated starting to move. And while switching queues might only end up costing a few minutes of time, such ‘grass is always greener’ tendencies can prove extremely damaging for long- term wealth generation.
Patience is a cornerstone of our philosophy but, given the sheer amount happening in the world at present – and the 24-hour news cycle fanning the flames – it is easier said
than done: and strong results from many equity markets in recent years have clearly tempted many into faster-moving queues.
To be clear, we are not saying equity investing is the wrong way to go: equities have clearly outperformed cash and inflation, and form the bedrock of a well-diversified portfolio as the main driver of long-term returns. Another similar acronym is enough to encourage investors into equities – FOLO, or fear of losing out – with inflation eating into the value of assets held in cash.
Data on the FTSE 100 makes the attraction clearer: looking at returns going back to 1986, a one-year investment in the index at any point gives a 76% chance of a positive outcome at the end of that period (although it is important to stress the maximum possible fall has been around 50%).
As would be expected, the longer people are prepared to commit capital, the greater chance they get of a positive result, and a 20-year investment during the period has always yielded a positive return.
Problems can come when investors attempt to pick between equity markets and again, some basic stats bear this out. $100 invested in the MSCI World Index just after the Lehman’s crisis in 2008 would be worth around $200 today, despite a near 50% fall in the immediate aftermath. If you tried to pick a market however, $100 invested in the MSCI USA Index would now be worth around $250 while the same amount in the MSCI World ex-USA would have given you around $150.
 While we look to add value – and maximise returns within those boundaries – via tactical allocation and fund selection, our portfolios are built specifically to avoid FOMO-type investing.
 ]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 5
  As would be expected, the longer people are prepared to commit capital, the greater chance they get of a positive result, and a 20-year investment during the period has always yielded a positive return.
Considering investment options back in 2008, it would have made sense to avoid
the epicentre of the sub-prime crisis and focus on parts of the world enjoying cleaner balance sheets – and these are exactly the kind of difficult questions investors must face if they try to pick markets. The MSCI World, a proxy for a broad equity portfolio, charts the middle path between these: not the worst or best but a solid end return without FOMO panic.
A further layer of complexity comes when people try to time their moves into and
out of markets: over the years, even the greatest investors have got this wrong more than right.
As we have said, over the long-term, equities have outperformed and we believe the best way to approach this is to imagine returns as a straight line moving upwards, from bottom left to top right on a chart. Of course, returns are not linear like this and there are plenty
of ups and downs along the way, but if you practice what we call noise-cancelling investment, the result has been strong performance.
The alternative, often driven by the dreaded FOMO, is to focus too much on the volatile reality of markets and investing according to daily ups and downs can risk falling into
irrational behaviour and making costly mistakes.
For us, a properly diversified multi-asset fund can take these FOMO concerns away, but this should not be taken to mean aggressive shifts into and out of asset classes: asset allocators often talk about the freedom to zero weight certain areas as a sign of an ‘active’ approach but we feel this fundamentally misses the point.
As Harry Markowitz – one of the pioneers of modern portfolio theory – said, diversification “is the only free lunch in finance”. While it might be uncomfortable to hold a falling asset, something else is likely to be rising at the same time and
it is the overall blend that helps produce
a smoother performance ride over the long term. Zero weighting completely throws that out and, again, runs the risk of pandering to FOMO tendencies.
Our multi-asset approach is target risk, meaning each portfolio is run within predetermined volatility bands and strategic asset allocation (SAA) is designed with those targets in mind. While we look to add value – and maximise returns within those boundaries – via tactical allocation and fund selection, our portfolios are built specifically to avoid FOMO-type investing.
Our SAA will change each year to meet volatility targets, but you will never find aggressive shifts into rising markets: on
the contrary, we usually want to be adding exposure to areas that have done less well and are therefore cheaper, in line with a basic buy low, sell high philosophy.
Ultimately, our core message is that limiting losses as well as generating gains – what
we call winning by not losing – rather than chasing gains and fleeing losses, has proved an efficient way of building performance towards meeting financial goals.
John Husselbee is the co-fund manager for the HC Verbatim Portfolio Growth Fund range, part of the Verbatim range of risk- managed multi-asset investment solutions. To find out more about Verbatim visit www.verbatimassetmanagement.co.uk or contact us on 0808 12 40 007.
The value of investments and any income from them can go down as well as up and is not guaranteed. Your clients could get back less than they originally invested. Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The portfolios’ investments are subject
to normal fluctuations and other risks inherent when investing in securities. Verbatim Asset Management has taken due care and attention in preparing this document, which is solely for the use of professional advisers. Verbatim cannot be held responsible for any inaccuracies arising out of information detailed within and will not accept liability for any loss arising out of or in connection with its use. This article is for information only and should not be deemed as advice.
  ]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  6
Is ’reckless caution’ having a negative impact on your clients’ savings?
 Nick Dixon | Investment Director | Aegon
Britons appear to be naturally risk-averse, with two in five choosing to avoid investment risk. As a result, large numbers of investors could be missing out on the investment growth they need.
A recent survey by Aegon of more than 2,000 UK adults shows that the majority of consumers are risking financial stagnation, and investment growth well below the rate of inflation, because they worry about taking investment risk.
Concerns about making the wrong decision when it comes to investing were cited by more than a quarter of those surveyed (28%). In addition, 12% said they were more cautious now than they were a decade ago. Yet 14% would be “more open” to taking more risk if they were told that good investment returns over the long-term meant some risk needed to be accepted.
Despite the UK Bank Base rate averaging
just 0.5%* each year over the last 10 years,
it seems most savers would still prefer the perceived safety blanket of bank accounts
to stock market investments. This lack of confidence and unwillingness to take risk means opportunities for returns above inflation are being missed. To compare, the average fund in the ABI Mixed Investment 40- 85% Shares sector returned 7.5%* a year over the same ten-year period.
Risk should be measured
Regardless of the current turbulent political and investment landscape, failing to take measured risk is not prudent. However, more than half of those surveyed said their appetite for risk was “low” or “zero”, preferring lower returns for minimal potential loss.
Just 6% of people said family and friends would describe them as “risk takers”. And only 13% said they would opt for either high or adventurous levels of risk in return for high or very high long-term returns.
Knowledge a key barrier
As well as a lack of risk appetite among savers, the survey suggests a poor understanding
of investments and highlights a general
lack of knowledge about where to turn for professional advice. 80% of those surveyed said they have not sought financial advice, while almost a third suggested they would likely rely on money influencers in the media for ideas and guidance.
 * Morningstar Direct, ten-year annualised returns of UK Base Rate and ABI Mixed Investments 40-85% Shares (pen) to 31 December 2018. Past performance is no guide to future performance.
   ]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 7
  A recent survey by Aegon of more than 2,000 UK adults shows that the majority of consumers are risking financial stagnation, and investment growth well below the rate of inflation, because they worry about taking investment risk.
  More than two-thirds said they would be “unlikely” to invest any extra money they have into riskier investments, such as stocks and shares, within the next year. Of those who said they are more risk-averse now than they were 10 years ago, 31% are nervous about the overall state of the global economy, a quarter (24%) have concerns that there will be another financial crash, 19% have made financial losses in the past and are now more cautious with their money, and 12% are uncertain about the best investment strategy to use.
This comes at a time when market volatility has been increasing in a number of markets, including the US. Many investors appear
to be nervous about how this might affect their finances if they take on a degree of investment risk.
Good financial advice can boost savers’ confidence
While fear and uncertainty seem to be key factors holding people back from taking increased risks with their investments, their lack of understanding about the balance between investment risk and potential rewards highlights the value of good financial advice as a way to build savers’ confidence, improve their understanding of risk and to inform the right long-term investment decisions.
Without it, the biggest risk investors may be running is the risk that they miss out on the potential long-term rewards that investing in a well-balanced, diversified portfolio can offer.
Conversations about risk, and the use of
risk rating models and client suitability questionnaires have arguably never been more important or powerful as advisers help their clients understand their own attitudes to and appetite for risk.
The Aegon Core Portfolios range of funds are now risk rated by Synaptic to help advisers match the funds to the risk profiles of their clients.
Please go to www.aegon.co.uk/investments, or speak to your usual Aegon contact to find out more.
The information in this article is based on research among more than 2,000 UK Adults, conducted by Opinium on Aegon’s behalf in October 2018. The sample has been weighted to be nationally representative.
  ]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  8
 Platforms or SIPPs? BPS or flat fees?
  Jessica List | Pension Technical Manager | Curtis Banks Group
Traditionally SIPPs have been seen as bespoke products, designed solely for investors with very high fund values or for those looking to invest primarily in unusual investments. In recent years, however, the range of products marketing themselves as SIPPs has broadened considerably.
SIPPs were already known for their flexibility, in relation to retirement options as much
as investment opportunities, which meant they were perfectly placed to become the product of choice for taking advantage of the pension freedoms. As a result, there are now many ‘mid-market’ and ‘e-SIPP’ type products available, which tend to offer more streamlined investment solutions suitable for a much broader range of investors.
The traditional purpose of platforms was to give investors an easy way to hold multiple savings products in the same place: SIPPs, ISAs and GIAs – all held together. However, it seems that the reality is somewhat different, with plenty of evidence that the average platform investor holds on average considerably fewer than two products on each platform.
Traditional usage aside, one of the big differences between most SIPP and platform pensions is the fee structure. The majority of SIPP products have a flat fee structure, whereas the majority of platforms charge percentage-based fees. We recently commissioned a pricing analysis paper by
the lang cat to support the launch of our new product, Your Future SIPP, and of
the chosen group of platforms and life companies all except one had a percentage- based fee model.
It’s commonly understood that percentage fees will work out cheaper for very low fund values and that fixed fees work out best for those with very large pensions. But where does that cross-over happen and is it that simple?
Of course, the answers depend on which products you’re considering, so there are as many answers as there are combinations of products to compare. For this purpose then, we’ll use the findings from the lang cat’s paper. The first part of their price analysis focuses on funds in the accumulation stage of saving, and compares a number of pension products across the market, primarily using percentage-based charging, with a fixed fee of £260 +VAT.
You might be surprised to hear that the fixed fee works out about market rate for fund values of £75,000, and by the £500,000 mark it is approximately a quarter of the
market rate. Looking at the same group
of providers but including their costs for a pension in drawdown, the fixed fee model is market rate at a fund value of £200,000, and about a third of market rate by £500,000.
Admittedly, very few fully bespoke SIPP products will be available for that level of flat fee. However, many of the mid-market type products will be. Although relatively simple compared to their multiple-investment- account, commercial-property-holding cousins, these mid-market products are still likely to offer more investment flexibility than a platform pension, and may have other advantages over them too. For example, cost is only one of many factors, and service may be a key differentiator in the choice between a SIPP or platform pension. Many of these mid-market products will be offered by dedicated SIPP providers, meaning advisers and their clients will have access to the same levels of administration, service and support as the provider’s bespoke SIPP holders.
 ]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  9
 One of the big differences between most SIPP and platform pensions is the fee structure. The majority of SIPP products have a flat fee structure, whereas the majority of platforms charge percentage-based fees.
SIPP providers are also more likely to offer a fully flexible range of retirement benefit and death benefit options for their clients, and their staff are pension specialists. It’s certainly true that you have to take care to choose the right SIPP provider, given some of the recent headlines. Legacy issues are working their way through the industry and poor practices are being weeded out, but this means that despite the negative press, the outlook for the SIPP market is good. We believe it will emerge stronger, and well placed to continue serving the needs of pension freedoms customers. At the same time, platforms have hardly been immune from their own challenges, with many reported issues with re-platforming and reams of regulatory changes.
Of course, there are many factors to consider with any pension and transfer decision. However, it’s worth considering that with the range of SIPPs available today, they may be valid options for people who wouldn’t traditionally be seen as SIPP investors. Is it worth thinking twice the next time you see a client with a pension fund over £75,000?
If you would like any more information about Curtis Banks or the Your Future SIPP, please call us on 01473 296 950 or email enquiries@curtisbanks.co.uk
 PRODUCT
    CHARGING APPROACH
  CORE CHARGES
  PENSION CHARGES
   DRAWDOWN CHARGES
  Curtis Banks Your Future SIPP
  Fixed-fee
 £260 + VAT for investment partner list, £560 + VAT for full investment range.
Pension only
  £120 + VAT for designating funds, £150 + VAT per annum for income.
 Prudential Retirement Account
    Stepped %
   Steps down from 0.45% to 0.25%
    Royal London Pension Portfolio
  Stepped %
 Steps down from 0.90% to 0.35%
  £199 one off drawdown fee (removed if plan in force for over 12 months)
 Scottish Widows Retirement Account
   Stepped %
  Steps down from 0.90% to 0.10%
  Aegon Retirement Choices (ARC)
    Tiered %
  From 0.60% to 0.45% capped at £1,215 pa
     £75 annual fee
  AJ Bell Investcentre
  Hybrid
From 0.20% to 0.10%
   Between £30 to £50 quarterly charge + VAT depending on fund value. Waved above £200k.
  £150 + VAT flexi-access drawdown charge. Menu of additional drawdown charges.
 Alliance Trust Savings
   Fixed-fee
Fixed-fee applies per wrapper. £210 + VAT for standard SIPP, £350 (no VAT) on the inclusive fee option where trades are bundled in.
 Additional £90 admin charge on top of the usual pension fee.
 Ascentric
   Tiered %
 0.30% down to 0.06% (minimum £180 annual fee)
      Aviva Platform
   Tiered %
Tiered from 0.40% down to 0.15%. Non-pension wrappers have lower tiered fees that start at 0.25%.
  Elevate
   Stepped %
 Stepped charge from 0.35% to 0.25%
    FundsNetwork
    Hybrid
  0.25% + £45 annual fee
       James Hay MiPlan
  Hybrid
0.25% down to 0.01%
  Additional £179 fee for portfolios lower than £200k
 Annual £154 charge and £100 set-up fee.
 Novia
   Tiered %
 From 0.50% down to 0.15%
   £62.50 + VAT charge for any 12-month period when an income payment is made.
 Nucleus
   Tiered %
 0.35% down to 0.05%
    Old Mutual Wealth
    Tiered %
  0.50% down to 0.15%
       Seven IM
   Tiered %
 0.30% down to 0.15%
   £100 + VAT if the account value is less than £75K
  £135 pa for taking income, £75 for each crystalisation.
  Standard Life Wrap
  Tiered %
From 0.55% down to 0.25%. Like Aviva, non-pension wrappers have lower charges. Lower still 'core terms' are available for adviser firms placing large quantities (£20m+) of business. This results in 10 basis points off the pension.
   Transact
    Tiered %
  From 0.5% down to 0.05%
  £80 annual charge
     Zurich Intermediary Platform
   Tiered %
 From 0.35% down to 0.10%
   £75 annual fee
      ]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  10
           The future of portfolio management
  Steve Nelson | Head of research | the lang cat
Hello again. So, in my last column I hinted that this time round I’d be taking a look at what the future of portfolio management on platforms might have in store. Consider this a sequel then. Or the difficult second album. They’re always just as good, right?
Awkward. Anyway, in my last column for the fine people at Capita, I took a swift look at the main methods of Centralised Investment Proposition (CIP1) construction on platforms and I shared my views on some of the pros and cons of each method. Now, I’m going to turn that on its head and take a punt at what the future might have in store and how some things may change.
Predictions are a tricky business to get right (although, I’ve long since stopped betting on Scotland to qualify for anything) but the truth is that if you ground them in enough common sense and stretch out the timeframe long enough then no-one can possibly hold you to account. Bonus! That’s a top class consultancy technique that you can have for free.
I jest of course. Let’s cut to the chase and have a look at three things which I think the future might have in store.
Building a wall between financial planning and investment management
No, not that kind of wall. We’re not trying to make platforms great again, they’re alright as they are. It’s a metaphor, innit.
What we see is that lots of firms have different people within the same firms running elements of the house model portfolio framework. This can create a series of unfortunate events with permission and
rebalancing issues causing a long trail of version control dead. Frankly, if you were to build the UK financial services sector from the ground up, this situation would simply not exist.
In short, I reckon running advisory models and investment management functions under the same roof at any kind of scale doesn’t
feel sustainable to me. Doing it properly will require either discretionary permissions, outsourcing or a watertight series of processes and controls.
 I reckon running advisory models and investment management functions under the same roof at any kind of scale doesn’t feel sustainable to me. Doing it properly will require either discretionary permissions, outsourcing or a watertight series of processes and controls.
1 We know from our various items of research that CIPs are the centre of gravity for platform business which is why we talk about it so much. 86% of respondents to our November 2018 State of the Adviser Nation study (235 respondents) state that they run a CIP
 ]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 11
            What we see is that lots of firms have different people within the same firms running elements of the house model portfolio framework. This can create a series of unfortunate events with permission and rebalancing issues causing a long trail of version control dead.
Ultimately, I’m betting that the market might polarise to the point that advisory models in the truest sense are generally found only in small specialist operations or in firms where functions are separated. We’re already seeing tonnes of adjacent evidence in the market where many financial planners, particularly in the next generation, are favouring behavioural financial planning over tinkering with investment products.
Tech will make things better
Well, of course tech will get better because that’s what tech does. Slow down Nostradamus!
In the longer term, Blockchain and distributed ledger technology has the potential to be a huge disruptor in financial services making lots of processes much easier (AML, onboarding, suitability et al), reducing the admin burden, building and storing client profiles which in turn will drive better client segmentation.
In the shorter term, we’re going to see some very clever algorithms from some very, very clever people delivering tweaks and enhancements to current processes and practises. While we understand the drive towards industrialised, commoditised CIPs, current practise leaves little wiggle room for individualisation.
I reckon in the short to medium future we’ll see more developments around tailoring for individual needs. Think stuff around tax- optimisation and individualisation (e.g. ethical overlays) of otherwise off-the-shelf portfolios. Some of this kit is hitting the shelves now. It’ll soon be the standard.
A problem for the ages
I’ll win no awards for pointing out the potential implications and concerns of an ageing market for individual advice. Why I’m doubling down on this concern is how this squares up with the current accepted wisdom around safe withdrawal rate theory + drawdown + cash management being the vehicle of choice for retirement portfolio management.
While I can get on board with much, if
indeed all, of this thinking, I have two recurring worries: (1) What happens to the small minority of customers for whom the safe withdrawal rate pans out as being less than safe and (2) how is the sector going to (efficiently) service an ageing population who, in the nicest and politest sense, may not wish to be serviced in their twilight years.
What could tip the balance? Annuities
will continue to play a role and we may
see another generation of sophisticated guaranteed income products (including products that offer flexibility with some element of guarantee). Data and technology will drive the market here. Guarantees may become more affordable as the industry harnesses the power of big data to design better products.
More obviously, technology will enable income sustainability kit. Algorithms that
can analyse investment performance in the context of risk and objectives will enable portfolios to be managed, work seamlessly with the cash management aspect of platform tech, be rebalanced and more easily reviewed. This paradigm doesn’t exist yet, but it will.
Dystopia/utopia?
So, there we have it. Three things that may or may not happen at an arbitrary point in the future. But let’s close our eyes, say a collective prayer to our deity of choice and imagine
a post-Brexit utopia where it matters little whether that nerdy guy from that Scottish consultancy with the weird name was right or not. You’ll be too content to care.
Visit www.langcatfinancial.co.uk for more from Steve and the rest of the lang cats.
 ]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  12
US Fed policy update: A single rate hike likely in 2019
 Joe Davis, PhD | Global Chief Economist | Vanguard
Anxious investors, take heart: The US Federal Reserve hears you.
Policy uncertainty and market volatility
of late have prompted us to revise our expectations for the Fed’s target for short-term interest rates in 2019. Our new baseline forecast is for a single additional rate increase, the tenth since December 2015 and perhaps the final hike of the current monetary-policy cycle. It represents a change from the 2019 outlook we published last month.
To be sure, Fed policymakers themselves have signalled in recent days a willingness
to reconsider their path forward. Not long ago that path included as many as three expected rate hikes this year. The latest forecast from the Fed’s policy-setting Open Market Committee anticipates a pair of 2019 rate increases. Meanwhile, bond investors
in aggregate now suspect the Fed will stand firm, keeping its current target of 2.25%– 2.5% in place for a while. Thus our revised baseline estimate of a one-more-and-done approach to rate-setting this year puts us inbetween the Fed’s own crystal ball and that of the bond market.
Markets underestimated the Fed in 2018 and are doing so again for 2019
   Notes: The historical federal funds rate indicates the midpoint of the target range. Market forecasts reflect implied pricing from federal funds futures. Data are as at 31 December 2018.
Sources: Vanguard, Bloomberg, and the Federal Reserve.
  ]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 13
 We expect the Fed to hold its rate target steady for several months before raising rates, likely in June. Our forecast of the risk of US recession in this scenario now stands at 35%, up marginally from 30% in the outlook we issued last month.
 To treat the future with the deference it deserves, however, we believe economic
and market forecasts should be expressed in terms of probabilities. We don’t pretend that only one outcome can occur. Instead, we consider baseline, or most likely, scenarios, as well as potential outcomes to the upside and downside. Here are our revised expectations:
• Baseline: The Fed will hike rates just once in 2019. Our revised expectation
is based on an analysis of current policy uncertainty and anticipates that the current level of financial market volatility will persist through the first quarter.
In this case, the likelihood that market volatility will dent the real economy – the production of goods and services and their consumption – is high. We expect the Fed to hold its rate target steady
for several months before raising rates, likely in June. Our forecast of the risk of US recession in this scenario now stands at 35%, up marginally from 30% in the outlook we issued last month.
• Upside: Policy uncertainty and market volatility significantly recede before the end of the first quarter. In this case, there’s a higher likelihood that the Fed will raise rates twice this year, as we initially forecast. A second hike would
lift the Fed’s target to 2.75%–3.00%.
This was our baseline scenario in early December, but given recent conditions we now view it as the upside.
• Downside: Policy uncertainty and market volatility persist through the first half of the year. In this scenario, economic fundamentals are likely to be damaged and the Fed is likely to take a pass on any additional rate hikes. If the Fed does not raise rates by mid-2019, their window of opportunity could close and the next change in the target rate would likely be a reduction.
While we’ve revised our outlook for Fed policy, our investment outlook remains unchanged. Several factors will raise the risk of recession this year, but a slowdown in growth, led by the United States and China, is the most likely outcome. We also forecast:
• Periodic growth scares, sparking elevated levels of market volatility.
• Inflation remaining in check, in the
range of 2% or less, but an escalation in tariffs, oil prices or wages could alter that outlook. Even if price increases accelerate, however, our research shows that inflation-caused recessions have become rarer as a result of more proactive central bank action and anchored inflation expectations.
• US economic growth likely to decline toward 2% this year amid declining support from federal tax and spending policies and continued monetary policy normalisation. Higher wages are unlikely to funnel through to consumer prices.
For additional perspective on what the future may hold for investors, please see ‘Vanguard economic and market outlook
for 2019: Down but not out’ at https:// www.vanguard.co.uk/documents/adv/ literature/vg-economic-outlook-2019.pdf
Important risk information:
The value of investments, and the income from them, may fall or rise and investors may get back less than they invested. Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future results.
Other important information:
This material is for professional investors as defined under the MiFID II Directive only. Not for public distribution.
This article is for educational purposes only and is not a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell investments.
The opinions expressed in this article are those of the author and individuals quoted and may not be representative of Vanguard Asset Management, Ltd.
Issued by Vanguard Asset Management, Ltd, which is authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority.
   ]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  14
  Where next for investors?
 John Stopford | Head of Multi-Asset Income | Investec Asset Management
Last year was a tough one for investors, says John Stopford, portfolio manager on the Investec Diversified Income Fund, and there isn’t a lot of clarity this year either. Investors need to do more than simply buy and hold.
Last year was a tough year for investors: a lot of assets went down and relatively few went up. This was in spite of significant optimism at the start of the year as synchronised global growth and US tax cuts buoyed investor sentiment. It concluded in one of the weakest Decembers in recorded history.
From here, says John Stopford, Head of Multi-Asset Income at Investec Asset Management, his team is asking itself a number of questions: Was that it? Is the correction over and will markets resume their bull run? Or is it the beginning of another bear market? In this scenario, any rally would be a selling opportunity rather than a buying opportunity. He says there are arguments on both sides.
There are plenty of reasons for caution, he suggests: “It is late in the business cycle and there does not appear to be a lot of upside for growth assets such as equities and corporate debt. Unemployment figures
around the world are low; this is a late cycle phenomenon and suggests there is not a lot of spare capacity.”
On the other hand, Stopford argues, below trend growth doesn’t equal a recession. The yield curve is showing a probability of
recession by 2020, but it remains an outside possibility for 2019, which means growth can keep going through to the middle of next year. Monetary policy is a major factor. Even though interest rates haven’t gone up a lot, Stopford says there is an argument that policy support is being removed too quickly.
He says: “The central banks seem to be
on autopilot and are much less inclined to respond to market weakness in this part of the cycle. As such, they are quite likely to continue to shrink their balance sheets and continue with quantitative tightening.
The central banks don’t want to reignite debt growth and that means they can’t ease policy as aggressively as they have done
in the past. It seems like things have to get worse before they will get material support from central banks.”
China is also a concern. The data is clearly weakening, with the country’s manufacturing tipping into contraction territory at the end
 The central banks seem to be on autopilot and
are much less inclined
to respond to market weakness in this part of the cycle. As such, they are quite likely to continue to shrink their balance sheets and continue with quantitative tightening.
 ]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 15
  The yield curve is showing a probability of recession by 2020, but
it remains an outside possibility for 2019, which means growth can keep going through to the middle of next year. Monetary policy is a major factor. Even though interest rates haven’t gone up a lot, there is an argument that policy support is being removed too quickly.
of last year. China is also held back by the trade war. He says: “There are reasons for both China and the US to get together and do a deal. However, their differences relate to economic power. The US has a legitimate concern that China has taken advantage
of trade rules and helped itself to US intellectual property to push itself forward.
This is about who will be the biggest dog in the pack for the next 30 years.” This is not
a question that resolves itself overnight.
In the meantime, the Chinese government has announced some easing measures, but the government is still worried about the country’s debt burden and is unlikely to turn the taps on significantly. Elsewhere fiscal easing looks unlikely. The boost from the US tax cuts will fade this year and with the Democrats in control of the House, further cuts look unlikely.
Europe is constrained by the EU rules. Corporate health says Stopford is also waning: “Earnings revisions are becoming more negative and buybacks are fading, particularly as bond yields have risen.”
On the other hand, it is plausible that earnings and growth will stabilise or the Federal Reserve will slow quantitative tightening. This would resolve some uncertainty and provide a boost for risk
assets. How is he managing this environment in his portfolios: “The way we think about the world is different: unlike a typical multi- asset manager, we believe it is difficult to
get big picture asset allocation calls right. The biggest opportunities lie in selecting individual securities. There are 25,000 individual securities, and we aim to build a portfolio of around 250.”
Stopford and his team look for those securities with certain characteristics aligned to the outcome of the Diversified Income Fund: “That is income with capital stability, low volatility and limited drawdowns. We want the income to be sustainable and resilient. In this portfolio, income does the heavy-lifting. We look for strong balance sheets and income in excess of what is necessary.”
Once he has found those securities, he looks at how they can be blended for resilience. “We make sure we’re properly diversified. Diversification by sensitivity to economic growth, for example, or interest rates. We are looking at behavioural characteristics not asset classes.”
As such, the group’s asset allocation discussions are not the typical ‘bonds versus equities’. At the moment, for example,
he is buying call options for the portfolio,
which look cheap given the insurance they provide. He adds: “Volatility is likely to be an important factor this year, both in economies and in markets. There are growing risks to the business cycle. That said, there will be opportunities as well. We want to make sure we capture both sides.”
To find out more about the Investec Diversified Income Fund, including its track record of minimising losses during extended bouts of volatility, please visit www.investecassetmanagement.com/DIF
Investment involves risks. Bond & Multi- Asset strategies may invest more than 35% of their assets in securities issued or guaranteed by an EEA state.
This communication is for institutional investors and financial advisors only. It is not to be distributed to the public or within a country where such distribution would be contrary to applicable law or regulations. Nothing herein should be construed as an offer to enter into any contract, investment advice, a recommendation of any kind, a solicitation of clients, or an offer to invest in any particular fund, product, investment vehicle or derivative. The information may discuss general market activity or industry trends and is not intended to be relied upon as a forecast, research or investment advice. The economic and market views presented herein reflect Investec Asset Management’s judgment as at the date shown and are subject to change without notice. There is
no guarantee that views and opinions expressed will be correct,
and Investec’s intentions to buy or sell particular securities in the future may change. The investment views, analysis and market opinions expressed may not reflect those of Investec as a whole, and different views may be expressed based on different investment objectives. English language copies of the Fund’s Prospectus and Key Investor Information Documents are available from Investec Asset Management on request. Issued, January 2019.
  ]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  16
  2019: the year of sustainable investing?
 Phoebe Stone | Head of Sustainable MPS | LGT Vestra
Every investment has an ‘impact’. Until recently, some of us have been guilty of ignoring the repercussions of where we have chosen to invest our money and been predominantly focused on one thing: financial return. But what if your investments could generate competitive financial returns and also be used to improve the health of our planet and the wellbeing of the global community?
The reality is that sustainable investing
is going to become ‘mainstream’. Once synonymous with negatively screening
for ‘sins stocks’ i.e. tobacco, alcohol, adult entertainment, armaments and gambling, investing with an awareness of global challenges is gaining new found popularity. Sustainable investing now sees investors demanding options that align with their personal values and prioritise environmental, social and governance factors whilst not sacrificing financial return. The socially responsible investing (SRI) market is now estimated to be worth almost $23 trillion globally, with around half of all assets managed in Europe and a third in the
United States. Staggeringly, the growth of Environmental, Social and Governance metrics (ESG) assets in the US is up over 200% over the past decade.1
The options available for clients are growing at an unprecedented rate across all asset classes, as are the number of related indices. The growing consensus across the market over the past few years is that a strong performance across ESG can be a representation of operational excellence. Companies that make a conscious effort
to tackle issues such as resource waste
and employee working conditions usually translate these ESG returns into financial ones. Even during economic downturns,
an ESG focus can enhance performance as factors such as good governance can feasibly result in lower corporate risk. When one compares traditional equity indices to the MSCI ESG-focused alternatives, it is clear that since 2012, annualised returns for ESG indices have matched or indeed exceeded their counterparts across developed and emerging markets.2
Sustainable equity portfolios that feature companies that have a strong ESG focus have the potential to outperform the market in the long-term. Sustainable investing can give investors an edge to mitigate risk and, in some cases, deliver outstanding long-term returns.3
Socially responsible investing is not a new phenomenon but, despite its growth, it has traditionally been a niche part of the market. 2019 may be the year where that all changes. Last year, the government released a report entitled ‘Growing a Culture of Social Impact Investing in the UK’.4 The report outlines
key recommendations to help encourage the growth of investing that has a positive impact on society as well as producing positive financial returns. Whilst the report focuses on a small aspect of sustainable investing, it signifies the wider change in
 ]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 17
  Sustainable investing now sees investors demanding options that align with their personal values and prioritise environmental, social and governance factors whilst not sacrificing financial return.
the public’s attitude to investments and shows the UK Government’s clear political commitment to supporting the market this year.5
A second indicator of sustainable investing’s advance towards being considered ‘mainstream’ is the increasing growth of fixed income ESG product innovation. Bloomberg has reported that the supply of ‘green bonds’ (bonds that are issued to raise money to tackle specific environmental challenges) is expected to increase more than 60% on 2017 from $155 billion to $250 billion. Of course, when compared to the world’s total bond market of nearly $100 trillion, this seems inconsequential, but issuance growth in 2017 and 2018 across all categories remains encouraging.6
Long-term thinking is a critical part of
ESG and sustainable investing. The UN Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs)
can be utilised as a framework for guiding investments that make a positive societal and environmental impact.7 The 17 SDGs were adopted in 2016 by all 193 UN member states to work towards a better future for all.8 The goals comprehensively detail targets and provide tangible indicators of impact to address global challenges such as climate change, education and healthcare. The
UN estimates that it will require between $5 trillion and $7 trillion dollars a year to achieve the goals by 2030.9 Crucially, in developing countries alone, the annual investment gap in major SDG sectors is estimated at $2.5 trillion a year.
Furthermore, with the current levels of private sector participation, there will be
a shortfall of $1.6 trillion to be covered by the public sector.10 Evidently, a significant acceleration of private investment in SDG sectors is required to aid the UN in meeting its targets. The long-term framework that the SDGs provide has encouraged us at LGT Vestra to engage with investments that not only have a deeply engrained ESG ethos or impact initiative, but investments that also encourage progress by supporting companies that show a measurable engagement with the SDGs.
Together, small changes can have a large impact
We are delighted to have our newly launched Sustainable Model Portfolio Service (SMPS) risk rated by Synaptic Risk. Our Sustainable MPS is a discretionary investment service comprising three diversified portfolios to meet a range of client objectives and risk profiles.
The ultimate goal of the portfolios is to support both socio-economic development and sustainable business practices, whilst generating strong and consistent investment returns for your clients. We believe that reducing environmental and societal negative impact on the world can achieve attractive levels of capital growth. Allocating capital
to companies focused on responsible and sustainable operational practices, enables us to all be a part of the sustainable movement.
For more information, please visit lgtvestra.com or call +44 (0)20 3207 8211.
Important information
LGT Vestra LLP is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Our regulation details are set out in the FCA register: Firm Reference No: 471048. Registered in England and Wales: OC329392. Registered office: 14 Cornhill, London, EC3V 3NR. This article is for information purposes only and is intended for professional financial advisers only. The wording contained in
this document is not to be construed as
an offer, advice, invitation or solicitation
to enter into any financial obligation, activity or promotion of any kind. Any information herein is given in good faith,
but is subject to change without notice and may not be accurate and complete for your purposes. This document is not intended
for distribution to, or use by, any individual or entities in any jurisdiction where such distribution would be contrary to the laws
of that jurisdiction or subject LGT Vestra LLP to any registration requirements. Investors should be aware that past performance is not an indication of future performance, the value of investments and the income derived from them may fluctuate and you may
not receive back the amount you originally invested.
1. ‘Sustainable Investing is Moving Mainstream’. J.P. Morgan 20/04/18. 2. MSCI ACWI ESG Screened vs MSCI ACWI. Accessed on 17/12/18.
3. Friede et al. 2015; Morgan Stanley 2015a; Trunow and Linder 2015. 4. ‘Growing a Culture of Social Impact Investing in the UK’. Department for Digital, Culture, Media & Sport, HM Treasury, Tracey Crouch MP and Stephen Barclay MP. 14/11/17.
5. Ibid.
6. ‘Blossoming green-bond market growing toward $250 billion year’. Bloom Berg Intelligence. 08/04/19.
7. ‘About the Sustainable Development Goals’.
8. ‘The Sustainable Development Agenda’.
9. ‘Financing for the SDGs: Breaking the Bottlenecks of Investment from Policy to Impact’. UNHQ. 11/06/18. p1.
10. Ibid.
  ]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  18
 Active investing – passive pricing
 Mark Parry | Director | Head of Distribution Partners | BMO
Launched in late 2017, the BMO Universal MAP Range brought something new to the funds marketplace – a suite of actively managed risk-targeted options that, with an Ongoing Charge Figure capped at 29 basis points, come at a price usually associated with passive investing.
In many ways, today’s investors find themselves in an enviable position compared with that of their predecessors. There is greater choice in terms of asset types, product providers and individual funds. Investing is easier thanks to technology, meaning you can select, monitor and
adjust your portfolio, often instantly. It’s
also increasingly cost-effective, with a real downward trend in the prices associated with investment. The latter is important as lower costs means less of a drag on returns and greater scope for achieving the outcomes investors are looking for.
Nonetheless, it remains the case that the value of investments can go down as well as up and investors may not get back the original amount invested.
Proven principles
Despite these changes, many of the principles associated with sensible investing are as applicable today as they have been in the past.
✓ Diversification – spreading your portfolio across a range of investments
✓ Long-term thinking – riding out shorter- term challenges and fluctuations
✓ Consider valuation – remembering that the price you pay for an asset is a key determinant of its long-term potential.
The push to passive
It’s unsurprising, therefore, that many of today’s more popular investment options emphasise the benefits of diversification etc alongside the obvious advantages of lower costs. The latter has seen passive strategies proliferate, with individuals now able to access portfolios investing across a host of asset classes in a cost-effective manner through products like Exchange Traded Funds.
Active benefits
Whilst great news from a price perspective, those choosing to allocate to passively managed strategies are, by default, forgoing the potential benefits associated with active
management. The advantages of active investing are multi-faceted in nature.
• Asset allocation – making active adjustments to a portfolio’s overall asset mix to reflect economic and market conditions. For example, if the economy
is growing, a greater emphasis on equities may be sensible, whereas in more challenging conditions it may be prudent to favour the more resilient characteristics of fixed income. Exposure to individual countries can also be adjusted to reflect geographic differentials between regions and countries.
• Tactical moves – alongside strategic asset allocation, it does make sense to think tactically too – taking advantage of more time sensitive opportunities and navigating near-term risks. Markets can move fast so a tactical overlay has scope to add real value.
• Stock picking – the way components – such as individual equities or bonds – are selected can have a big impact as the
 ]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ difference between the winners and losers can be stark. In January 2018 for example, Carillion plc became the largest ever trading liquidation in the UK – bad news for its employees, customers and shareholders. If outperformance is the desired outcome, then doesn’t it make sense to invest on the basis of detailed company analysis rather than passively mirroring the composition of a stock market index?
• Risk management – any investment involves a degree of risk, so assessing
and managing this is a big part of any active strategy. A market may be looking expensive, for example, so taking steps to protect the portfolio may be prudent.
BMO Universal MAP funds –
an active solution at a passive price point
It’s with these factors in mind that we developed the BMO Universal MAP Range, launching the funds in late 2017. We recognised the desire for a well-diversified portfolio building block at an attractive price but felt that cost considerations were leading individuals down a wholly passive route, which in turn meant forgoing the potential benefits of active management.
The range is built on firm foundations – we’ve been managing multi-asset portfolios for many years and used a proven multi-asset platform together with our other specialist capabilities to deliver a suite of actively managed funds at a price point typically associated with passive funds. For investors seeking attractive long-term returns and an investment aligned with their attitude to risk, the BMO Universal MAP funds offered a new and unique option.
A good start
It’s worth noting that 2018 was an eventful and challenging year for markets and the team managed to add value through strategic asset allocation, tactical adjustments and bottom- up stock selection. Although the funds are little over a year old, we are pleased with how they have performed so far relative to their peers (the IA Volatility Managed).
Teamwork – the BMO Universal MAP funds are managed by the BMO Multi-Asset team. Based in London, Chicago and Toronto, the 20+ strong team manages over £30bn for institutions and individuals. As well as their own experience (an average of 21 years in the industry), the team draw on insights and expertise from across our other specialist capabilities.
8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0
-1 -2 -3 -4 -5 -6 -7
31/01/2018
30/04/2018
31/07/2018
31/10/2018
31/01/2019
BMO Universal MAP funds performance vs IA Volatility Managed
BMO Universal MAP Balanced C Acc BMO Universal MAP Growth C Acc
BMO Universal MAP Cautious C Acc IA Volatility Managed NR
Past performance should not be seen as an indicator of future performance.
BMA Universal MAP Funds: performance in context
Performance against key indices and the IA Managed Volatility sector for comparative purposes
BMO Universal Growth C Acc
BMO Universal Balanced C Acc
BMO Universal Cautious C Acc
FTSE All World FTSE All Share
MAP MAP MAP
Rank
Out of 115 funds
1 2
3
- -
Since inception
5.29% 4.52%
3.79%
2.59% -1.37%
Rank 2018 2017
Out of 115 funds
1 -0.49% - 2 -0.67% -
3 -0.85% -
- -3.44% - - -9.47% -
2016 2015 2014
- - - - - -
- - -
- - - - - -
Source: LIM, net of fees in sterling as at 31.01.2019. Past performance should not be seen as an indicator of future performance.
About BMO Global Asset Management
We’re a worldwide asset manager with over 20 offices in 14 countries. We are part of the BMO Financial Group that, with over 900 branches across Canada, is a household name. Having officially started doing business in November 1817, BMO was Canada’s first bank and its pioneering status is reflected in its official Canadian bank number, 001. In the 200+ years following its creation, BMO has grown to service the needs of over twelve million customers worldwide.
Did you know? BMO paid its first dividend in 1829 and hasn’t missed a payment since. At 190 years, this is the longest-running dividend payout for any Canadian company and means that cash has been returned to shareholders through major crises including World War I, the Great Depression, World War II and the 2008 financial crisis.
Views and opinions have been arrived at by BMO Global Asset Management and should not be considered to be a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell any products that may be mentioned.
19
% Growth,TR Def,ExD,Def,GBP
]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  20
 Humans and investing
 David Norman | CEO | TCF Investment and MAPS
When it comes to investing, customers are not always as rational as they think they are and often reduce their returns by poor investment behaviour. The recent market volatility may exacerbate these issues and lead to investors suffering far worse outcomes than they should. Advisers have an important and valuable role in helping their customers avoid or mitigate these issues.
The behaviour gap
Much of economic theory is based on the belief that individuals behave in a rational manner and that all existing information is included in their investment process.
Researchers continue to provide evidence that rational behaviour is often lacking. The study of behavioural finance attempts to understand and explain how human emotions influence investors in their decision-making process.
While there is a debate about how best to measure the gap between the return we should achieve and that which our poor behaviour delivers, there is little doubt about whether it exists and what causes it. Estimates put the behaviour gap between just over 1% and over 4% (though there
is dispute at the efficacy of the latter’s methodology), see chart1.
Figure 1 - Estimates of the behaviour gap
 Source: Betterment
 ]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 21
  So how irrational are we?
Here is a quick summary of some of the behavioural theories and their impacts.
A. Regret theory
Regret theory deals with the emotion people experience after realising they’ve made an error in judgment. Faced with the prospect of selling a fund, investors become affected by the price at which they purchased the fund. They avoid selling it to avoid the regret of having made a bad investment, as well as the embarrassment of reporting a loss.
Regret theory can also impact investors when a fund that they had considered buying has increased in value – the feeling of having missedout.
B. Mental accounting
Humans tend to place events into ‘compartments’ and the difference between these compartments sometimes impacts our behaviour more than the events themselves e.g. the hesitation to sell an investment that once had large gains and now only has a small gain.
C. Prospect/loss-aversion theory
Prospect theory suggests people express
a different degree of emotion towards gains than towards losses. Individuals are more distressed by prospective losses than they are happy from the same size gain – advisers don’t get calls when portfolios rise by £100,000 but they do when they fall by £100,000!
Prospect theory also explains why investors hold onto losing funds: they often take more risks to avoid losses than to realise gains. Gamblers on a losing streak will behave in
a similar fashion, doubling up bets to try to capture what’s already been lost.
D. Anchoring
In the absence of better or new information, investors often assume that the market price is correct. People tend to place too much credence in recent market views, opinions and events, and mistakenly extrapolate
recent trends that differ from historical, long- term averages and probabilities.
E. Overreacting
Investors become very optimistic when the market goes up, assuming it will continue
to do so. Conversely, investors become overly pessimistic during downturns. A consequence of anchoring or placing too much importance on recent events, while ignoring longer term data, is an over- or under-reaction to markets. So, we see prices falling too much on bad news and rising too much on good news.
F. Overconfidence
People generally rate themselves as being above average in their abilities (apparently 90%ofusbelievethatwearebetterthan average drivers!). They also overestimate
the precision of their knowledge and their knowledge relative to others. Overconfidence results in excess trades, with trading costs eroding performance.
G. Reaching for yield
Since the global financial crisis, interest rates have been at historic lows and there is growing evidence that these low interest rates increase investors’ appetite for risk taking, a phenomenon referred to as “reaching for yield”.
What can advisers do to help?
The key role of the financial planner/fiduciary is to be aware of these issues and to help coach investors (and themselves!) through these issues. And to employ strategies to assist.
1. Setlongtermgoals–usecashflow models to help and show clients what a 20% fall looks like in £s terms. Make it real for them so when it happens, they are ready.
2. Keepaneyeoncosts-Morningstar found that the best predictor of fund performance is fees, simply because paying too much directly erodes your performance and directly contributes to the behaviour gap. It’s wholly possible for
an uneducated investor to overpay by 1% or more for a product and another 1% for their platform.
3. Tradeinfrequently(andcosteffectively) – use pre-funding and free switching on platforms to rebalance. Analysis in each of 19 countries has shown that performance decreases with increased account activity. “It is worth paying
an adviser to make sure you don’t do
things!”
4. Diversify-acarefullytargetedportfolio
enables customers to reap the benefits of an “optimised” portfolio designed
to meet their long-term needs with an appropriate capacity for loss, without the need for regular expansive intervention.
5. Beawareofclientbiases-aclientwho has experienced five years of 10% annual returns is likely to expect that going forward, when the reality is likely far less appealing than that.
6. Finally, despite every effort at inoculating clients against bad behaviour, it’s inevitable that some are going to panic in volatile times, which is where your just-in-time reassurance, support and advice come in.
The future
The way we are wired as humans has ensured our survival as a species over tens of thousands of years, but it turns out to be a considerable hindrance in our ability to run investment portfolios effectively. There is a clear and valuable role for advisers to help customers close the behaviour gap and flourish - perhaps that’s why we are seeing
a rise in robo-advisers - if humans are poor when it comes to investing we should let the robots take over?
For more information please drop me a line. David A Norman aka DAN david.norman@tcfinvestment.com
]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  22
Give your CIP a Prod!
 Jon Lycett | Business Development Manager | RSMR
Long ago when I first joined the financial services industry, the acronym ‘CIP’ didn’t exist and nor did the process to which it refers. It’s probably unfair to use the oft quoted ‘pin sticking’ analogy, but there was certainly a culture where research was largely limited to a flick through the life and pensions supplement of a particular trade publication.
Thankfully, most would agree that we’re
in a much better place now. Post-RDR, the majority of firms have adopted some form
of standardised process for matching clients with a suitable product or service – helped in large part by the increased use of back office systems, risk profiling software and platforms.
But just as many firms were settling down into the broad use of a CIP, along came MiFiD II (which caused much consternation throughout 2018) and Prod. Worryingly, studies show that over half of UK advisers are unaware of the full implications of Prod. We will return to the impact of Prod in future articles but for now it does seem like a good time to set out some basic best practice principles on how to build and monitor a centralised investment proposition.
The primary benefit of a well-designed CIP
is that it creates a consistent and repeatable approach, which should produce better outcomes for investors. It should also enable a firm to operate more efficiently – with more time dedicated to offering clients the level of service that demonstrates value for money. It
goes without saying that if the CIP is operated robustly and is well documented, then the regulatory risk to a business is significantly reduced.
So where do you start? The first questions would usually relate to the philosophy that a firm adopts and the tools that it uses. This should be documented to form the basis
of a client service proposition. Common questions are;
• Am I independent or restricted?
• How do I consider risk and discuss
capacity for loss?
• What is my approach to asset allocation? • What type of clients do I deal with?
And how do I segment them into
defined categories?
• How do I research and select solutions
to match the requirements of each client segment?
Having a structured advice process, containing several stages that are each underpinned by a robust methodology, will set your firm apart from the competition and help you to target
the type of clients who see the value in the services that you offer.
This is the bread and butter for advisers. Increasingly, many are introducing lifestyle and life planning questionnaires into the process along with cash-flow modelling software tools, seeking to respond to the increasing sophisticated client needs and to differentiate their service from the competition.
Attitude to risk
Advisers use a variety of tools to determine
a client’s attitude to risk and increasingly these involve more scientific approaches such as psychometric testing and questioning techniques, but there is no substitute for
a good old fashioned discussion with your client where you can probe and challenge their attitude to risk and their understanding of the impact of market volatility on their investments. This area is fundamental to establish client understanding, another part of TCF, and needless to say this must all be recorded on the client file.
  ]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 23
  Robust research & analysis | Documented methodology | Due diligence | Full audit trail
 Jon focuses on key relationships with RSMR’s existing and new advisory client firms. He joined RSMR from Macmillan Cancer Support, where he led in the development of a unique financial guidance service tailored to the needs of cancer patients and their families.
Before this, Jon spent many years with HSBC Global Asset Management.
He brings a wealth of relationship management experience – having worked with advisers, wealth managers and DFMs. He travelled internationally in his role at HSBC, but some years ago made the decision to return to Yorkshire to be closer to his family. Jon lives locally with his partner and young son and outside of work he enjoys family life, rugby league and real ale.
 The investment advice process
     Discovery meeting, risk & capacity for loss
Asset allocation
Fund selection & portfolio building
Monitoring & quarterly reporting
Ongoing client service & review
 Asset allocation
screen allows a more detailed look at how the fund actually operates.
By combining both quantitative and qualitative research you build up a thorough understanding of the fund and how it works in different investment conditions, and this can then be fed through into any selection for portfolio building.
Monitor and review
Not least to ensure you can justify the payment of ongoing remuneration, you need to have a formal process for monitoring the underlying funds which form part of your recommendations made to clients and for reviewing performance and any required rebalancing.
Platforms
Once your investment strategy and process have been agreed, selecting a platform will be easier and some solutions will probably be capable of being eliminated because of the approach you want to take.
Conclusion
By spending time reviewing your investment strategy you will provide focus in delivering a world class client service that will allow you to continue the journey towards delivering improved levels of advice and building trust with your clients.
Many books have been written on the subject of asset allocation and the impact
– both positive and negative – on long term investment performance. In setting asset allocation it is necessary to do this at a strategic level, based on the client’s appetite for risk over the longer term, meeting the client’s expectations as determined by the risk profiling exercise. Some form of tactical overlay may then be considered to respond to shorter term shifts and trends in the market, but the strategic position should remain the starting point.
Fund selection/portfolio construction
This is an equally important stage of your investment advice process and you should ensure you choose funds based on a combination of quantitative and qualitative factors. The quantitative measures centre on performance and risk with a number of measures used in each area to provide a comprehensive picture.
The qualitative assessment of any fund is to assess how the fund will perform in the future. The purpose of this part of the analysis is
to ensure that the fund has robust fund management processes in place and a strong fund management team, and the qualitative
This is one in a series of articles around CIPs and PROD.
Contact us for more details at enquiries@rsmgroup.co.uk or register onto the RSMR Hub at www.rsmr.co.uk
©RSMR 2019. RSMR is a registered Trademark.
 ]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  24
  Five good reasons
 JacquiGillies|HeadofMarketing |Guardian
We’re a woefully underinsured nation. We know that. And there are lots of reasons why people are reluctant to buy the protection they need. In our industry, we’ve talked for years about how to combat the common objections – ‘it’s too expensive’, ‘I don’t need it’, ‘the State will provide’ and all the other excuses people come out with. But in concentrating on the obvious objections, have we possibly missed the most fundamental?
We know customers find protection products too complicated to understand and, more importantly, they don’t trust us to pay out when they claim on their policy.
Of course, the reality is that as an industry we do pay claims. In fact, we do everything we can to make sure we do. But still customers don’t believe it. Even sharing our claim statistics isn’t helping. At Guardian we believe the way to really shift customer perception is to change the way protection policies are designed.
Complexity creates doubt in people’s minds. Removing complexity from protection products, making it simpler for customers
to engage with their policies as their needs develop over time and should they ever need to claim, is the key to improving customer perceptions.
Here are just five examples of how protection proposition design can help
you create more meaningful long-term relationships with your clients, giving them reasons to return to you for advice.
1. Our clear critical illness definitions give your clients certainty
We’ve used language that’s easy for you to explain and for your clients to understand. This way, your clients will be clear about what they’re buying so that when they come to make a claim, they won’t need to worry about not meeting the definition. And we won’t need to disappoint them because they’ve not had a ‘serious enough’ heart attack for example.
 Payout Planner allows your clients to nominate up to nine beneficiaries easily when they apply – and update them anytime. This means any payout is excluded from their estate, so it bypasses probate and goes straight to loved ones without delay.
 ]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 25
  Complexity creates doubt in people’s minds. Removing complexity from protection products, making it simpler for customers to engage with their policies as their needs develop over time and should they ever need to claim, is the key to improving customer perceptions.
But we’ve not just made the wording in our definitions as simple as we can – for as many conditions as possible, we only need confirmation from a UK Consultant rather than asking for detailed medical evidence. They’re the experts, after all.
2. Payout Planner means no more probate delays
Probate can delay a payout from reaching the family when they need it most. Placing policies in trust is one way to avoid this of course, but trusts are complex and time- consuming to set up.
Payout Planner allows your clients to nominate up to nine beneficiaries easily when they apply – and update them anytime. This means any payout is excluded from their estate, so it bypasses probate and goes straight to loved ones without delay.
3. Reserved Cover makes increasing or adding new cover effortless
Setting up home is expensive, which
means the price of protection is a barrier
for many people when you add it to the
cost of moving and the monthly mortgage repayments. Because of this, most people protect their mortgage with life cover alone, so they have no protection against the bigger risk of critical illness.
However, we automatically reserve cover for your clients, when we can, above and beyond what you ask for. This makes it easy for
your clients to get the protection they can afford today, and increase it tomorrow when they’re better able to afford it.
Using this reserved cover, you can increase their Life Protection or add – or increase – Critical Illness Protection anytime within the first 27 months, on the same terms, just by answering a few simple questions.
4. We include Premium Waiver at no extra cost, for everyone
Waiver of premium is usually an optional add-on which means if your clients don’t take it, they could quickly find their premiums become a burden when they can least afford them.
However, with us, Premium Waiver comes as standard – at no extra cost – regardless of age, occupation or activities. So, if we offer someone cover they automatically get waiver. And we not only waive premiums if they’re too ill to work, we also waive them for up to 6 months after they have a baby or if they lose their job.
5. Our dual life option keeps policies separate so couples are better protected
Usually, if a couple applies for cover together and one claims, the other is left uninsured.
Our dual life cover, on the other hand, gives both of them their own individual cover, at a discount. This means that if one claims, the other is still covered. And if their relationship ends, their cover doesn’t because their policies are separate.
We only offer dual life because we don’t believe joint life policies are fair.
These are just five good reasons to consider our cover. But there are plenty more, because we’re always looking for a better way.
The Guardian proposition is live on the Synaptic Product & Fund Research tool. And you can quote and apply using Synaptic Webline Protection.
Discover more about Guardian’s proposition and register to do business at www.guardian1821.co.uk/advisers
 ]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  26
 Look a little closer
 Mark Cracknell | Head of Protection Distribution | Aviva
Most protection policies look pretty similar on the surface these days. Prices are all in the same ballpark, give or take a few pounds. And
the vast majority of claims – 97.8% in 2017, in fact – are paid out without problems.
So, with all else being relatively equal, it’s the things beyond these factors which can help determine which policy is going to be the best fit for your client and their loved ones.
For instance, is it a brand you and your client trust? How quickly and smoothly can you get the business written? How comprehensive
is the cover? And – importantly – are there any extras that could give your client further reassurance and support?
Dig for treasure
Several providers now offer a package of extras bundled with their protection policies. And some of the biggest differences between policies can be uncovered if you look at which specific extras are actually included with them.
At Aviva, for example, our protection policies now give your clients – and their families, in some cases – access to up to eight separate support services, at no extra cost.
Many of you will be familiar with some of them. For instance, the fact that we give policyholders access to an expert second medical opinion through Best Doctors. Or that clients (and their loved ones) can access the Bupa Anytime Healthline to speak to a qualified nurse, 24/7.
But you might not know we also give 25% off gym memberships at health clubs throughout the UK (terms and conditions apply). That we offer Income Protection+ clients access to private physio treatment. Or that we provide rapid access to mental health counselling, meaning people don’t have to wait months before receiving treatment.
What clients say
When set against the large lump sums that protection policies pay out, these added extras may seem small. But from speaking to customers and advisers, we know first-hand how important they can prove to clients when it really matters.
Customers like Adam Hyde, for instance.
A former ambulance worker, he received psychotherapy – organised by Aviva – when he was signed off work with stress and anxiety.
Adam said he was in “a really bad place” when he first called Aviva. But thanks to the support he received, he was able to get back to work in a new job, with a new, more positive frame of mind.
With support through the state proving more and more difficult to come by these days, the extras that come bundled with some protection policies are proving increasingly important. They can also make your protection conversations that little bit easier.
If you’d like a closer look at the support services that come with our protection policies, speak to your usual Aviva consultant or visit aviva-for-advisers.co.uk today.
 ]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 27
   Is it true that insurers try not to pay out on claims?
That’s the perception many people have of insurers – that we’re quick to take money, but not so quick to pay it out.
Yet last year, we paid out more than 97%
of the protection claims we received, supporting over 25,000 customers and their families.
Lack of trust is a major reason people don’t take out financial protection
65% of UK adults don’t have any form of protection*. People don’t look at protecting their loved ones in the same way as they do protecting their house, car or even their pet. And what’s one of the main reasons for not taking out financial protection? Not trusting insurers to pay out on a claim.
So why is that? We’ve been trying to find out.
Perception versus reality
For our 2018 protection claims report, we spoke to several customers who claimed in 2017.
Before claiming, a number of them thought they would need to go through a rigorous process to get their money. And they were pleasantly surprised to find that wasn’t the case.
We’re proud of our claims record. Settling over 97% of all claims and paying out £900 million to our customers is what we’re here for. It’s our reason for being.
Contrary to popular opinion, we actively look for reasons to pay out – the complete opposite of public perception.
We see how these pay-outs make such a difference to customers which makes it even more frustrating that negative perceptions stop people from getting the cover they might so desperately need in future.
It’s time to change the way people think
Publishing our report is just one way we’ll do this.
Every year, there are a small number of cases where we don’t pay out, but, in our report, we clearly outline the reasons why. We
also tell some of our customers’ stories to help break open the myth that we make it as difficult as possible for people to get the money they’re due.
Read Aviva’s 2018 protection claims report https://www.aviva.co.uk/adviser/ documents/view/pt15836c.pdf
Hear from Aviva’s customers
http://www.aviva-for-advisers.co.uk/ adviser/site/public/products/protection/ protection-claims
* Understanding the financial lives of UK adults, Findings from the FCA’s Financial Lives Survey 2017
 Last year, we paid out over 97% of the protection claims we received
 ]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  28
  Choice
 Ian Berrett | Protection Marketing Manager | Old Mutual Wealth
“As much money and life as you could want! The two things most
human beings would choose above all – the trouble is, humans do have
a knack of choosing precisely those things that are worst for them.” J K. Rowling, Harry Potter and the Sorcerer’s Stone
I’m not really a fan of Harry Potter, but this quote does appeal to me. It can be applied to the simplest of day-to-day choices and to decisions with much greater, life-changing consequences.
In the critical illness market the opportunity for choice has grown substantially over the last few years, both in terms of providers and, probably more so, the choices a single product can present. This often includes the choice of cover for a core group of illnesses and conditions or an upgrade to include an additional list of conditions. Similar choices can be made for children’s cover.
I don’t think choice is a bad thing, but choosing a critical illness policy isn’t easy. There are ever-increasing lists of unfamiliar illnesses to navigate. Choosing whether to include all of these or leave some out, and whether you include children’s cover or not, maybe what level of children’s cover; it’s a lot to consider.
We have a slightly different approach. We don’t want you to be faced with a decision of what to choose, or perhaps more crucially, what to leave out. It would be a terrible situation if a client became ill only to find that they cannot claim because their illness is covered by the upgraded cover they chose not to include.
This is why the full cover that we offer is the only cover that we offer.
Numbers aren’t everything
We provide full payment for a wide ranging 50 illnesses and conditions, plus additional payments for a further 28 conditions. But numbers aren’t everything. What’s important to us is providing quality cover and that starts with comprehensive cover for the most claimed for conditions.
This includes a cancer definition that goes beyond ABI standard, plus cover for a range of less severe cancers and any cancer in situ
that requires surgery – no matter where it is in the body.
We pay out for any heart attack, whatever the severity. There are a further 13 cardiovascular conditions covered including cardiac arrest and treatment with a pacemaker.
For strokes, including spinal, the effects only have to last 24 hours for us to pay out. ‘Eye stroke’ is also covered.
These are just three examples and cover extends across neurological conditions, serious accidents and mental illness.
Support for long term illness
For some of these conditions it’s possible to make a full recovery and return to everyday life, but for some the effects can last far longer. That’s why we include Additional Care Benefit. This additional payment, of up to £50,000, pays when a critical illness leaves
 ]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 29
  In the critical illness market the opportunity for choice has grown substantially over the last few years, both in terms of providers and, probably more so, the choices a single product can present. This often includes the choice of cover for a core group of illnesses and conditions or an upgrade to include an additional list of conditions.
the life assured with severe and permanent physical or mental symptoms.
In some cases the benefit can be paid at the same time as the claim, in others, where symptoms of the condition become progressively worse, a claim for the additional support can be made up to two years after the initial claim.
Speeding up surgery
I’ve been lucky with my experiences of the NHS, but we all know that for some surgeries waiting lists can be lengthy.
A number of the conditions require surgery, and for 11 of these we can pay the cover before the surgery takes places, giving the option of private treatment rather than waiting.
Comprehensive cover for children
Probably one of the greatest worries for
a parent is that their child may become seriously ill. At such a stressful time, the last thing you need is financial difficulty. While our cover will never stop the worry, it can help to ease any financial burden.
We cover any number of children from birth to their 22nd birthday and children born after the cover has started will automatically be included - without having to tell us.
They’re covered for the same 50 full payments as adults, a further eight child specific illnesses and 27 of the additional payments.
Payments don’t reduce the main cover and can be doubled if both parents are covered by the policy or each have a separate policy.
Overseas treatment
Naturally we want the best care for our children, but sometimes treatment isn’t available in the UK. If treatment is only available outside of the UK, we will double the payment.
That means if both parents are covered we could pay up to a total maximum of £100,000 in total.
Children’s cover also includes surgery benefit, an additional £10,000 for an advanced illness and £5,000 life cover.
When is a child not a child?
So what happens when they reach 22? They’ll always be ‘children’ to their parents but not by the definitions of our policy.
They may have their own income, and bills to pay which is why we include First Time Cover.
It gives the child no longer covered the opportunity to apply for their own, full adult cover, of up to £50,000 if both parents are covered, without any health questions.
There for you
When we talk about comprehensive we mean more than helping to relieve the financial difficulties.
Our There for You service can provide the kind of emotional and practical support that a client may not get as part of their treatment by connecting them with a RedArc nurse adviser.
Available at any time, without having to claim, and at no extra cost, the service provides second medical opinions, counselling and therapies, care advice, and so much more – enough for another article!
Importantly, the one-on-one support with the same nurse adviser is available to the client and their family for as long as it’s required.
And so, back to choice. A policy that
offers many choices or a policy that offers comprehensive cover as standard? I guess it’s just another choice to throw into the mix.
We’ve put together a short video infographic to help you explain to your client, in less than two minutes, what we include as standard
in our critical illness cover. Visit www.bitly. com/OMWCI-video to view the video.
Our protection specialists are here to support you. Visit www.bitly.com/OMWCI-contact to get in touch.
 ]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[         30
                          Money doesn’t grow on trees... but the best things in life are free, aren’t they Dad?
  Paul Quarendon | New Product Development Manager | Synaptic Software Limited
I really wish I had a pound for each time I’ve uttered those first five words.
It’s been some time now since financial education was introduced into England’s secondary schools, and it has been cited that school leavers now have better money management skills than many adults*, so surely this bodes well for the UK in years to come?
I’m not sure. Although London has been ranked the world’s capital for global
financial services, it does however rank disappointingly below average for its teaching of financial literacy. Surprised? I was, so I thought I would take it upon myself to survey the offspring of my colleagues and ask parents how they think children should be educated in the ways of finance and their long-term financial security.
Before we delve into the feedback, whose job is it to educate our children on financial matters; just parents, or school as well, or only society in general, when perhaps it’ll be too late? In my opinion, it’s all three, with our children needing good role models to follow so they can apply what they have learned when going into our wider society.
Back to the survey, and the cross-section of children and parents quizzed were asked
about matters ranging from, “What is income protection?” to “Do they have targets when saving?” Is it fair to say that I didn’t expect them to know too much, if anything, about insurance, as anything they have learned already at school or from parents would be around saving, but nonetheless, the answers made for some revealing and interesting reading, and aren’t short of talking points!
I started off by asking “What do you think ‘protection’ means in a financial context?” None of the respondents were expected
to speak ‘financia-lese’, so other than the predictable “no” responses, which was a fair answer for ages ranging from 10 – 21, those responses returned, whether right or wrong, made complete sense – “the protection of one’s money,” and, “protecting financial information.” It’s great that GDPR seems to have possibly crept into their psyche, perhaps also not a surprise the word ‘insurance’ didn’t feature in any replies, however, by extending the question to, “what do you need to protect, if you take a mortgage or rent a house?”, answers seemed more thought through, varying between, “protecting the money you pay for rent or a mortgage”, to “home/legal insurance and life insurance”, to
“need to protect any debt, and your money, yes, you need to protect the salary that you earn each month”.
Then came the trickier questions like “what does income protection do?”, and “What is term assurance?” Perhaps, based on these answers, albeit a small sample size, as an industry we do need to rethink the naming convention of our products. I’ll start with term assurance. “No idea”, was the most common riposte.
In fact, there was only one answer other than that, which was “future planning – like putting money away for a holiday”. Now I’m not saying we need to change it on the back of one reply from a 21-year-old, but it has been a while since you would have surely had to explain a term like this:
Term Life Assurance is a policy that provides coverage at a fixed rate of payments for a limited period, the relevant term. After that period expires, coverage at the previous rate of premiums is no longer guaranteed and the client must either forgo coverage or potentially obtain further coverage with different payments or conditions. If the
life insured dies during the term, the death
Source: Independent
 ]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[     31
                              Have I got a solution for all IFAs? No, I don’t think so yet, but I would strongly urge you to think about talking to your clients, who have children, and asking them to talk to their children about all matters financial, in whatever level of detail.
benefit will be paid to the beneficiary. Term insurance is typically the least expensive way to purchase a substantial death benefit on a coverage amount over a specific period.
Thanks to Wikipedia for that clarity, but surely one could just say it is life insurance that pays out if you die during the term of the policy? You then tag on the essential trust discussion, but can’t we look to move towards product names that mean something to us all, ones that evolve as different generations grow up and take the protection they will need, especially in this world dictated by money and spending?
We all know income protection is a different beast. Let those surveyed tell you why.
It can mean literally anything to anyone, whether you work in financial services or not. Apparently, IP is a “security tool to stop people stealing your money online or by hacking”, or it’s “when an insurance man knocks on your door and demands protection money”. Man from the Pru, you have so much to answer to!
We did get closer to the right answer though. To one teenager it is “when you have income from a job you put some into a protection scheme in case something happens to you.” A good start, however I am told the discussion
quickly descended into dying your hair
and moving home like you’re in a witness protection scheme! Others did however, and it was the younger children who grasped the fact that IP “protects the income you get, income being what you earn from work and this would be something that would pay you if your work didn’t”, and, “protects your income”!
The saving grace though could be saving. Something this bunch of Alphas and Generation Zs take very seriously - well almost. There are some caveats. One 13-year-old saves “for an expensive item but if something else comes along that I also want,
I get my parents to buy one of them for me”, but overall, saving and budgeting were high on everyone’s agenda, although marrying a millionaire still got a look in.
So, what’s the answer from this snapshot? Some funny anecdotes, but in the main each young person canvassed expressed the same overarching approach to finances, in that they will take it very seriously in the future, once and if the bank of mum and dad ever closes its doors for a final time!
What about the parents then? A couple of highlights stand out. The first being, “Hmm, don’t really talk about the detail very much but they do know our property is our main
investment for now, that money is being
set aside for a uni fund, if required, and that we have policies in place if the worst were
to happen. It’s the sort of thing that I never spoke about with my parents and in hindsight I seemed to have passed that down”.
Another was, “We do try to talk about finances with them occasionally and we have a few things in place to help support their future. In terms of educating them about finances, we dabbled with the Go Henry card to get them used to managing money and thinking about saving, but we stopped it as the novelty soon wore off and the monthly subscription of £3 became more than the amount being earned for doing tasks around the house”!
Have I got a solution for all IFAs? No, I don’t think so yet, but I would strongly urge you to think about talking to your clients, who have children, and asking them to talk to their children about all matters financial,
in whatever level of detail. I’d also love to hear how you explain insurance products
to your customers and maybe we can get
an aide memoire produced to help advisers, customers, and possibly educators. Perhaps encouraging youngsters to get involved in local Young Enterprise schemes is one answer.
 ]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 32
 Financial Education
                                      The amount boys at school now think they will be earning when they reach 30 years old. Girls think they will earn £42,850.
Well above the national average of £30,400 and £27,500 respectively.
The percentage of children between 7-17 not receiving any financial education at school, home, or another setting in 2018.
LESS THAN HALF
£1.78 trillion
The amount in £ of debt currently in the UK.
As of the first quarter of 2018, UK debt amounted to £1.78 trillion, or 86.58% of total GDP, at which time the annual cost of paying interest the public debt amounted to around £48 billion.
18-24
Debt amoung 18-24 year olds has risen 104% since 1992.
This age group spends almost 30% of its income on debt repayments
TEN 1/3
£54K
           Only 40% of UK schools are teaching financial literacy as part of their curriculum
   31% of students are covering university tuition fees by credit cards and payday loans
The age at which children can purchase items online
       The age a child can open their own current account but still needing a parent’s permission. You must be 18 to get a credit card or a loan.
TWO THIRDS
The proportion of children whose parents open their bank account for them
]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                    The Suitability Suite
Risk. Costs. Due diligence. Best advice
Proof of suitability is easier with Synaptic Research
 • The regulator is making proof of suitability the cornerstone of its enforcement policy
• Synaptic provides proof of suitability in the key areas of product features, risk and costs
         Synaptic Product and Fund Whole of market product and fund research, full suitability reporting
                       Synaptic Comparator
Detailed price analysis for platforms, products and funds including R.I.Y. calculations
                                                  RISK
Synaptic Risk A.T.R.Q. and Risk Rated funds and portfolios
            Synaptic Modeller
Models investment outcomes for new and existing holdings. Manage and assess investment risk
                                        SYNAPTIC
WEBLINE
Synaptic Webline
Protection and annuity quotes and on-line applications (including enhanced annuities)
                 Synaptic Analyser Retirement income analysis and drawdown product comparison.
                              Synaptic Suitability offer: £175 per licence, per month (excl. VAT) - rrp £309
Apply today, call us on 0800 783 4477 or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk quoting ‘Suitability Offer’.
  SAVE OVER
£130 PER LICENCE
]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[         34
                       Risk-taking?
A ‘rational process’ since 1654
 Eric Armstrong | Client Director | Synaptic Software Limited
In his book Against the Gods, Peter L. Bernstein proposes that the success of human ingenuity in modern times is as a result of the mastery of risk.
The mix of science and art practiced by financial planners is an advanced form of what has driven intellectual development from
the explosion of technological, cultural and societal progress in the 17th century during the Enlightenment: ‘The revolutionary idea that defines the boundary between modern times and the past is the mastery of risk’.
By defining a ‘rational process of risk-
taking’ the true nature of modern progress was revealed. In Bernstein’s words, ‘Risk management guides us over a vast range of decision-making, from allocating wealth to safe-guarding public health, from waging war to planning a family, from paying insurance premiums to wearing a seatbelt, from planting corn to marketing cornflakes’.
An understanding of risk evolved through the work of a series of intellectual giants; ‘mathematicians transformed probability theory into a powerful instrument for organising, interpreting, and applying information.’
Modern stochastic techniques can rightfully (in our view) claim to be full expressions of
what has evolved since 1654 when Pascal first introduced the concept of probability
as a means of solving problems. Modern students of investment may be more familiar with Nobel Laureate Harry Markowitz, whose mathematical insights produced Portfolio Theory with its Efficient Frontier and explained the enormous benefits of diversification.
Modern investment strategies also capture another pivotal idea from the 18th century. Swiss mathematician Daniel Bernoulli wrote a paper identifying the concept of ‘utility’ where ‘the value of an item must not be based on its price, but on the utility that
it yields’. Subjectivity is as important part
of decision making and risk assessment as probability. Even though outcomes can be predicted, different people value different outcomes. Investors may or may not be comfortable taking on investment risk, based on subjective considerations, usually relating to their existing financial circumstances or their aspirations to grow wealth. In short, this is the familiar territory of advisers undertaking psychometric questionnaires with clients.
In our industry, there is a growing realisation that forward looking techniques that
seek to describe the universe of ‘viable’ investment outcomes provides a more reliable methodology for managing investment risk than more traditional analysis predicated on historical returns, including historical volatility.
The kind of mathematical analysis referenced above is generated by a stochastic engine comprising rules that describe the behaviour and inter-relation of the constituents of the model (for example interest rates or asset class growth rates), coupled with powerful simulation, creating thousands of viable outcomes.
It is very difficult to predict the outcome of an investment in the short term, but in the longer term, the power of probability kicks in and
we can predict much more accurately. It is a similar explanation as to why a dice may have 1 out of 6 outcomes in a throw, meaning the next throw is impossible to predict. However, throw a dice 10k times and the outcome can be predicted with certainty.
 ]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[     35
                          The real challenge for many advisers is that MiFID II has introduced the concept of ex-ante and ex-post research, meaning that full suitability must be established in advance of a transaction and at every review.
Risk, MiFID II and the advice process
Having a well-structured approach to risk profiling and managing investment risk is no longer optional in the MiFID environment. We have written and posted a ‘white paper’ that is available on the Synaptic website. The purpose of this paper is to provide insight into the mechanics of risk and return, on
the premise that improved management of investment risk with clients can be delivered through an effective, modern investment strategy. In the paper, we cover the following fundamentals:
• Risk profiling of clients The real challenge for many advisers is that
• Building an efficient frontier using MiFID II has introduced the concept of ex-
‘Value at Risk’ measure (rather than ante and ex-post research, meaning that full
volatility) suitability must be established in advance of a
• The role of asset allocation in transaction and at every review.
forming probability-based models for
investment outcomes
• How to measure and compare risk
inherent in investment
• The role of risk in retirement planning
• Longevity of investment and
sustainable withdrawals
Both screens below from Synaptic Modeller show the analysis of a client’s investment on the left, to be compared on the right with the analysis of the Strategic Asset Allocation for the appropriate Risk Category, in this case Balanced (hi end in our 1-10 range, level 6).
  If you have any concerns about your firm’s ability to meet the challenges of MiFID II, risk and proof of Suitability, consider adopting the Synaptic Risk Ratings. You can use the ATRQ, Investment Strategy and Risk Ratings at our cost (free to you!). Call our sales team on 0800 783 4477.
 Material taken from the Synaptic Risk White Paper, downloadable from the Synaptic website www.synaptic.co.uk
 ]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[            36
                         Stochastic modelling in the context of retirement planning
 Eric Armstrong | Client Director | Synaptic Software Limited
Most of us will be familiar now with the starting point for most discussions of this kind – the Bengen 4% rule. This research was a landmark in establishing a new kind of calculation, but Bengen’s research only dealt with US historical returns, and our intention here is to outline how Bengen’s approach might be applied in a UK retirement context today, using modern stochastic techniques.
First of all, the use of cash-flow plans
As readers will know, cash-flow models are prescribed for DB transfers, but in his recent report ’An-ex-regulator’s guide to cash-flow planning’, Rory Percival explains why cash- flow plans should be taking centre stage in a wider context of advice:
• ‘Cash-flow planning can be about any form of income and outgoings and does not have to be related to the client’s overall position.’ A cash-flow plan need not be a holistic view of a client’s finances.
• The second point is that the cash-flow plan can establish a client’s Capacity
for Loss for most clients. In fact, writes the author, ‘it should be the main way of assessing Capacity for Loss for most clients.’ Capacity for Loss is the lynchpin of compliance, and meeting the funding requirement for future income is central
to any plan. An adviser needs to make an expert, objective assessment of Capacity for Loss, or using its FCA definition, identify the level at which loss may make a ‘material impact on the standard of living’.
Moody’s overview of sustainable retirement income
Synaptic users can use growth assumptions from the Synaptic Risk profile, but the calculations remain deterministic. In our
view, retirement advice is most effectively delivered using a combination of cash-flow modelling and stochastic analysis. In the last edition of this publication, we provided graphs illustrating the ‘longevity’ of retirement funds, created by Synaptic Modeller.
Additionally, we wanted to show you one more graph that beautifully captures the role of investment risk, the impact of withdrawals and probability of success.
The graph shows a greater than 80% chance of success (income sustainability over 25 years) for everything:
• With a greater investment risk than -0.1, which is equivalent to a portfolio with Moderately Cautious risk profile (loss of up to 10% of portfolio in a bad (1 in 20) year).
• Drawing down 5% or less of portfolio (adjusted for inflation). The 0-800 are bps i.e. 400 is 4%. Notice also that the classic 4% level of income will return a 90% chance of success if the funds are invested above Moderately Cautious Strategy.
• Summary – investment risk is obligatory for meeting most retirement investment needs!
 ]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 37
  Additionally, we wanted to show you one more graph that beautifully captures the role of investment risk, impact of withdrawal and probability of success.
                                   Moody’s 2-risk chart. Decumulation Strategies
 What’s shown?
• 25-year retirement decumulation projections for portfolios ranging from 0% to 100% equity, for a range of fixed income levels.
• The Strategic Asset Allocations (SAAs) used are a blend of Equity (70% Global
ex UK; 30% UK) and UK Fixed Income. EBR (Equity Backing Ratio, i.e. proportion of equity) is stepped in 5% increments from 0% to 100% - shown on the chart as points.
• For each set of Strategic Asset Allocations, we run a decumulation scenario with fixed income level ranging from 0% to 8% of the initial fund. Lines show constant income levels, as specified in the RH legend: 0bps, 30bps, 70bps, 100bps, 130 bps and so on.
• For reference, the current single life fixed annuity rate is about 5.0% for a 65-year old – shown as a red dashed line.
• On the y axis is income sustainability, i.e. probability of maintaining the stated income to age 90.
• On the x axis is max 1yr 95% var. That is, the maximum 1-year loss at the 1 in 20 level over the investment horizon. This loss reflects losses on the fund due to investment returns only and does not reflect the income cashflows.
What does it mean?
This is a “2-risk” chart showing two of the principle sources of investment risk for decumulation investors: “shortfall risk”, as represented on the y-axis in terms of “income sustainability”, and “market risk” represented on the x axis as the “potential 1yr loss”.
Use of retirement withdrawal statements
Synaptic recommends the use of retirement withdrawal statements to anticipate
the various market conditions. Abraham Okusanya has written a fantastic book, Beyond the 4% Rule, that explains the maths and the various rules that can be applied in more detail than we have room for here.
To make a withdrawal statement work, the adviser should establish the probability-based parameters for success or failure (easy with the Moody’s model), and signpost the likely responses. The latter will include several simple rules that can be applied, for example the expectation of increasing the withdrawal rate by inflation, except when the portfolio has lost 10% over any 12-month period. Inflation-linked increases to be resumed when the portfolio has regained the former valuation. The rules to address different market conditions are also the best way to demonstrate the suitability of the plan, as the
rules will be designed to prevent the depletion of the principal and breach of the client’s Capacity for Loss. Abraham Okusanya’s
book ‘Beyond the 4% Rule’ is a great place to research the various strategies in more detail.
A major concern of course is the cognitive ability of the client (and the adviser!) in later years, so the due diligence and research needs to be very thorough, including a detailed understanding of how the reviews will be undertaken.
There are many interesting considerations that come out of this research, for example, how different asset allocations and investment styles might work; whether the use of natural yield to determine withdrawal rates might help, or what happens when you allow the asset classes to drift, which again provides some interesting results and options for the adviser.
 Article is an extract from the Synaptic Risk White Paper, available to download at www.synaptic.co.uk/risk
]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                            Risk and suitability in a perfect ‘10’
         • Synaptic Modeller provides complete risk and suitability and investment risk management for head offices, paraplanners and advisers, combining Moody’s Analytics investment strategy and stochastic projections
• Accurate and consistent values for downside risk that can be used to align Capacity for Loss with risk in chosen investments
• Includes fully integrated ATR Questionnaire, Asset Allocations and stochastic engine for illustrative projections
• Synaptic Modeller offers key Moody’s probability based risk metrics: the Value at Risk in any given investment scenario and the investment outcome
• Adviser controls inputs for investment amount, term, costs including adviser charges
• Perfectly complements RSMR qualitative research, accessible through Synaptic Product and Fund Fact sheets
• Integrates with Intelliflo via iO Store
                              Synaptic Modeller is now available with 1-10 risk categories as well as 1-5, defined by Moody’s Analytics asset allocations
  Synaptic Modeller is available as a standalone module from £50 per month. Network deals can apply. Can also be deployed as part of the full Synaptic Research Suite.
 For more information call 0800 783 4477 or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk
   ]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                                                            Aegon Conservative Core Portfolio Aegon Cautious Core Portfolio Aegon Balanced Core Portfolio Aegon Balanced Plus Core Portfolio Aegon Growth Core Portfolio Aegon Growth Plus Core Portfolio Aegon Adventurous Core Portfolio
                                                        MA Passive Prudent
MA Passive Reserve
MA Passive Moderate MA Passive Intermediate MA Passive Progressive MA Passive Growth
MA Passive Dynamic
MA Blended Reserve
MA Blended Moderate MA Blended Intermediate MA Blended Progressive MA Blended Growth
MA Active Reserve
MA Active Moderate Income MA Active Intermediate Income MA Active Progressive
MA Active Growth
MA Active Dynamic
                                                                                                                                                                                                    MAF I MAF II MAF III MAF IV MAF V
                 BMO MM Lifestyle 3 Fund
BMO MM Lifestyle 4 Fund
BMO MM Lifestyle 5 Fund
BMO MM Lifestyle 6 Fund
BMO MM Lifestyle 7 Fund
Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling) BMO MM Navigator Distribution Fund BMO MM Navigator Cautious Fund BMO MM Navigator Balanced Fund BMO MM Navigator Growth Fund BMO MM Navigator Boutiques Fund BMO Universal MAP Cautious
BMO Universal MAP Balanced BMO Universal MAP Growth
                                  Newton Multi-Asset Diversified Return Newton Multi-Asset Income
Newton Multi-Asset Balanced Newton Multi-Asset Growth
Newton Global Balanced
Newton Global Dynamic Bond Newton Global Dynamic Bond Income Newton Real Return
              ]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                                           Cautious MPS
Income MPS
Balanced MPS Growth MPS
Global Equity MPS Cautious Passive+ Income Passive+ Balanced Passive+ Growth Passive+ Global Equity Passive+
                                                                                                  MPS Low Risk (Defensive Income)
MPS Low Medium Risk (Income & Growth) MPS Low Medium Risk (Income)
MPS Medium Risk (Income)
MPS Medium Risk (Income & Growth) MPS Medium Risk (Passive)
MPS Medium High Risk
MPS Medium High Risk (Passive)
MPS High Risk (Income & Growth)
MPS High Risk (Growth)
IFSL BM Defensive Income
IFSL BM Cautious Growth
IFSL BM Balanced
IFSL BM Strategic Growth
IFSL BM Defensive Capital
MPS Low Medium Risk (Passive)
                                                                                                                                                                 LF Canlife Portfolio III LF Canlife Portfolio IV LF Canlife Portfolio V LF Canlife Portfolio VI LF Canlife Portfolio VII Canlife Portfolio 3 Canlife Portfolio 4 Canlife Portfolio 5 Canlife Portfolio 6 Canlife Portfolio 7
LF Canlife Managed 0%-35% Canlife Managed 0%-35%
                             Carmignac Portfolio Sécurité
Carmignac Portfolio Patrimoine
Carmignac Portfolio Capital Plus
Carmignac Portfolio Commodities
Carmignac Portfolio Emergents
Carmignac Portfolio Unconstrained Global Bond
Carmignac Portfolio Euro-Entrepreneurs Carmignac Portfolio Capital Cube
Carmignac Portfolio Investissement
Carmignac Portfolio Long-Short European Equities
Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Discovery Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Patrimoine Carmignac Portfolio Grande Europe
                        Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk
]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Cazenove Cautious Portfolio
Cazenove Balanced Portfolio
Cazenove Balanced Income Portfolio
Cazenove Growth Portfolio
Cazenove Aggressive Portfolio
Cazenove Equity Risk Portfolio
Cazenove Cautious Active/Passive Portfolio
Cazenove Balanced Active/Passive Portfolio
Cazenove Growth Active/Passive Portfolio
Cazenove Aggressive Active/Passive Portfolio
Cazenove Equity Risk Active/Passive Portfolio
Close Managed Growth Fund
Close Tactical Select Passive Growth Fund
Close DMS Growth
Close Managed Balanced Fund
Close Tactical Select Passive Balanced Fund
Close DMS Balanced
Close Managed Income Fund
Close Managed Conservative Fund
Close Tactical Select Passive Conservative Fund
Close DMS Income Plus
Close DMS Conservative
Close Bond Income Portfolio Fund Close Growth Portfolio Fund
Close Balanced Portfolio Fund
Close Conservative Portfolio Fund Close Diversified Income Portfolio Fund
Cautious Moderately Cautious
Dynamic Passive 1 Dynamic Passive 2 Dynamic Passive 3 Dynamic Passive 4 Dynamic Passive 5
Multi Manager Income 1 Multi Manager Income 2 Multi Manager Income 3 Multi Manager Income 4 Multi Manager Income 5 Multi Manager Total Return 1 Multi Manager Total Return 2 Multi Manager Total Return 3 Multi Manager Total Return 4 Multi Manager Total Return 5
GS Global Multi Asset Conservative Portfolio
GS Global Multi Asset Balanced Portfolio GS Global Multi Asset Growth Portfolio
Multi Manager
Synaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:
Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation
Balanced Moderately Adventurous Adventurous
Dynamic Passive
]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Defensive Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Cautious Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Balanced Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Growth Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Aggressive Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Distribution Hawksmoor Sustainable World Balanced MI Hawksmoor Vanbrugh
MI Hawksmoor Distribution
MI Hawksmoor Global Opportunities
Invesco Asian Fund (UK)
Invesco Corporate Bond Fund (UK)
Invesco Distribution Fund (UK)
Invesco Global Bond Fund (UK)
Invesco Global Smaller Companies Fund (UK)
Invesco Global Targeted Returns Fund (UK) Invesco High Income Fund (UK)
Invesco High Yield Fund (UK)
Invesco Hong Kong & China Fund (UK) Invesco Income Fund (UK)
Invesco Latin American Fund (UK) Invesco Managed Growth Fund (UK) Invesco Managed Income Fund (UK) Invesco Monthly Income Plus Fund (UK) Invesco Pacific Fund (UK)
Invesco Tactical Bond Fund (UK)
Invesco UK Smaller Companies Equity Fund (UK)
Invesco UK Strategic Income Fund (UK) Invesco Summit Growth 1 Fund (UK)* Invesco Summit Growth 2 Fund (UK)* Invesco Summit Growth 3 Fund (UK)* Invesco Summit Growth 4 Fund (UK)* Invesco Summit Growth 5 Fund (UK)*
HSBC Global Strategy Cautious HSBC Global Strategy Conservative HSBC Global Strategy Balanced HSBC Global Strategy Dynamic HSBC Global Strategy Adventurous HSBC Global MPS Cautious
HSBC Global MPS Conservative HSBC Global MPS Balanced
HSBC Global MPS Dynamic
HSBC Global MPS Adventurous
Diversified Income Fund Diversified Growth Fund Investec Cautious Managed Fund MAP
Investec Global Multi-Asset Total Return Fund
Henderson Cautious Managed Henderson MM Absolute Return Henderson MM Distribution Henderson MM Income & Growth Henderson MM Managed Henderson MM Active Henderson Core 3 Income Henderson Core 4 Income Henderson Core 5 Income Henderson Core 6 Income
]]></page><page Index="43" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Jupiter Absolute Return
Jupiter Strategic Bond
Jupiter Distribution
Jupiter Monthly Income
Jupiter Merlin Conservative Portfolio Jupiter Merlin Income Portfolio Jupiter Merlin Balanced Portfolio Jupiter Merlin Growth Portfolio Jupiter Merlin Worldwide Portfolio
MPS Growth 1
MPS Growth 2
MPS Growth 3
MPS Growth 4
MPS Growth 5
MPS Growth 6
MPS Growth 7
MPS Growth 8
MPS Income 1
MPS Income 2
MPS Income 3
MPS Income 4
MPS Income 5
MPS Income 6
MPS Dynamic Beta 1 MPS Dynamic Beta 2 MPS Dynamic Beta 3 MPS Dynamic Beta 4 MPS Dynamic Beta 5 MPS Dynamic Beta 6 MPS Dynamic Beta 7 MPS Dynamic Beta 8
Multi-Index 3 Multi-Index 4 Multi-Index 5 Multi-Index 6 Multi-Index 7 Multi-Index Income 4 Multi-Index Income 5 Multi-Index Income 6
MPS
WSS Risk Grade 1 WSS Risk Grade 2 WSS Risk Grade 3 WSS Risk Grade 4 WSS Risk Grade 5 WSS Risk Grade 6 WSS Risk Grade 7 WSS Risk Grade 8 WSS Risk Grade 9 WSS Risk Grade 10 WSS Income 1 WSS Income 2 WSS Income 3 WSS Income 4 WSS Income 5 WSS Income 6 WSS Dynamic WSS Dynamic WSS Dynamic WSS Dynamic WSS Dynamic WSS Dynamic WSS Dynamic WSS Dynamic WSS Dynamic WSS Dynamic
Beta 1 Beta 2 Beta 3 Beta 4 Beta 5 Beta 6 Beta 7 Beta 8 Beta 9 Beta 10
WSS
]]></page><page Index="44" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                            MPS – Defensive
MPS – Cautious
MPS – Balanced
MPS – Growth
MPS – Adventurous
MPS – Strategic Income Volare Defensive Fund Volare Cautious Fund
Volare Balanced Fund
Volare Growth Fund
Volare Strategic Income Fund Sustainable MPS – Cautious Sustainable MPS – Balanced Sustainable MPS – Growth
                                Flexible Guaranteed Funds Cautious Flexible Guaranteed Funds Balanced Flexible Guaranteed Managed Growth
                                     MP3 MP4 MP5 MP6 MP7
                                                                                  Portfolios
  Premier Capital Builder Portfolio Premier Capital Builder Plus Portfolio Premier Income and Growth Portfolio Premier Income Portfolio
Premier Conservative Portfolio Premier High Income Portfolio Premier Balanced Portfolio
Premier Balanced Plus Portfolio Premier Growth Portfolio
Premier Growth Plus Portfolio Premier Dynamic Growth Portfolio
                                     Funds
      Premier Multi-Asset Conservative Growth Premier Multi-Asset Absolute Return Fund Premier Multi-Asset Distribution Fund Premier Multi-Asset Monthly Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Growth & Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Global Growth Fund Premier UK Money Market Fund
Premier Defensive Growth Fund
Premier Corporate Bond Monthly Income Fund
Premier Diversified Fund Premier Diversified Income Fund Premier Liberation IV Fund Premier Liberation V Fund Premier Liberation VI Fund Premier Liberation VII Fund
                                                                                                                                               ]]></page><page Index="45" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ PruFund Cautious
PruFund Protected Cautious PruFund Growth
PruFund Protected Growth PruFund Risk Managed 1 PruFund Risk Managed 2 PruFund Risk Managed 3 PruFund Risk Managed 4 WP Optimum Return
Risk Managed Passive 1
Risk Managed Passive 2
Risk Managed Passive 3 Risk Managed Passive 4 Risk Managed Passive 5
Risk Managed Active 1
Risk Managed Active 2
Risk Managed Active 3
Risk Managed Active 4
Risk Managed Active 5
MPS Global Growth MPS Growth
MPS Balanced
MPS Global Income MPS Income
MPS Conservative MPS Cautious IDX Growth
IDX Balanced
IDX Income
IDX Conservative
MPS Global Growth (Platform) MPS Growth (Platform)
MPS Balanced (Platform)
MPS Global Income (Platform) MPS Income (Platform)
MPS Conservative (Platform) IDX Growth (Platform)
IDX Balanced (Platform)
IDX Income (Platform)
IDX Conservative (Platform)
Cautious
Moderately Cautious
Balanced Moderately Adventurous Adventurous
Synaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:
Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation
]]></page><page Index="46" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                              QI Generation CPI+ 3
QI Generation CPI+ 4
QI Generation CPI+ 5
Quilter Cirilium Conservative Fund Quilter Cirilium Balanced Fund Quilter Cirilium Moderate Fund Quilter Cirilium Dynamic Fund Quilter Cirilium Adventurous Fund Creation Conservative
Creation Balanced
Creation Moderate
Creation Dynamic
Creation Adventurous
CRA 3 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 4 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 5 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 6 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 7 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 8 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 9 Active Managed Portfolio CRA 10 Active Managed Portfolio
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          Bespoke
   Strategy 1 Strategy 2 Strategy 3 Strategy 4 Strategy 5 Strategy 6
                  Managed Portfolios
  Cautious Balanced Income Balanced Plus Equity
Equity Plus
              RMAP Total Return RMAP Strategic Growth RMAP Enhanced Growth RMAP Strategic Income
Multi Asset
                       Global Multi Asset Portfolios
  RL GMAP Conservative RL GMAP Defensive
RL GMAP Balanced
RL GMAP Growth
RL GMAP Adventurous RL GMAP Dynamic
           Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk
]]></page><page Index="47" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                                    RSMR Rfolio Defensive RSMR Rfolio Cautious RSMR Rfolio Prudent RSMR Rfolio Balanced RSMR Rfolio Growth RSMR Rfolio Dynamic RSMR Rfolio Adventurous RSMR Rfolio Income RSMR Rfolio SRI Cautious RSMR Rfolio SRI Balanced RSMR Rfolio SRI Dynamic
                                                                                             Governed Portfolios
       RL Governed Portfolio 1 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 2 RL Governed Portfolio 3 (s) RL Governed Portfolio 4 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 5 RL Governed Portfolio 6 (s) RL Governed Portfolio 7 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 8 RL Governed Portfolio 9 (s) RL GRIP 1
RL GRIP 2 RL GRIP 3 RL GRIP 4 RL GRIP 5
                                                                                                                                                      Russell Investments Secure Portfolio Russell Investments Cautious Portfolio Russell Investments Conservative Portfolio Russell Investments Moderate Portfolio Russell Investments Balanced Portfolio Russell Investments Progressive Portfolio Russell Investments Adventurous Portfolio Russell Investments Growth Portfolio Russell Investments Aggressive Portfolio Russell Investments Aggressive Plus Russell Investments Defensive Assets Fund Russell Investments Real Assets Fund Russell Investments UK Growth
Russell Investments International Growth Russell Investments MA Growth 1
Russell Investments MA Growth 2
Russell Investments MA Growth 3
Russell Investments MA Growth 4
Russell Investments MA Growth 5
Russell Investments MA Income
                                          2 Portfolio
2 Income Portfolio 3 Portfolio
3 Income Portfolio 4 Portfolio
4 Income Portfolio 5 Portfolio
5 Income Portfolio 6 Portfolio
7 Portfolio
                            ]]></page><page Index="48" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                               Schroder MM Diversity
Schroder MM Diversity Balanced Schroder MM Diversity Income Schroder MM Diversity Tactical Schroder MM International Schroder MM UK Growth
Schroder Mixed Distribution Fund Schroder Global Multi Asset Income Schroder Dynamic Multi Asset Schroder Managed Balanced
                     Santander Atlas 3 Santander Atlas 4 Santander Atlas 5 Santander Atlas 6 Santander Atlas 7 Santander Atlas Income
                                   Pension Portfolio 1
Pension Portfolio 2 Pension Portfolio 3 Pension Portfolio A Pension Portfolio B Pension Portfolio 4 Pension Portfolio C Pension Portfolio 5 Premier Pension Portfolio 1 Premier Pension Portfolio 2 Premier Pension Portfolio 3 Premier Pension Portfolio A Premier Pension Portfolio B Premier Pension Portfolio 4 Premier Pension Portfolio C Premier Pension Portfolio 5
                                                                                                                                                                                                         Cautious
Income
Moderately Cautious Balanced
Moderately Adventurous Adventurous
Personal Injury
                                                                                    S&W Defensive Portfolio - 3
S&W Defensive Income Portfolio - 4 S&W Balanced Income Portfolio - 5 S&W Balanced Growth Portfolio - 6 S&W Growth Portfolio - 7
S&W Dynamic Growth Portfolio - 8
                Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk
]]></page><page Index="49" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ MyFolio Market I
MyFolio Market II
MyFolio Market III
MyFolio Market IV
MyFolio Market V
MyFolio Managed I
MyFolio Managed II
MyFolio Managed III
MyFolio Managed IV
MyFolio Managed V
MyFolio Multi-Manager I
MyFolio Multi-Manager II
MyFolio Multi-Manager III MyFolio Multi-Manager IV MyFolio Multi-Manager V MyFolio Managed Income MyFolio Managed Income MyFolio Managed Income MyFolio Managed Income MyFolio Managed Income MyFolio Multi-Manager Income I MyFolio Multi-Manager Income II MyFolio Multi-Manager Income III MyFolio Multi-Manager Income IV MyFolio Multi-Manager Income V
HC Verbatim Portfolio 3
HC Verbatim Portfolio 4
HC Verbatim Portfolio 5 Growth HC Verbatim Portfolio 6
HC Verbatim Portfolio 7
HC Verbatim Portfolio 5 Income
Thesis Optima Income Thesis Optima Balanced Thesis Optima Growth Thesis Collectives 1 of 7 Thesis Collectives 2 of 7 Thesis Securities 3 of 7 Thesis Securities 4 of 7 Thesis Securities 5 of 7 Thesis Securities 6 of 7 Thesis Securities 7 of 7
Commercial Freehold Fund
Vanguard LifeStrategy 20% Vanguard LifeStrategy 40% Vanguard LifeStrategy 60% Vanguard LifeStrategy 80% Vanguard LifeStrategy 100%
I II III IV V
Portfolios
]]></page><page Index="50" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                                     VDS
  VDSJH3 VDSJH4 VDSJH5 VDSJH6 VDSJH7 VDSJH8 VDS RSMR 2 VDS RSMR 3 VDS RSMR 4 VDS RSMR 5 VDS RSMR 6 VDS RSMR 7 VDS RSMR 8 VDS RSMR 9 VDS RSMR 10 VDS TCF 3 VDS TCF 4 VDS TCF 5 VDS TCF 6 VDS TCF 7 VDS TCF 8 VDS S&W 3 VDS S&W 4 VDS S&W 5 VDS S&W 6 VDS S&W 7 VDS S&W 8 VDSHR3 VDSHR4 VDSHR5 VDSHR6 VDSHR7 VDSHR8
                                                                      RSMR
       RSMR Model Portfolio 2 RSMR Model Portfolio 3 RSMR Model Portfolio 4 RSMR Model Portfolio 5 RSMR Model Portfolio 6 RSMR Model Portfolio 7 RSMR Model Portfolio 8 RSMR Model Portfolio 9 RSMR Model Portfolio 10
                                                                                               Total Clarity
      HC Verbatim Multi-Index Portfolio 3 HC Verbatim Multi-Index Portfolio 4 HC Verbatim Multi-Index Portfolio 5 HC Verbatim Multi-Index Portfolio 6
                       VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 3 VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 4 VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 5 VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 6 VitalityInvest Risk Optimiser 7
Vitality Investec Multi-Asset Moderate Vitality Investec Multi-Asset Balanced Vitality Investec Multi-Asset Growth Vitality Investec Multi-Asset Income Vitality Investec Dynamic Multi-Asset
                                                                                                            (s) These portfolios were constructed with short investment timelines (5 year) in mind.
(l) These portfolios were constructed with longer investment timelines (15 year) in mind. Otherwise Synaptic Risk Ratings assume a 10 year investment horizon. You should consult Royal London directly for further information before recommending.
About the service: Synaptic Risk Ratings are worked out by analysing the underlying asset classes within the fund or portfolio. Synaptic Software have requested asset allocation information from participating providers in a specific format aligned to the risk framework of the system. These asset classes are used by the model to determine the risk rating, a process that may result in a level of approximation though in most cases this will be insignificant. It is also possible that certain asset classes may not be represented exactly in the manner that providers would prefer.
Reasonable endeavours are made to provide accuracy and consistency, however neither participating providers nor Synaptic Software can be held responsible for any errors or omissions. No recommendation should be made solely on the basis of the Synaptic Risk Ratings, and additional research should be undertaken for any case. This service is intended for use by investment professionals only.
    ]]></page><page Index="51" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                                                            THE NEW WHITE PAPER
Enabling better outcomes in financial planning by optimising investment risk and reward using stochastic modelling
Download your free copy today
www.synaptic.co.uk/risk
How to improve your
Synaptic Modeller is now available
with 1-10 risk categories as well as 1-5, defined by Moody’s Analytic’s
investment performance
and optimise risk
asset allocations
  Features research and calculations from
Moody’s Analytics
  ]]></page><page Index="52" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                Win the protection clients you want.
Faster.
Take your advice business to the next level with Adviser Business Accelerator.
Discover tips, tools and guides to help you win more protection clients and boost your profits. All at the click of a mouse button.
Help your firm fly higher.
Visit adviserbusinessaccelerator.aviva.com
 Aviva Life Services UK Limited.
Registered in England No 2403746. Aviva, Wellington Row, York YO90 1WR.
Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Firm Reference Number 145452. TR01445 11/2018
      ]]></page></pages></Search>